<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon, occasioned by the execution of a man found guilty of murder, preached at Boston in N.E., March 11th, 1685/6 (together with the confession, last expressions, &amp; solemn warning of the murderer to all persons, especially to young men, to beware of those sins which brought him to his miserable end) / by Increase Mather ...</title>
            <author>Mather, Increase, 1639-1723.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 218 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 67 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50229</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1248</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC W19800</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">19603360</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 19603360</idno>
            <idno type="VID">109162</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50229)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 109162)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1692:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon, occasioned by the execution of a man found guilty of murder, preached at Boston in N.E., March 11th, 1685/6 (together with the confession, last expressions, &amp; solemn warning of the murderer to all persons, especially to young men, to beware of those sins which brought him to his miserable end) / by Increase Mather ...</title>
                  <author>Mather, Increase, 1639-1723.</author>
                  <author>Moodey, Joshua, 1633?-1697. Exhortation to a condemned malefactor.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[4], 124 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R.P., sold by J. Brunning ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Boston :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Special t.p.: The call of the Gospel applyed unto all men in general and vnto a condemned malefactor in particular.</note>
                  <note>Includes Joshua Moodey's An exhortation to a condemned malefactor, which has special t.p.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, with print show-through and some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Morgan, James, d. 1686.</term>
               <term>Murder --  Biblical teaching --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Capital punishment --  Religious aspects --  Christianity --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:109162:1"/>
                  <p>A SERMON Occaſioned by the EXECUTION of a man found Guilty of MURDER</p>
                  <p>Preached at Boſton in N. E. <hi>March 11th</hi> 1685 / 6</p>
                  <p>(Together with the <hi>Confeſſion,</hi> Laſt <hi>Expreſſions,</hi> &amp; ſolemn <hi>Warning</hi> of that Murderer to all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; <hi>eſpecially</hi> to <hi>Young</hi> men, to beware of <hi>thoſe</hi> Sins which brought him to his <hi>miſerable End.</hi>)</p>
                  <p>By <hi>INCREASE MATHER,</hi> Teacher of Church of CHRIST.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>SECOND EDITION.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Deut. 19. 20. 21.</bibl>
And thoſe which remain ſhall hear and fear, and ſhall henceforth commit no more any ſuch <hi>Evil</hi> among you.</q>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 21.</bibl>
And thine eye ſhall not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ity, but <hi>Life</hi> ſhall go for <hi>Life,</hi> Eye for Eye, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Prov. 28. 17.</bibl>
A man that doth violence to the blood of any perſon, ſhall flee to the pit, let no man ſtay him.</q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Boſton,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. P.</hi> Sold by <hi>J. Brunning</hi> Book-ſeller, at his Shop at the Corner of the <hi>Priſon-Lane</hi> next the <hi>Exchange.</hi> Anno 1687.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:109162:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:109162:2"/>
                  <head>To the Reader<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe <hi>Sermons</hi> emitted herewith (both that of <hi>mine,</hi> and that alſo delivered by my <hi>Son</hi>) are publiſhed to gratify ſome, who have been perhaps too importunately deſirous to have it ſo. The Perſon that <hi>occaſioned</hi> the Preaching of them is now <hi>uncapable</hi> of receiving Benefit by them. Whether they <hi>were</hi> bleſſed for any ſaving Good to his Soul, the Lord knowes; and it become<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> us to leave <hi>Secret things</hi> with GOD. <hi>Late Repentance is ſeldom true<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> There are who think that many who periſhed in the <hi>Floud,</hi> were by means of that <hi>Judgment,</hi> brought to <hi>true Repentance<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> To this ſenſe ſome interpret that Scripure, <hi>1. Pet. 4. 6.</hi> otherwiſe we read not of more than <hi>one</hi> man in all the <hi>Book of God,</hi> that was brought home to Chriſt but a few hours before his death. Nevertheleſs, the Lord knows how to make the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful death (as to his <hi>Body</hi>) of a great Sinner, to occaſion the <hi>Converſion</hi> and <hi>Salvation</hi> of many <hi>Souls.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If any be awakned by this ſad <hi>Example,</hi> to turn from thoſe ſins which proved the ruin of a miſerable
<pb facs="tcp:109162:3"/>
man: and if theſe <hi>Sermons</hi> (ſuch as they are) may be a meanes to further the work of <hi>Repentance towards God, &amp; Faith in our Lord Jeſus Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> in <hi>any</hi> that ſhall read them; the Deſign of this <hi>Publication</hi> will be attained.</p>
                  <p>As for the <hi>Exhortation</hi> annexed to theſe Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, it was delivered on the ſame day with that <hi>Sermon</hi> preached by my <hi>Son,</hi> (whom the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus hath fixed in the <hi>ſame Church</hi> to which I am related) but in the <hi>after part</hi> of the day. The Reverend and worthy Author has not had time to tranſcribe his <hi>whole</hi> Sermon, only that <hi>part</hi> of it which concerned the then Condemned <hi>Malefactor.</hi> Many have earneſtly deſired that it might in this way be made publick. And becauſe it is moſt ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able that the <hi>Beſt</hi> ſhould come <hi>laſt,</hi> it is in this Publication <hi>added</hi> to the other Sermons <hi>The</hi> Lord <hi>proſper his Truth, by whomſoever ſpoken or written for the Good of Souls.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Increaſe mather<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>March 26. 1686.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:109162:3"/>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>NUMB. XXXV. 16.</hi>
                        </bibl> And if he ſmite him with an Inſtrument of Iron (ſo that he die) he is a <hi>Murderer,</hi> the <hi>Murderer</hi> ſhall ſurely be <hi>put to DEATH.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>A Great part of this <hi>Chapter</hi> is taken up in declaring who ſhould have benefit by <hi>the City of Refuge;</hi> and who might <hi>not</hi> expect advantage thereby. There are Two ſorts of <hi>Man-ſlayers,</hi> (1) One may kill his Neighbour <hi>Accidentally,</hi> tho he had <hi>no deſign</hi> of <hi>Hurt to</hi> him, nor any <hi>Diſpleaſure againſt</hi> him. The <hi>City of Refuge</hi> was for <hi>ſuch.</hi> (2.) A Man may in <hi>Hatred</hi> or in <hi>Paſſion</hi> kill another, and <hi>then</hi> then the <hi>City of Refuge</hi> could <hi>not</hi> ſecure or ſave him from the <hi>hand of Juſtice;</hi> To intimate which is the Scope of the Words which have been now read wherein we have <hi>two</hi> things, 1. A <hi>Criminal</hi> 2. The <hi>Puniſhment</hi> to be <hi>inflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> on ſuch a Criminal.</p>
                  <p>1. <hi>A</hi> Criminal, <hi>He is a Murderer:</hi> There are <hi>three</hi> Particulars mention'd, which if they <hi>concur</hi> the Perſon is <hi>guilty</hi> of <hi>Murder:</hi> 1. If he <hi>ſmites</hi> another man, <hi>h. e.</hi> if he does ſo, <hi>not accidentally</hi> but <hi>deſignedly.</hi> 2. If the <hi>Inſtrument</hi> which he ſmites him with be of <hi>Iron,</hi> that makes the Murder to be the more <hi>evident.</hi> In the Verſes following it is added, That <hi>if he ſmite him</hi> mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:109162:4"/>
                     <hi>with a Stone or with Wood, he ſhall be account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Murderer.</hi> The <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Writers tell us, <note n="(a)" place="margin">v. Grotium &amp; Ainſworth <hi>in</hi> loc.</note> That if a man were ſlain, there was diligent en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry made concerning the <hi>Inſtrument,</hi> whereby he was killed: If it was with a <hi>Stone</hi> or with <hi>Wood,</hi> they examin'd whether the ſtone or wood were of that <hi>Bigneſs</hi> as that the <hi>dead man</hi> might probably receive his Deaths Wound thereby: But (they ſay) If it were with an Inſtrument of <hi>Iron,</hi> no enquiry was made as to the <hi>greatneſs</hi> of it, becauſe the leaſt nail of <hi>Iron</hi> might eaſily kill. And it is to be preſumed, that a man will not ſtrike another with an <hi>Inſtrument of Iron,</hi> except <hi>Blood</hi> and <hi>Murder</hi> be in his Heart. 3. If the Wound prove <hi>mortal,</hi> then the Striker is <hi>guilty</hi> of <hi>Murder.</hi> Tho a man ſhould ſmite another, and that with an Inſtrument of Iron, if Death does not follow, he is not guilty of that <hi>high de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree</hi> of Murder which the Text ſpeakes of; but if he ſmite his Neighbour ſo that he <hi>dye,</hi> then he is a <hi>Murderer.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Here is the <hi>Puniſhment to be inflicted</hi> on ſuch a Criminal. <hi>The Murderer ſhall ſurely be put to death.</hi> Only Gods <hi>Order</hi> was to be obſerved; he was to be put to death in a <hi>Judiciary way.</hi> Amongſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> the <hi>Avenger of blood</hi> was to be the <hi>Executioner;</hi> as the <hi>19th ver.</hi> in this <hi>chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> ſhews, where it is ſaid, that <hi>the Avenger of blood himſelf ſhall ſlay the Murderer.</hi> The <hi>Hebrew</hi> word for the <hi>Avenger pf bloud</hi> is GOEL, which
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:109162:4"/>
is ſometimes tranſlated a <hi>Redeemer:</hi> The word properly ſignifyes one that is <hi>near a kin.</hi> The <hi>next</hi> Kinſman had right to <hi>Redeem,</hi> he alſo was to be the <hi>Avenger of blood:</hi> Only before Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion could be done the Magiſtrate was to paſs a <hi>Judgment.</hi> The Man-ſlayer was ſent from the City of Refuge whither he fled, unto the place where the Fact was done, <hi>there</hi> to have his Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al. If the Magiſtrates of that Place found him <hi>not guilty,</hi> he was returned to the <hi>City of Refuge,</hi> there to be in ſafety till the death of the <hi>High Prieſt,</hi> and then to be ſet at Liberty: But if he was found <hi>Guilty</hi> of Murder, he was to be put to death publickly by the hand of Juſtice.</p>
                  <p>The DOCTRINE then before us, as ſuited to the preſent Occaſion is,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That</hi> Murder <hi>is a Sin ſo great &amp; heinous, as that whoever ſhall be found Guilty of it, muſt be put to death by the hand of publick Juſtice.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Explication and Confirmation of this Doctrin may be ſet before us in 3 <hi>Propoſitions.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Prop.</hi> 1. Murder, <hi>is when a man does voluntarily</hi> &amp; unjuſtly <hi>take away the Life of another perſon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>So that there are 3 Things implied in <hi>Murder<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>1. <hi>The Object ſlain muſt be one of</hi> Man-kind. To take away the Life of <hi>another</hi> Creature is <hi>not</hi> Murder. The <hi>Sixth</hi> Commandment ſaith, <hi>Ye ſhall not kill.</hi> The <hi>Hebrew</hi> words are, LOT<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>RT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ZACH, <hi>i. e. Thou ſhalt not Murder.</hi> It was a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ain Opinion of the <hi>Manachees,</hi> whom <hi>Auſtin</hi>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:109162:5"/>
That the Life of <hi>no</hi> Creature might be taken away becauſe the Commandment of God ſaith, <hi>Thou ſhalt not kill.</hi> God has given ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs leave to all the Sons of <hi>Noah,</hi> i. e., to <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind,</hi> that they ſhould take away the Lives of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther creatures as they ſhould ſee cauſe; only <hi>Man</hi> being a more Divine Creature, <hi>his</hi> Life is to be Sacred: it may not be medled with, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept in caſes where the Great &amp; Soveraign <hi>God,</hi> who has an abſolute power of Life and Death, hath appointed.</p>
                  <p>2. <hi>Capital Murder is wilful.</hi> There is a differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence between Murder and <hi>caſual Homicide,</hi> or accidental <hi>Manſlaughter.</hi> If a man ſhoots an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, or throws a ſtone, or the like, not think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that any one will be hurt thereby; in caſe it ſhould happen to kill a man, it is not Murder. If he did it ignorantly, unawares, and no way <hi>ſought the harm</hi> of the ſlain man, he is not to be puniſhed as a Murderer. This we ſee in the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text,</hi> ver. 15. <hi>to</hi> 26. The <hi>City of Refuge</hi> was for <hi>ſuch</hi> an one; <hi>Deut. 19. 4. 5. And this is the caſe of the ſlayer which ſhall flee thither, that he may live: whoſoever killeth his neighbour ignorantly, whom he hated</hi> not <hi>in time paſt; as when a man goes into the Wood with his neighbour to hew wood, and his hand fetcheth a ſtroke with the Ax, to cut down the tree, and the head ſlippeth from the helve, &amp; lights upon his neighbour that he die, he ſhall flee unto one of thoſe cities and live.</hi> Not but that a man may
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:109162:5"/>
be guilty of Murdering his Neighbour, tho he did not intend to <hi>kill</hi> him; <hi>namely,</hi> If he did ſmite him in <hi>Anger,</hi> or intend to <hi>harm</hi> him, as the expreſſion is in the 23. <hi>ver.</hi> of this Chapter. And it is here expreſly declared, not only that he who ſhall <hi>lye in wait,</hi> or watch for an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to deſtroy his Neighbour, or that did <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly hate him</hi> ſhall be judged a Murderer, but if he <hi>ſmite him in emnity that he</hi> dy, <hi>v. 21. i. e.</hi> in an <hi>hoſtile</hi> way: tho he had no quarrel with him before, if he <hi>fall out</hi> with him, and in his <hi>paſſion</hi> ſmite him a <hi>mortal</hi> Blow, he hath <hi>murdered</hi> his Neighbour, and is guilty of death. This is <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptous</hi> Murder, the <hi>heart</hi> was in it, nor can it be ſaid to be done <hi>ignorantly.</hi> There is another clear Scripture which proves, that if perſons <hi>fall out,</hi> and in the <hi>ſtrife</hi> one ſhall ſtrike the other a <hi>deadly blow, life ſhall go for life.</hi> Ex. 21. 14, 21, 22</p>
                  <p>But then <hi>3dly.</hi> In Murder, the Life of a man is taken away <hi>unjuſtly.</hi> In <hi>ſome</hi> caſes it is <hi>lawful</hi> to take away the Life of another. Yea, Matters may be ſo circumſtanced, as it would be a great ſin <hi>not</hi> to do it. There are <hi>Three</hi> caſes wherein the <hi>Life</hi> of a man may be taken away, and yet no <hi>Sin,</hi> no Murder committed.</p>
                  <p>1. In caſe of a <hi>Juſt War.</hi> There is a great dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between blood ſhed in <hi>war,</hi> and in a time of <hi>Peace. Joab</hi> was guilty of Murder, becauſe he <hi>ſhed the blood of War in</hi> peace. 1. <hi>King</hi> 2. 5<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> had he killed <hi>Abner &amp; Amaſa</hi> in the <hi>war</hi>-time, before
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:109162:6"/>
                     <hi>David</hi> had made <hi>peace</hi> with him, he had not bin guilty of Murder; but becauſe he ſhed blood after a peace was concluded, he was a Murderer. Somtimes in War, they that take away lives, do an acceptable ſervice to God. <hi>Abigal</hi> told <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> that God would certainly bleſs, him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he <hi>fought the Battles of the Lord.</hi> 1. Sam. 25. 28. And we know that <hi>Abraham</hi> was bleſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, after he returned from the <hi>Slaughter of the Kings</hi> with whom he had a juſt war. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. 2. In theſe caſes, the <hi>not</hi> ſhedding of blood may poſſibly expoſe to a <hi>Curſe.</hi> Jer. 48. 10 <hi>Curſed be he that does the work of the Lord deceitfully, and curſed be he that</hi> keeps back his ſword from <hi>blood.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>2. They that <hi>are in Civil Authority, may</hi> and <hi>ought to take away the Lives of men, that ſhall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit Crimes, by the Law of God worthy of Death.</hi> The Apoſtle therefore ſaith concerning the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, <hi>He is the miniſter of God to thee for good, but if thou do that which is</hi> evil, <hi>be afraid, for he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eareth not the ſword in vain; for he is the miniſter of God; a Revenger to execute wrath upon him that does</hi> Evil. <hi>Rom. 13 4. Private</hi> Reveng is <hi>evil,</hi> but <hi>publick Revenge</hi> on thoſe that violate the Laws of God, is <hi>good.</hi> The <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> is God's <hi>Vice-gerent.</hi> As none can <hi>give</hi> life but God; ſo none may <hi>take it away,</hi> but God, or <hi>ſuch</hi> as He has <hi>appointed.</hi> It is their work to ſee that the Lives of men be <hi>taken from</hi> them, when God has ſaid, <hi>that they ſhall ſurely be put to death.</hi> Hence
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:109162:6"/>
                     <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks, as in <hi>Pſal. 101. 8. I will early de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy all the wicked of the land, that I may cut off all the wicked Doers from the City of the Lord.</hi> God had put the <hi>Sword</hi> into his hand for that <hi>end,</hi> that ſo he might clear the <hi>Land</hi> of <hi>Malefact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors,</hi> who were worthy of Death, and he was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to ſee Juſtice done. But <hi>private</hi> Perſons are not to arrogate to themſelves that which is the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi>'s proper work. Men muſt have <hi>lawful Authority</hi> for what they do; <hi>elſe</hi> in ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing away Life, they become guilty of Murder. Suppoſe a perſon to have committed never ſuch Capital Crimes, if a <hi>private</hi> perſon, or one that has no <hi>Legal Authority</hi> ſhall take away his Life, he is guilty of Murder. Except</p>
                  <p>3. <hi>In caſe of a man's own juſt</hi> Defence. <hi>So</hi> a <hi>private</hi> perſon <hi>may</hi> take away the life of another<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The light of Nature teaches men <hi>Self-Preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> If a Murderer aſſault him, he may <hi>kill</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than be killed. We cannot ſay that <hi>Abner</hi> was guilty of Murder when he ſlew <hi>Aſahal</hi> in his <hi>own defence.</hi> 
                     <note n="(b)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Alſted,</hi> Theol. Caſ. Cap. 15. p. 350.</note> If a man be, coutrary to Juſtice, invaded or ſet upon by another in an <hi>hoſtile</hi> manner, and there he no other way for him to preſerve his own life, but by <hi>killing</hi> the <hi>Aſſailant;</hi> the Law of Nature, and of all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons acquit him from the guilt of <hi>Murder.</hi> But he that has ſhed blood <hi>cauſleſs,</hi> or that has <hi>aven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged himſelf,</hi> is a Murderer. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 25. 31.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:109162:7"/>Propoſ. 2. <hi>Murder is an exceeding great Sin.</hi> It's an expreſſion in the Scriptures, <hi>he is as if he</hi> ſlew <hi>a man,</hi> Iſa. 66. 3. Implying that to <hi>ſlay</hi> a man is a thing moſt horrid &amp; <hi>hateful:</hi> it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the <hi>greateſt</hi> Sin againſt the <hi>2nd</hi> Table of the Moral Law, and is therefore ſet in the <hi>firſt</hi> place, amongſt negative Precepts therein. God forbids the greateſt ſin in the <hi>firſt place.</hi> It is a <hi>Crying</hi> Sin: The Lord ſaid to <hi>Cain. The</hi> voice <hi>of thy brothers blood</hi> cryeth <hi>to me from the ground, Gen.</hi> 4. 10. In the Original, the word is in the <hi>Plural</hi> Number, the voice of thy brothers <hi>bloods.</hi> Every drop of <hi>Abel</hi>'s blood, had as it were a <hi>voice,</hi> a <hi>tongue</hi> in it, crying for vengeance againſt his brother that had murdered him. But that This is a grievous ſin is manifeſt: 1. <hi>In that it is a moſt</hi> unnatural <hi>thing.</hi> Creatures of the <hi>ſame kind</hi> are not wont to deſtroy <hi>one another.</hi> Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raliſts obſerve concerning Wolves, that though they be <hi>cruel</hi> creatures, they will never kill <hi>one another:</hi> therefore if Men do ſo they are worſe than <hi>Wolves</hi> &amp; <hi>Tygers:</hi> ſo that Murder is an <hi>unnatural</hi> and a <hi>monſtrous</hi> Wickedneſs. 2. <hi>The</hi> Vengeance <hi>which is wont to follow this Sin, proves that it is an</hi> horrid <hi>and</hi> hainous <hi>Transgreſſion.</hi> There is a peculiar <hi>Vengeance</hi> that does purſue <hi>this</hi> ſin at the heels of it. The <hi>Gentiles</hi> had the motion of <hi>this</hi> fix'd in their minde: hence thoſe <hi>Barbarians</hi> could ſay, <hi>No doubt this man is a</hi> murderer, <hi>whom tho' he eſcaped the ſeas, yet</hi> Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:109162:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <hi>ſuffereth not to live,</hi> Act. 21. 4. <note n="‖" place="margin">Ethnici <hi>Dicen</hi> tanquam deam &amp; filiam <hi>Jovis</hi> co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebant in <hi>Plut.</hi> l. de ſer a vindict. <hi>Dice</hi> daemon dicitur<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </note> The Heathen eſteemed [<hi>dike</hi>] (the word there uſed for <hi>Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance</hi>) as a <hi>Deity</hi> that would not ſuffer great Sinners, and in ſpecial <hi>Murderers</hi> to go unpun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhed. <hi>Temporal</hi> Vengeance purſueth this Sin. Hence they that have been guilty of it, ſeldom live long in quiet. <hi>Bloody and deceitful men ſhall not live out half their days.</hi> Pſal. 55. 23. Either they are cut off by the Sword of Civil Juſtice, or if their Murders happen to be undiſcovered, a ſecret Curſe of God follows them: Often times they are themſelvs Murdered, as both Divine and humane Records do abundantly declare. Nay, tho men ſhould truly <hi>repent</hi> of this ſin, and are then thro' the Merit of Chriſt ſaved from <hi>everlaſting</hi> Puniſhment, yet not from <hi>Temporal</hi> Judgment. I cannot tell whether ever any man that was found guilty of this ſin, did eſcape Temporal Judgment at laſt. When <hi>David</hi> had cauſed <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah</hi> to be Murdered, he did repent of it moſt deeply and unfeignedly, yet God pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed him ſeverely as to outward Judgments; he ſaw but few comfortable dayes after that, the <hi>Sword never departed from his houſe.</hi> I have read of a man that fought a <hi>Duel,</hi> and murder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Adverſary, who afterwards was very pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent, and for ſeveral years an eminent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of exemplary piety; but at laſt he was
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:109162:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <hi>ſmitten</hi> by the immediate hand of God, ſo as that <hi>Blood</hi> guſhed out of all the paſſages of his Body, and he dyed ſuddenly. The Relator notes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, that tho' God forgave him as to <hi>eternal,</hi> yet not as to <hi>temporal</hi> Vengeance. But eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Spiritnal</hi> Vengeance follows this Sin: The Murderers Soul is filled with helliſh horrour of heart; ſo that he is as it were Damned above ground, and in hell whilſt he is yet alive. The <hi>avenger of blood purſues his ſoul.</hi> Murderers have confeſſed, that as ſoon as ever they had commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the bloody fact, they felt the flames of Hell fire in their conſciences: and this we ſee in <hi>Cain:</hi> therefore after he had murdered his Brother, he cried and roared out, that his ſin was great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than could be forgiven, his puniſhment great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than could be endured. And ſome think that the <hi>mark</hi> which the Lord ſet upon <hi>Cain,</hi> was a gaſtly guilty <hi>Countenance,</hi> that he had <hi>Hell &amp; Horror</hi> in his <hi>countenance,</hi> as well as in his <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</hi> And without <hi>Repentance,</hi> everlaſting ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance will follow that Sin. Its ſaid, <hi>No murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer has eternal life.</hi> 1. Joh. 3. 15. that is, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out true Repentance. And if he has not etern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al <hi>life,</hi> then I am ſure he has eternal <hi>death</hi> and Damnation. If the Murderer were only to have the life of his <hi>body</hi> taken from him, tho' in a painful, ſhameful &amp; accurſed way, that were a light matter; but there is an <hi>eternal</hi> Curſe, a weight of everlaſting vengeance, heavier than Mountains
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:109162:8"/>
of <hi>Lead,</hi> that ſhall preſs his Soul to <hi>death,</hi> world without <hi>end.</hi> Murder then is a <hi>fearful ſin.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Propoſ. 3. <hi>The Murderer is to be put to death by the hand of Publick Juſtice.</hi> And this confirms the former Propoſitions concerning the <hi>greatneſs</hi> of this Sin. <hi>Men</hi> may not pardon or remit the Puniſhment of that Sin. Among the <hi>Jews</hi> there was no <hi>City of Refuge</hi> for a wicked or <hi>wilful man-ſlayer;</hi> and it is ſaid in the 31 verſe of this Chapter, <hi>You ſhall take</hi> no <hi>ſatisfaction for the</hi> life <hi>of a</hi> Murderer <hi>which is</hi> guilty <hi>of</hi> death, <hi>but he ſhall ſurely be put to</hi> death. <hi>This</hi> ſin ſhall not be ſatisfyed for, with any other puniſhment, but the <hi>death</hi> of the Murderer. There are <hi>ſome</hi> Crimes, that other puniſhment <hi>leſs</hi> than Death may be accepted of, as a Compenſation for the wrong done; either by ſome Mulct or Fine in their <hi>Eſtates,</hi> or ſome other Coporal Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment leſs than death: but in caſe of <hi>Murder,</hi> no Fine or Impriſonment, or Baniſhment, or corporal puniſhment leſs than <hi>death</hi> can be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted; <hi>You ſhall take</hi> no ſatisfaction <hi>for the life of a murderer.</hi> And indeed <hi>Equity</hi> requires this; by the law of Retaliation, it is meet that men ſhould be done <hi>unto,</hi> as they have <hi>done</hi> to <hi>others;</hi> and that as limb ſhould go for limb, ſo <hi>Life</hi> for <hi>Life.</hi> But beſides that, there are <hi>two</hi> Reaſons mentioned in the Scripture, why the Murderer muſt be put to Death.</p>
                  <p>Reaſ. 1. <hi>That ſo the</hi> Land <hi>where the murder is
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:109162:9"/>
committed, may be purged from the guilt of</hi> Blood. For Murder is ſuch a ſin as does pollute the very <hi>Land</hi> where it is done; not only the <hi>perſon</hi> that has ſhed blood is polluted thereby, but the whole <hi>Land</hi> lies under Pollution until ſuch time as Juſtice is done upon the Murderer. Thus in the 33. <hi>v.</hi> of this Chapter, this is given as the Reaſon why no Satisfaction might be taken for the life of a Murderer; <hi>ſo ſhall ye not</hi> pollute <hi>the</hi> land <hi>wherein you are; for</hi> blood it defileth <hi>the</hi> land, <hi>and the land cannot be cleanſed of the blood that is ſhed</hi> therein, <hi>but by the</hi> blood <hi>of</hi> him <hi>that ſhed it.</hi> One Murder <hi>unpuniſhed,</hi> may bring guilt &amp; a curſe upon the whole Land, that all the Inhabitants of the Land ſhall ſuffer for it; So that <hi>Mercy</hi> to a <hi>Murderer</hi> is <hi>Cruelty</hi> to a <hi>Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi> Therefore it is ſaid concerning the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer, <hi>Thine eye ſhall</hi> not pity <hi>him but thou ſhalt put away the guilt of innocent blood from</hi> Iſrael, <hi>that it may go well with thee.</hi> If the Murderer be not puniſhed it may go ill with the Whole, <hi>all</hi> may fare the worſe for it; if the ſin be not duly puniſhed, there is a partaking in the guilt of it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
                  <p>Reaſ. 2. <hi>Becauſe man is made in the</hi> Image <hi>of God.</hi> This reaſon is mentioned <hi>Gen.</hi> 9. 6. <hi>Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſheddeth mans blood, by man</hi> (i. e. by ſome man in <hi>Authority,</hi> proceeding in an orderly way of <hi>Judicature,</hi> as the Hebrew Expoſitors do rightly interpret the words) <hi>ſhall his blood be ſhed, for in the</hi> Image of God <hi>made. He him.</hi>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:109162:9"/>
Hence there is Sacrilegious Guilt in this Sin. Amongſt the <hi>Romans</hi> 
                     <note n="(d)" place="margin">Sueton, in Tiber. cap. 58.</note> if a man did but <hi>ſtrike</hi> his Servant near the place where one of their Emperours lay, he was to dye for it, becauſe that was look'd upon as an affront put upon his <hi>Imperial Majeſty;</hi> ſo he that ſhall <hi>kill a man</hi> that is made after the Image of God, puts a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt upon the <hi>DIVINE</hi> Majeſty, there is Treaſon againſt God contained in the bloody Bowels of this Sin. Upon this account it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed a greater ſin to kill a <hi>good</hi> man that has the Image of God renewed in him, than to kill a <hi>wicked man.</hi> Nevertheleſs, <hi>that</hi> alſo is a <hi>Capital</hi> Crime; for <hi>all</hi> men have ſomething <note n="(e)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Calvin. Rivet. &amp; Pareus</hi> in <hi>Gen.</hi> 9. 6.</note> of Gods <hi>Image</hi> remaining in them: not only in that every man has an immortal ſoul, and is in that reſpect more like the <hi>immortal God</hi> than any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther creature in the world, and in that men have a dominion over the Creatures, which is one part of Gods Image; on that account does the Apoſtle ſay, that <hi>Man is the</hi> Image <hi>and Glory of God.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11, 7. But alſo, in that the <hi>Law</hi> is written in the hearts of men by <hi>Nature;</hi> 
                     <note n="(f)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Ames. Theol. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 14.</note> though God has executed ſpiritual death upon Mankind for <hi>Adam</hi>'s Apoſtaſy, after a dreadful manner, yet he has moderated that puniſhment; hence men in a <hi>natural</hi> eſtate, yet cloſe with
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:109162:10"/>
ſome <hi>practical</hi> principles of Piety &amp; Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſs; as That <hi>God ought to be worſhiped,</hi> that <hi>Men ſhould</hi> do <hi>as they would be done</hi> by: and the like: and many <hi>natural men,</hi> yet have an <hi>image</hi> of <hi>Vortue;</hi> they have ſomething like Grace, a ſhadow of it, they hate <hi>flagitious</hi> Crimes, and approve of a morally honeſt Converſation; Theſe things ſhew that there are ſome <hi>Remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> of the Image of God in men: therefore he that ſhall <hi>murder ſuch</hi> a creature is <hi>worthy of death.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But thus for the <hi>Doctrinal</hi> handling of the Truth before us. I proceed to make ſome <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication.</hi> (1.) By way of <hi>Information.</hi> (2.) For <hi>Exhortation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Infor. 1. <hi>This Doctrin</hi> juſtifyeth <hi>the</hi> Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity <hi>here, in reſpect of the</hi> Sentence <hi>of</hi> Death <hi>which has been paſſed on the</hi> Murderer, <hi>who is this day to be</hi> Executed. <hi>There</hi> is a man ſtanding before the Lord, and among His people this day, who has done <hi>juſt</hi> as my Text expreſſeth, he hath <hi>ſmitten</hi> his Neighbour, and that <hi>with an Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of lorn</hi> too, with a cruel <hi>Spit</hi> made of <hi>Iron;</hi> the thing proved by ſeveral Witneſſes, and the man that was hurt <hi>dyed</hi> of <hi>that</hi> wound, therfore he that has ſmitten him is a <hi>Murderer,</hi> and muſt ſurely be put to death. Tho' for a long time he denied it, nevertheleſs ſince his Condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he has acknowledged it; and yeſterday he confeſſed to me, that he had in his Rage mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered the man, whoſe death and blood has bin
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:109162:10"/>
laid to his Charge; he told me that the other gave him ſome ill language whereby he was provoked, and that he ſaid to him, <hi>if he came within the</hi> door, <hi>he would run the</hi> Spit <hi>into his Bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els;</hi> and he <hi>was</hi> as wicked as he <hi>ſaid</hi> he would be, ſo that he is <hi>guilty of Murder.</hi> Therefore none ought to blame Thoſe in Authority for cauſing the Murderer to <hi>be put to death;</hi> Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to <hi>God,</hi> &amp; to the <hi>People</hi> under their Charge, and to their own Souls alſo, has <hi>neceſſitated</hi> them to do what they have done in this matter. Let every one remember that Scripture, <hi>Prov.</hi> 28. 17. <hi>A man that doth violence to the</hi> blood <hi>of any perſon, ſhall flee to the</hi> Pit, <hi>let</hi> no <hi>man</hi> ſtay <hi>him;</hi> if he has <hi>ſhed blood,</hi> to the Pit let him go, and <hi>flee</hi> thither; let all convenient <hi>Speed</hi> be uſed in the Execution of Juſtice, that ſo the Land may be cleared from blood, and let no man in Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <hi>ſtay</hi> him, let no private perſon <hi>ſolicit</hi> for him. But let us be <hi>thankful</hi> to God, that we are under <hi>ſuch</hi> Magiſtrates as will <hi>do Juſtice,</hi> and <hi>Execute Judgment,</hi> &amp; puniſh Sin according as the Word of God requires that it ſhould be done.</p>
                  <p>Infor. 2. <hi>Hence,</hi> Thoſe <hi>Things which have a tendency</hi> to, <hi>and a degree</hi> of Murder <hi>in them, muſt needs be evil. e. g.</hi> Raſh ſinful <hi>Anger</hi> is an evil thing, Murder <hi>begins</hi> there. 'Twas ſaid of thoſe Brethren in Iniquity, <hi>Simeon &amp; Levi,</hi> That <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of</hi> Cruelty <hi>were in their habitations, for in their</hi> Anger <hi>they</hi> ſlew <hi>a man, curſed be their</hi>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:109162:11"/>
wrath <hi>for it was</hi> cruel. <hi>Gen.</hi> 49. 5. 6. And ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Lord Jeſus Chriſt in His Expoſition of the <hi>Sixth Commandment,</hi> ſhews, that <hi>raſh</hi> Anger is a <hi>degree</hi> of <hi>Murder,</hi> Mat. 5. 21, 22. <hi>You have heard that it was ſaid by them of old time, Ye ſhall not</hi> kill, <hi>and whoſoever ſhall kill, ſhall be in danger of the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but I ſay unto you, that whoſoever is</hi> angry <hi>with his brother without a cauſe ſhall be in danger of the Judgment.</hi> There is <hi>Man</hi>'s Judgment-ſeat, and GOD's Judgment-ſeat: Murder makes a man be in danger of the former, ſinful <hi>Anger</hi> expoſes him to the latter. Not that <hi>all</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger is ſinful<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> there is an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nger that is <hi>good;</hi> when a man is angry in <hi>God</hi>'s cauſe, moved with zeal &amp; indignation becauſe <hi>God</hi> is <hi>diſhonoured;</hi> that's very good<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and a man may <hi>ſometimes</hi> be angry in his <hi>own</hi> cauſe too and yet not ſin. <hi>Be angry and ſin not.</hi> But when men are angry <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out</hi> a juſt cauſe, <hi>that</hi>'s Evil. When they are an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry more than they have cauſe for, that they are all in a flame for a meer triſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, when (as one well expreſſes it) a man ſhall <hi>ſuffer the</hi> 
                     <note n="(g)" place="margin">
                        <hi>v. M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi> C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>ocks Supplement. cap. 9. p. 368.</note> 
                     <hi>Beco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> of his ſoul to be ſit all on</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ire <hi>at the landing of every ſmall</hi> Boat, <hi>that</hi>'s a fooliſh and evil thing; or when men ſhall be angry longer than they ought to be; an <hi>implacable</hi> ſpirit, is a <hi>vile</hi> mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous ſpirit. <hi>Anger</hi> reſts <hi>in the boſom of ſools.</hi> Sinful Anger is <hi>poyſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> which as ſoon as ever a man has taken it into his mouth, he ſhall ſpit it
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:109162:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
out again. And when Anger ſhall break out into <hi>Curſes</hi> and wicked Imprecations, thats wicked Anger. This condemned man, that ſtands here, confeſſes, that he was wont in his <hi>paſſion</hi> to <hi>curſe</hi> all near him. He murdered many a man with his bloody <hi>tongue,</hi> before he was left of God to murder any with his <hi>hand.</hi> His <hi>mouth was full of</hi> Curſing &amp; <hi>Bitterneſs,</hi> before he ſhed blood. And when men in their Rarge imprecate &amp; curſe <hi>themſelvs,</hi> its a very evil thing: there are ſome that will ſay, <hi>They wiſh they might be hang'd,</hi> if ſuch a thing be ſo, and many times the <hi>righteous Judgment of God</hi> brings <hi>that</hi> very evil upon 'em<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
                  <p>There is a Printed Relation concerning <note n="(h)" place="margin">Sr. <hi>Gerv. Elways.</hi> mention'd by Mr. <hi>Howel</hi> in his Londinop. &amp; by Mr. <hi>Ball,</hi> of the power of Godlineſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> l. 4. c. 3. p. 329. &amp; by Mr. <hi>Leigh</hi> in his <hi>Body of Divinity<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi> Lib. 4. Cap. 16. P. 445.</note> a Perſon of Quality that was hang'd for a Crime laid to his charge, and when he came to <hi>dye,</hi> he confeſſed, that he had been much addicted to that ſinful Recreation of <hi>Card-Playing,</hi> and that many times when the Game went otherwiſe than he wiſh'd for, he would in his <hi>paſſion,</hi> wiſh that he might he <hi>hang'd</hi> if it were ſo, and once he wiſh'd he might be hang'd if ever he play'd agen; and therefore (ſaid he) God is juſt in bringing me to ſuch a death as this. And when Anger ſhall break out into <hi>Blows,</hi> Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reling, and <hi>Fighting</hi> between Neighbours that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:109162:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ought to live in peace, there is great Evil in it. This miſerable creature before us, acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that it was ſo with him. In his mad <hi>paſſions</hi> he car'd not who he did <hi>ſtrike</hi> or <hi>hurt.</hi> It is not good for them that have lawful power to ſtrike others, to do it in <hi>paſſion.</hi> It is not good for Parents to ſtrike their children, or Maſters their Servants, or School-maſters their Scholars in heat of Anger, le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t they become guilty of break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>ſixth Commandment.</hi> A moral <hi>Heathen,</hi> when his ſervant had committed a fault that greatly in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed him, ſaid to him, <hi>If I were not</hi> angry <hi>with the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, I would ſtrike thee, but I will ſtay till my paſſion is</hi> over <hi>before I puniſh thee.</hi> Again, a ſpirit of <hi>Revenge</hi> is an evil thing: it is <hi>Murder</hi> in <hi>God</hi>'s ſight, 1. <hi>Joh. 3. 15. He that</hi> hateth <hi>his brother is a</hi> Murderer. <hi>Hatred</hi> never reſts but in the deſtruction of the thing <hi>ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ed.</hi> To ſay no more here; <hi>Cruelty</hi> is a degree of Murder, and a great Evil: and moſt of all for men to be cruel to thoſe that ſtand in neareſt Relation to them (as this Malefactor owns that <hi>he</hi> has been) whom they ought to <hi>love</hi> dearly, is an high degree of Inhumanity. <hi>No man</hi> that acted like a man, <hi>ever hated his own fleſh.</hi> To be cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el, tho to a Servant or <hi>Slave,</hi> is a very ſinful thing. Nay, Cruelty tho to a <hi>Beaſt</hi> argueth a murderous, bloody Diſpoſition. The Scripture ſaith, <hi>a good man is merciful to his Beaſt.</hi> They then that make themſelvs ſport with Putting
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:109162:12"/>
                     <hi>dumb</hi> creatures to miſery, do very ſinfully. Yet <hi>that</hi> has been practiſed here of later years in the open Streets, eſpecially on one day of the year. To do it at <hi>ſuch</hi> a <note n="*" place="margin">I intend the Cock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>alings on Shr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ve<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Tueſday.</note> Time is vanity &amp; Heathen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Superſtition; beſides to make ſport with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſing cruelty on dumb creatures, which had never bin miſerable had not the <hi>ſins of men</hi> made them ſo, it is a wicked thing, and ought not to be among thoſe that call themſelvs Chriſtians.</p>
                  <p>Infor. 3. <hi>If Murder be ſuch a</hi> Crime <hi>as hath been ſhewed, It is then a</hi> ſorrowful <hi>thing that ſo many of the Children of men ſhould be found guilty of this Evil.</hi> There are ſome places of the world where Murder is a <hi>common</hi> ſin. The dark corners of the earth, are full of the habitations of Cruelty. And there are many in the world, that call themſelvs <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> who nevertheleſs <hi>delight</hi> in <hi>ſhedding</hi> innocent blood. <hi>Perſecutors</hi> are Murderers. Bloody <hi>Papiſts</hi> are in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures charged with Murder on this account: it is ſaid of them, <hi>they repented not of their</hi> Murders, <hi>Rev.</hi> 9. 21. namely of their murdering the <hi>Saints</hi> of God for their Religion, for the Truth- ſake, and becauſe they would not comply with their Superſtitions and Idolatries. That <hi>Mother of Harlot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſhe has made her ſelf drunk with <hi>blood<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> many Millions of Saints have been murdered by her. Perſecutors are <hi>Cain's</hi> Children. O how many are there going
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:109162:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
up and down the world with <hi>Cain's bloody clubb</hi> in their hands to this day! It was <hi>Luther</hi>'s Saying, <hi>Cain will kill</hi> Abel <hi>to the end of the world,</hi> But beſides this, That which the Civil Laws of Nations make to be Murder, is frequent in ſome places. A late Hiſtorian reports, that in the the Kingdom of <hi>France,</hi> 
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>See Trap. on Geneſ.</hi> 9. 6.</note> within the ſpace of <hi>ten</hi> years, there were <hi>known</hi> to be no leſs than 6000 Murders committed. And in <hi>popiſh</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, they have <hi>Sanctuaries</hi> for Murderers <note n="(i)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Vide C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> a Lapide in Deut.</hi> 19.</note> A man that has bin guilty of <hi>wilful</hi> Murder, if he does but run into a <hi>Church</hi> (as they call it) or into a <hi>Monaſtery,</hi> he is protected in thoſe bloody places of Refuge. Their Writers plead for this. And tho no convicted Murderer did ever eſcape the ſtroke of Juſtice in this Land (which is a matter of rejoicing) yet it is a very ſad thing that <hi>any</hi> in ſuch a place as this ſhould be found guilty of ſuch a <hi>Crime:</hi> that men ſhould do ſo wickedly in a <hi>Land of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>prightneſs!</hi> but ſo it has been. Divers have been executed for this ſin formerly, and here is one that is to be executed for it this day. And there have been ſeveral Murders committed among us, the Authors of which are not yet known. Some have bin ſo monſtrouſly wicked and unnatural, as to embrew their hands in the blood of their own <hi>Children;</hi> who they are God knowes, and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:109162:13"/>
will find a time to judg them; and one day <hi>we</hi> and all the <hi>world</hi> ſhall know who they are. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides theſe, ſeveral others have bin under vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Suſpition, and tryed for their Lives, on the account of this ſin. We have all cauſe to pray for <hi>New-England,</hi> as the Lords People of old were directed to do, in caſe of an uncertain <hi>Murder,</hi> Deut. 21. 7. 8. <hi>They ſhall anſwer &amp; ſay, our hands have not ſhed this blood, neither have our eyes ſeen it; Be</hi> merciful, <hi>O Lord, to thy people</hi> Iſrael, <hi>whom Thou haſt redeemed, and lay not inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent blood to the people of Iſraels charge: and the blood ſhall be forgiven them.</hi> Be merciful, O Lord, to Thy people in <hi>New-England,</hi> and lay not innocent blood to <hi>their</hi> Cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ge!</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SE.</hi> 2. For <hi>Exhortation.</hi> There is a <hi>double</hi> Exhortation before us:</p>
                  <p>1. <hi>Hence men ſhould</hi> beware <hi>that they do not</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come guilty <hi>of this Sin.</hi> It is in Man's corrup-Nature. Nothing is more natural than a ſpirit of <hi>Revenge:</hi> as we ſee in little Children; which diſcovers that the Children of men bring mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous natures into the world with 'em. Hence the Apoſtle declaring what men by nature are, ſaith, that <hi>their feet are ſwift to ſhed blood.</hi> Rom. 3. 15. becauſe there is a marvellous <hi>Propen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>y</hi> in Man's nature unto this ſin. Should not the Lord either by ſpecial or common Grace reſtrain them, how many would ſoon become guilty of <hi>Murder</hi> it ſelf! Yea, and thoſe too that don't
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:109162:14"/>
believe any ſuch thing concerning, themſelves. When the Prophet <hi>Eliſha</hi> told <hi>Hazael</hi> what a prodigious Murderer he would be, <hi>What</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>am I a Dog,</hi> that thou ſhouldſt have ſuch thoughts of me? But in a little time he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peard to be as curſ'd a <hi>Blood-hound</hi> as ever the Prophet had ſaid to him. O then beware of this ſin. And therefore take heed of giving way to wicked <hi>Paſſions.</hi> Leſſer ſins <hi>make way</hi> for greater. And eſpecially take heed of <hi>great</hi> ſins: For many a man by being guilty of <hi>other</hi> great ſins, has provoked the Holy GOD to leave him unto <hi>this</hi> ſin too. The poor condemed Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor who ſtands here in the ſight of this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, does acknowledge, that he hath by living in other ſins provoked God to leave him unto <hi>this,</hi> which he muſt now <hi>dye</hi> for. And he warns others, eſpecially <hi>Young</hi> Men, to take heed of thoſe ſins, as they love their <hi>Lives</hi> or <hi>Souls.</hi> I know not but that it may be for <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſieation,</hi> and tend to God's Glory, if I ſhould read in this great Aſſembly, what I received in Writing from this dying &amp; diſtreſſed Creature. Its this which followeth.</p>
                  <p>I James Morgan, <hi>being Condemned to dye, muſt needs</hi> own <hi>to the glory of God, that He is</hi> righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, <hi>and that</hi> I <hi>have by my ſins</hi> provoked <hi>Him to deſtroy me</hi> before my time. <hi>I have bin a</hi> great <hi>ſinner, guilty of</hi> Sabbath-breaking, <hi>of</hi> Lying, <hi>and of</hi> Uncleanneſs; <hi>but there are eſpecially</hi> two <hi>Sins,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:109162:14"/>
whereby I have offended the great God; one is that Sin of</hi> Drunkenneſs, <hi>which has cauſed me to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit many</hi> other <hi>Sins; for when in Drink, I have been often guilty of</hi> Curſing <hi>and</hi> Swearing, <hi>and quarrelling, and ſtriking others: But</hi> the <hi>Sin which lies</hi> moſt heavy <hi>upon my Conſcience, is,</hi> that I have deſpiſed the Word of God, <hi>and many a time</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to hear it preached. <hi>For theſe things, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve God has left me to that, which has brought me to a ſhameful &amp; miſerable death. I do therefore beſeech &amp; warn all perſons,</hi> young <hi>men</hi> eſpecially <hi>to take heed of theſe Sins, leſt they provoke the Lord to do to them as He has juſtly done by me. And for the further peace of my own Conſcience, I think my ſelf obliged to add this unto my foregoing Confeſſion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> That</hi> I own <hi>the</hi> Sentence <hi>which the</hi> Honoured Court <hi>has</hi> paſſ'd upon me, <hi>to be exceeding</hi> juſt; <hi>in aſ much as (tho I had no</hi> former Grudge <hi>and Malice againſt the man whom I have killed, yet) my Paſſion at the time of the Fact was ſo out-ragious, as that it hurr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>d me on to the doing of that which makes me juſtly now proceeded againſt as a Murderer.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thus</hi> does this miſerable man confeſs. But how many are there in the Congregation, that this may ſtrike <hi>terror &amp; trembling</hi> into <hi>their</hi> ſouls<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
                  <p>O Lord, how many are there in this great Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, who have lived, and <hi>do</hi> live in thoſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſins, for which this Man confeſſeth that God has been provoked to deſtroy him! Let ſinners hear &amp; take warning this day: This man now
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:109162:15"/>
that the Terrors of God have awakned his ſoul, bitterly complains of <hi>two</hi> Sins eſpecially; one is that of <hi>Drunkenneſs.</hi> And indeed, <hi>Drunkenneſs</hi> has bin a <hi>bloody</hi> ſin; it has bin the cauſe of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a Murder. The man here, who is now <hi>flying to the Pit,</hi> confeſſeth that in his Drink, he was wont to Curſe &amp; Swear, and to quarrel, and ſtrike thoſe near him; and he acknowledged to me, that he had made himſelf grievouſly drunk the day before he was left of God to commit the Murder which he now muſt dye for; yea, and that he had <hi>that</hi> very night bin drinking to exceſs, and that he was not clear of drink at the time when he did the bloody Fact. And does not the Scripture ſay, <hi>Who has wo, who has ſorrow, who has contentions, who has babling, who has wounds without cauſe? They that tarry long at the</hi> Wine—<hi>&amp;c. Prov.</hi> 23. 29, 30. Wicked men when they are in drink, will fall to Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relling; words will bring on blows, and thoſe blows will cauſe wounds, and thoſe wounds may perhaps prove <hi>mortal:</hi> and then, what Woe &amp; Sorrow followes! O how many have by means of this ſin, been guilty of <hi>Interpretative Murder <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> They have cauſed others to dye by making them drunk. There has been an horrible thing done in this place; ſome wicked perſons (who they are God knows) have given or ſold <hi>ſtrong Liquors</hi> to the <hi>Indians,</hi> and made them drunk alſo, and ſeveral of them have dyed in that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition:
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:109162:15"/>
Let ſuch know, that the Lord will judg them; yea, He will judg 'em as Men that have <hi>ſhed blood</hi> ſhall be judged; they muſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for the blood of Souls and Bodyes too, Moſt wicked and miſerable Creatures they are, that to gain a few <hi>pence,</hi> will bring upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelvs the guilt of the blood of Souls &amp; of Bodies too! And <hi>this bloody ſin of Drunkenneſs</hi> has bin the cauſe of many a <hi>Self</hi>-Murder: how many have made themſelvs the woful <hi>Martyrs of Bac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus</hi> thereby. By <hi>Drunkenneſs</hi> &amp; Intemperance<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they have brought their Bodies to the Grave, and their Souls to Hell before their <hi>time.</hi> It is an unhappy thing that of later years, a kind of Strong <note n="†" place="margin">Reverend Mr<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                        <hi>Wilſon</hi> once ſaid in a Sermon, there is a ſort of drink come into the country, which is called Kill-<hi>Devil,</hi> but it ſhould be call'd, Kill-<hi>men for</hi> the Devil.</note> Drink kath been <hi>common</hi> amongſt us, which the poorer ſort of people, both in Town &amp; Country, can make themſelves drunk with, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> cheap &amp; eaſy rates. They that are poor and wicked too (Ah moſt miſerable Creatures) can for a peny or two pence make themſelvs <hi>drunk.</hi> I wiſh to the Lord, ſome <hi>remedy</hi> might be thought of, for the prevention of this evil. It's a very ſad thing, that ſo many Bodyes &amp; Souls ſhould be eternally ruin'd, and no help for it. How few are there, that if once they be addicted to <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>his</hi> vice, do ever <hi>truly</hi> repent <hi>of</hi> it or turn <hi>from</hi> it.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:109162:16"/>
There was a Man, who hearing that his Son took evil courſes, and that he followed ſuch a vice, well, (ſaid he) I hope he'll leave that; and that he was given to another vice, I hope (ſaid he) he'll leave <hi>that</hi> too; but it was told him that his Son was given to <hi>Drunkenneſs</hi> alſo; Nay, then (ſaid he) <hi>I have no hope of him.</hi> I will not ſay (as he did) There is no hope that ever a Drunkard ſhould <hi>repent,</hi> but I ſay, there have been but <hi>few</hi> ſuch Inſtances in the world. How rarely have any of you known a man that has been addicted to this Body-deſtroying, and Soul-murdering Iniquity, that has truly repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>of</hi> it, or turned <hi>from</hi> it again! O then, Let Men that have any love for their Lives or Souls, beware of this bloody Sin.</p>
                  <p>But the other Evil which this undone Man does eſpecially cry out of, and which (now that he ſeeth his Soul going into <hi>Eternity</hi>) he ſaith, lies <hi>moſt heavy</hi> upon his Conſcience, is his <hi>Deſpiſing the Word of God.</hi> I do not wonder to hear him ſpeak ſo, for I have known ſeveral Condemned perſons, who have made the ſame out-cry: <hi>O nothing terrifies our Conſciences like the thought of</hi> This, <hi>that we have</hi> neglected <hi>the Means of grace;</hi> And what think you of Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners in Hell, who are wayling for this with tears of blood for ever &amp; ever? whoſe doleful and bitter cry, is, <hi>O the Sermons which we once heard, or</hi> might have <hi>heard but</hi> would not! <hi>Ten
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:109162:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Thouſand worlds would we give for an</hi> opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <hi>to hear one of thoſe Sermons again, with any hope of</hi> finding Mercy <hi>with God.</hi> O you that have lived under the Goſpel, but deſpiſed it, think of this. Verily I ſay unto you, <hi>all</hi> the ſins in the world will not damn like this: Suppoſe a man to have bin guilty of Adultry, or Murder, or the moſt horrid Tranſgreſſions againſt the Law of God, theſe will not damn his Soul like that of <hi>Deſpiſing</hi> the Word of God. <hi>For this is</hi> the <hi>Condemnation, that</hi> Light <hi>is come into the world, and men love</hi> Darkneſs <hi>rather than Light.</hi> And <hi>How ſhall we eſcape, if we</hi> neglect <hi>ſo great Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</hi> They that ſhall be found guilty of neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting the great Salvation offered in the <hi>Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel,</hi> cannot eſcape the wrath of God, to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of it. And this is true, not only concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch as have lived under the conſtant Preaching of the Goſpel, and yet remain, and live &amp; dye in a natural unconverted eſtate; but of them alſo that <hi>might</hi> hear the Word of God but <hi>will not:</hi> concerning <hi>Such,</hi> Chriſt ſaith, <hi>It ſhall be more tolerable for</hi> Sodom <hi>and</hi> Gomorrah <hi>at the day of Judgment, than for</hi> them. <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. 15. This dying man, now that his Conſcience is awaken<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d, ſaith, It is a terrour to him to think, <hi>I might have heard the Word of God preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed many a time, but refuſed it.</hi> He neglected to hear Sermons, not only on Lecture dayes, but on Lords-Dayes too: when he was a Servant, he
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:109162:17"/>
was wont (as himſelf ſaith) on Sabbath-Days, to go out into the Fields, and there to profane the Lords Dayes, at the very time when he might and ought to have bin hearing the Word of God: and ſince he had a Family, his cuſtom was to keep at home, when others were attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the publick Worſhip of God. And he told me, that he did fooliſhly pleaſe himſelf in think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that he had ſufficient reaſon to ſtay at <hi>home,</hi> becauſe he had not clothes <hi>good enough</hi> to appear publickly in; whenas the mony that he miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpent in <hi>drink</hi> would have procur'd him <hi>Cloathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> Let others then by his Example be warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt this evil, leſt they provoke God, and feel ſorrow for it, as he has done, I doubt there are very many in this great Town, guilty of his ſin in this particular, perhaps ſome that are profeſſors of <hi>Religion,</hi> which is dreadful to think on. I hear ſome ſay, that there are many Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds, nay, ſome <hi>Thouſands</hi> in this place, that ſeldom hear a Sermon preached, from one end of the year to the other: if that be ſo, it is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry lamentable. What is like to become of the ſouls of ſuch profane perſons? If they that are in place of power (be they Superior or Inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or Officers) can poſſibly redreſs this evil, they will certainly do a Service acceptable to GOD, and to our Lord JESUS CHRIST.</p>
                  <p>But I proceed to the Second Exhortation. If <hi>Murder</hi> be ſuch a <hi>Crime</hi> as has bin declared, then</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:109162:17"/>
                     <hi>Let whoever has been guilty of this Sin be humb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led</hi> for <hi>it, and repent</hi> of <hi>it.</hi> As for <hi>Interpretative</hi> Murder, <hi>many</hi> are guilty of <hi>that.</hi> O how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny have by <hi>Debauchery</hi> &amp; <hi>Intemperance,</hi> ſhortened the lives of <hi>themſelvs</hi> or others! let ſuch repent, and turn from their ſins unto God. But I hope there is none in this vaſt Aſſembly, that has bin guilty of that Murder which is by the Law of God and of the Land a <hi>Capital</hi> Crime, except<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>one</hi> man, and one ſuch perſon there is here preſent, unto whom I ſhall now particularly apply my ſelf. Do you then <hi>hear,</hi> that <hi>your ſoul may live.</hi> This is the <hi>Laſt</hi> Sermon that <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver</hi> you ſhall hear. Time was when you might have heard Sermons but <hi>would not,</hi> and now you <hi>ſhall not</hi> hear them, tho' you <hi>would.</hi> For as God ſaid to him, <hi>This night thy ſoul ſhall be required of thee;</hi> ſo <hi>I</hi> ſay to <hi>you</hi> in His Name, <hi>This night</hi> thy <hi>ſoul ſhall be taken from thee:</hi> This night <hi>your</hi> ſoul ſhall be in Heaven or Hell for ever. You are <hi>appointed</hi> to <hi>dye</hi> this day, <hi>and after death com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the Judgment.</hi> As ſoon as your <hi>Body</hi> is <hi>dead,</hi> your immortal <hi>ſoul</hi> muſt appear before the great GOD and <hi>Judg of all,</hi> and a Sentence of ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Life, or Everlaſting Death ſhall be paſſed upon you. Are you willing when thoſe Chains, which are about you, ſhall be taken off, that your immortal <hi>ſoul</hi> ſhould be hang'd in <hi>ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting</hi> Chains? Are you willing that when your Body is removed from the Priſon, your <hi>Soul</hi>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:109162:18"/>
ſhould go to the <hi>Spirits that are in priſon?</hi> You have complain'd that you have bin in a Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon, and had little light there; but are you willing to go where you ſhall never ſee light? Are you willing that when your Body is delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from <hi>this</hi> Dungeon, your Soul ſhould go in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that Dungeon, where is <hi>Blackneſs of darkneſs for ever?</hi> If not I charge you in the Name of God to hear and obey his Word; yea, that Word which you have many a time deſpiſed. I have ſpoken ſo often to you in private, ſince your being Apprehended, that I ſhall not need to ſay much now, only a few words.</p>
                  <p>1. <hi>Conſider what a ſinner you have bin.</hi> The Sin which you are to die for, is as red as <hi>Scarlet;</hi> and many <hi>other</hi> ſins, hath your wicked life been filled with. You have been a ſtranger to me, I never ſaw you, I never heard of you, till you, had committed the Murder for which you muſt dye this day; but I hear by others, that have known you, how wicked you have been: and you have your ſelf confeſſed to the world, that you have been <hi>guilty</hi> of Drunkenneſs, <hi>guilty</hi> of Curſing &amp; Swearing, <hi>guilty</hi> of <hi>Sabbath-breaking, guilty</hi> of Lying, <hi>guilty</hi> of ſecret Uncleanneſs; as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaid to <hi>Shimei, Thou knoweſt the wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs which thine</hi> own heart <hi>is</hi> privy <hi>unto:</hi> ſo I ſay to <hi>you.</hi> And that which aggravates your Guilti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs not a little, is, That ſince you have been in <hi>Priſon,</hi> you have done wickedly: you have made your ſelf drunk ſeveral times ſince your Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment;
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:109162:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
yea, and you have bin guilty of <hi>Lying</hi> ſince your <hi>Condemnation.</hi> It was ſaid to a dying man, <hi>Doſt not thou fear God, ſeeing thou art under</hi> Condemnation! <hi>Oh</hi> what a ſinner have you bin! for ſince you have bin under <hi>Condemnation,</hi> you have <hi>not feared God.</hi> And how have you ſinned againſt the <hi>Goſpel?</hi> What Unbelief, what <hi>Impenitency</hi> have you bin guilty of!</p>
                  <p>Conſider 2. <hi>What</hi> Miſery <hi>you have brought upon your ſelf,</hi> on your Body, that muſt dye an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>ed death:</hi> you muſt <hi>hang</hi> between Heaven and Earth, as it were forſaken of <hi>both,</hi> and unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be in <hi>either.</hi> And what Miſery have you brought upon your poor <hi>Children!</hi> you have brought an everlaſting Reproach upon them. How great will their Shame be, when it ſhall be ſaid to them, that their Father was <hi>hang'd,</hi> not for his <hi>goodneſs,</hi> as many in the world have bin, but for his <hi>wickedneſs:</hi> not as a <hi>Martyr,</hi> but as a <hi>Malefactor,</hi> truly ſo! But that which is Ten <hi>Thouſand Thouſand</hi> times worſe than all this, is, That you have (without Repentance) brought undoing Miſery upon your poor yet precious Soul: not only Death on your Body, but a <hi>Second</hi> Death on your never-dying <hi>Soul.</hi> It is ſaid in the Scripture, That <hi>Murderers ſhall have their part in the lake, which burns with fire and brimſtone, which is the</hi> Second <hi>Death.</hi> Rev. 21. 8. O tremble at that! I remember a Man that was condemned and Executed in this place ſome years ago, that had been a Souldier,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:109162:19"/>
and as ſtout a ſpirited man as moſt in the World, who when he came to <hi>dye,</hi> thus expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed himſelf to a Miniſter that treated with him about his Soul; <hi>I</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>never knew what</hi> Fear <hi>meant, tho' I have bin amongſt drawn Swords, and before the</hi> Cannons <hi>mouth; I feared not death; but now you tell me of a</hi> Second <hi>Death, it makes my Soul to ſhake within me!</hi> That's a Death, the Thoughts whereof may make the ſoul of the ſtouteſt Sinner in the world to tremble; for that's a death which is ETERNAL. <hi>The things which are ſeen are</hi> temporal, <hi>but the things which are not ſeen are</hi> ETERNAL. The death of the <hi>Body,</hi> that's <hi>ſeen,</hi> and is ſoon over; but what becomes of the <hi>Soul</hi> when a Sinner dyeth, they that ſtand by him do not ſee, but if he dye <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitent,</hi> the Death which is <hi>not ſeen</hi> takes hold on him, and it is <hi>eternal.</hi> The God againſt whom he has ſinned, liveth for ever to puniſh him. And <hi>a fearful thing it is, to fall into the hands of the ever-living</hi> God. O run not into the mouth of the Second Death, into the wide Mouth of the fiery Pit, which has devoured Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions of Millions of immortal ſouls; and know you for certain, that if you die impenitent, your Damnation will be no <hi>ordinary</hi> one: for you have not only tranſgreſſ'd againſt the <hi>Law</hi> of God, with a high hand, but ſinn'd againſt the <hi>Goſpel</hi> too. The Sermons which you <hi>have</hi> heard formerly, or <hi>might</hi> have done, will be as ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:109162:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
witneſſes againſt you, before the Judgment ſeat of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> the 3 Sermons which have bin preached to you in publick, ſince your Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, the pains that has bin taken with you in private by one or other of the Lords Servants; all theſe will aggravate your Condemnation, when you ſhall be judged again, before <hi>all the world</hi> at the <hi>laſt Day,</hi> if you dye <hi>impenitent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Conſider. 3. <hi>There's yet a Poſſibility that your ſoul may be ſaved.</hi> Notwithſtanding all that has bin ſpoken to you, don't <hi>deſpair;</hi> repent but do not deſpair. I would not have you ſay as <hi>Cain</hi> did, <hi>My ſin is greater than can be forgiven.</hi> The Lord is a <hi>merciful</hi> God. Tho' Men cannot forgive you, <hi>God</hi> can; and He <hi>will</hi> do it, if you <hi>unſeign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly</hi> repent &amp; <hi>believe</hi> on the <hi>Lord Jeſus.</hi> There is infinite Merit in the Death of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> if your bloody ſoul be <hi>waſh'd</hi> in <hi>his blood,</hi> it ſhall be made whiter than the Snow. That Sin which you muſt now dye for, God has forgiven to others upon their true Repentance. <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> filled the ſtreets of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> with <hi>innocent blood,</hi> but when he <hi>humbled</hi> himſelf, and beſought the Lord for <hi>Mercy,</hi> God was entreated of him. O therefore <hi>Repent,</hi> and then though your <hi>Body muſt</hi> dye, your <hi>Soul ſhall live and not dye.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I have but <hi>two</hi> words more to ſay to you, and then I ſhall take my leave of you for ever.</p>
                  <p>1. <hi>Be ſure that you be</hi> ſincere <hi>in your Repentance.</hi> Many times men under Fears, will <hi>ſeem</hi> very pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:109162:20"/>
whenas they do but <hi>flatter God with their mouths, and lye unto him with their tongues.</hi> Thus it was with <hi>Pharoah,</hi> and with many a ſinner, whoſe hard heart was never broken nor chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; we ſee often, that ſinners on <hi>ſick beds,</hi> when they behold Death &amp; Eternity before their eyes, will confeſs their ſins and promiſe <hi>Reformation;</hi> but if the Lord ſpare &amp; reſtore them, they are the <hi>ſame</hi> that they <hi>were</hi> before. And we have known Inſtances among our ſelvs, of men, that when they have bin <hi>Captive,</hi> and in <hi>Turkiſh Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very,</hi> they have <hi>pretended</hi> to a <hi>ſenſe</hi> of thoſe <hi>ſins</hi> which provoked the Moſt High to bring that miſery upon them, and have written <hi>ſeemingly pious &amp; penitent</hi> Letters to their Friends, but now God has delivered them they are as vain as profane as ungodly as ever in their lives before; nay, ſome of them <hi>worſe.</hi> For the Truth is, if men be not <hi>humbled</hi> and <hi>converted</hi> by ſuch ſignal Diſpenſations, many times they are judicially &amp; everlaſtingly <hi>hardned:</hi> They never leave ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning until they have ſinned themſelvs into <hi>Hell,</hi> paſt all hopes of Mercy or Recovery. To come nearer to you, I have known ſome, more than one or 2 or 3, that have bin condemned to <hi>dye,</hi> and whileſt they remained under that Sentence, they ſeemed <hi>very penitent,</hi> but they were pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned (for they had not bin guilty of <hi>Murder,</hi> as <hi>you</hi> have) and ſince that, have bin as wicked as <hi>ever</hi> O then look to your ſelf, that you do not <hi>diſſemble</hi> with GOD and Man, and your own
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:109162:20"/>
Soul too. And let not the <hi>Fear of Puniſhment</hi> only, but the <hi>Senſe of Mercy</hi> break your heart.</p>
                  <p>2. In this way of <hi>ſincere</hi> Repentance, <hi>Betake your ſelf to the City of Refuge.</hi> Go to <hi>Chriſt</hi> for Life. The <hi>wilful man ſlayer</hi> had (as you heard but now) no benefit by the City of Refuge; ſo ſhall <hi>impenitent</hi> Sinners have no Salvation by Chriſt: but they that have a real ſight of their Sins, and flee from the <hi>Avenger of blood</hi> unto Chriſt for life, He is ready to ſuccour them. Poor man! has the <hi>fiery</hi> Serpent ſtung thy ſoul? then <hi>look</hi> unto the <hi>Brazen</hi> Serpent, look unto the Lord <hi>Jeſus</hi> that you may live and not dye for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever. Build your hopes of Salvation on Chriſt &amp; <hi>His</hi> Righteouſneſs <hi>alone.</hi> Don't think you ſhall be ſaved only becauſe good <hi>men</hi> have <hi>pray'd</hi> for you, or for the <hi>Confeſſion</hi> of your <hi>ſins</hi> which you have now made, or for the ſake of <hi>any</hi> thing but CHRIST. And I pray the Son of GOD to have Compaſſion on you.</p>
                  <div type="testimony">
                     <head>The <hi>Laſt</hi> Expreſſions &amp; ſolemn Warning of <hi>James Morgan:</hi> As they were in <hi>Short-hand</hi> taken from his <hi>Mouth,</hi> at the <hi>Place</hi> of <hi>Execution.</hi> Mar. 11. 85 / 6.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I</hi> Pray God that I may be a <hi>Warning</hi> to you <hi>all,</hi> and that <hi>I</hi> may be the <hi>laſt</hi> that ever ſhall ſuffer af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this manner: in the fear of God I warn you to have a care of taking the Lords Name in vain, Mind &amp; have a care of that ſin of <hi>Drunkenneſs,</hi> for that ſin leads to all manner of ſins and Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs:
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:109162:21"/>
(mind &amp; have a care of breaking the ſixth Commandment, where it is ſaid, <hi>Thou ſhalt do no Murder</hi>) for when a man is in Drink, he is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready to commit all <hi>manner</hi> of <hi>Sin,</hi> till he <hi>fill up</hi> the cup of the wrath of God, as I have done by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting that ſin of <hi>Murder.</hi> I beg of God as I am a dying man, and to appear before the Lord within a few minutes, that you may take notice of what I ſay to you. Have a care of drunkenneſs, &amp; ill Company, and mind all good Inſtruction, and don't turn your back upon the Word of God, as <hi>I</hi> have done. When <hi>I</hi> have bin at meeting, <hi>I</hi> have gone out of the meeting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe to commit ſin &amp; to pleaſe the luſt of my fleſh. Don't make a mock at any poor object of pity, but bleſs God that he has not left you as he has juſtly done me to commit that horrid ſin of <hi>Murder.</hi> Another thing that <hi>I</hi> have to ſay to you, is to have a care of that houſe where that wickedneſs was commited, &amp; where I have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>in partly ruind by. But here I am, and know not what will become of my poor ſoul which is within a few moments of eternity. I have murder'd a poor man, who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>d but little time to repent, and I know not what is become of his poor ſoul; O that I may make uſe of this opportunity that I have! O that I may make improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this little little time, before I go hence and be no more. O let all mind what <hi>I</hi> am a ſaying now I'm going out of this world. O take warning by me, and beg of God to keep you from this ſin which has bin my ruine. [<hi>His</hi> laſt <hi>words were</hi>] O Lord, receive my ſpirit, I come unto thee O Lord, <hi>I</hi> come unto thee O Lord; I come, I come, I come.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:109162:21"/>
                  <p>THE CALL OF THE GOSPEL APPLYED Unto All men in general, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto a Condemned Malefacto in particular.</p>
                  <p>In a SERMON, Preached on the 7th Day of March. 1686.</p>
                  <p>At the Requeſt, and in the Hearing of a man under a juſt Sentence of Death for the horrid SIN of M<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RDER.</p>
                  <p>By COTTON MATHER. Paſtor to a Church at Boſton in N. E.</p>
                  <p>The SECOND EDITION.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Pſal. 89. 1.</bibl>
I will ſing of the mercies of the Lord for ever, with my mouth will I make known thy Faithfulneſs to all generations.</q>
                  <p>Nulla ſpecies Peccati tanta eſt qua non ſit Superior JESUS. Orig.</p>
                  <p>Printed at Boſton, by Richard Pierce. 1687.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:109162:22"/>
                  <head>To the Reader.</head>
                  <p>ALtho' my Conſent to the Publication of the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing <hi>Sermon</hi> had no ſmall <hi>Objections</hi> to Encounter with: for, <hi>Firſt,</hi> The ſhort time allow<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d me for <hi>Preparation</hi> after I was (by the little<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected <hi>dying Deſire</hi> of a poor man) diverted from my ſpending the whole of the Sabbath with a bereav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Congregation to which my help was promiſed; and <hi>Next,</hi> the Regard to be had unto the Adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> which now in the Abſence of an Honoured Relation that kindly anſwered my Engagement elſewhere I was to keep ſome <hi>Eye</hi> unto; <hi>both</hi> neceſſitated me to want in this Diſcourſe that <hi>Accuracy</hi> &amp; that full <hi>pertinency</hi> which might <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> unto the <hi>Iudicious;</hi> Nevertheleſs, ſo long as among all the <hi>Faults</hi> in it, I found not <hi>this, That it was not</hi> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſigned <hi>to do good,</hi> and ſo long as among all the <hi>Pleas</hi> (which in a curious &amp; cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious age my love to my own r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>poſe brought) againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he <hi>omitting</hi> of it, I never met with <hi>this,</hi> That <hi>It was impoſſible any good ſhould be</hi> done <hi>by it,</hi> I have at the urgent Importunity of others ventur'd to deliver it into the Hands of as many as ſhall think<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> themſelves concerned to peruſe it: Praying that it may <hi>reach &amp; touch</hi> the hearts of them, to whom a <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhould be a <hi>Pearl of great Price,</hi> till they <hi>LOOK unto</hi> HIM <hi>and be SAVED.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Cotton Mather.</signed>
                  </closer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:109162:22"/>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <head>The <hi>CALL of the GOSPEL,</hi> unto <hi>All the Ends of the Earth;</hi> Apply'd <hi>eſpecially</hi> unto a poor man under the <hi>juſt</hi> Sentence of <hi>Death</hi> for the Crying Sin of <hi>M<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RDER.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>Iſai. XLV. 22.</bibl>
LOOK unto M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, and be ye SAVED, all the Ends of the Earth.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <div type="part">
                     <p>THESE Words give unto us the moſt <hi>Joyful Sound</hi> that ever the Children of <hi>Death</hi> had the favour of. Some of us doub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>leſs can with a moſt Diſtinguiſhing and Experimental <hi>Reliſh,</hi> profeſs concerning this Oracle of God, as ſome<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> other perſons have concerning ſome other <hi>Paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> in the Sacred Pages, <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>e would not have had</hi> this <hi>Sentence left out of our Bibles, for the riches of both the India</hi>'s Yea, who among us all, at the reading of theſe <hi>glad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ydings</hi> unto us, can for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear joyning with the Rapturous ſhouts of Heaven, with that Angelical, and Evangelical Out-cry, in <hi>Luc. 2. 14. Glory to God in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, on earth peace,</hi> Good-will <hi>towards men!</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, the Saviour of the world is this day ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king unto you, ye Congregation of the Lord, Arrayed in His <hi>white garments,</hi> He looks thro<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Windows of His bright Ivory Palace, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tereth an Invitation to <hi>you,</hi> which Bleſſed are your ears that hear this day.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="40" facs="tcp:109162:23"/>This 45<hi>th</hi> Chapter of (that which we may not ineptly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ſt, the <hi>Goſpel according to) Iſaiah,</hi> ſeems the Cloſe of a <hi>Sermon</hi> begun at the 40<hi>th</hi> chapter of that admirable Book, whoſe <hi>Goſpel</hi>-ſtrains are ſo abundant, that in the <hi>New-Teſtament</hi> ſome have counted perhaps about <hi>threeſcore</hi> Quotati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from it; and good old <hi>Ambroſe</hi> hence ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed <hi>Auſtin</hi> unto a peculiar frequency in the Reading of it. <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſignifies <hi>the Salvation of God;</hi> now <hi>that</hi> very thing, eſpecially in the more <hi>promiſſory</hi> Concluſion of his Prophecy, is very much the Subject of his Miniſtry.</p>
                     <p>The Princely Prophet is predicting, perhaps about 200 years before the Accompliſhment thereof, the Reduction and Redemption of the captiv'd <hi>Jews</hi> from <hi>Babylon,</hi> together with the very <hi>name</hi> of the <hi>Perſian</hi> Emperor <hi>Cyrus,</hi> who ſhould be the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>rument thereof; and thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he aſſigns the ſeveral reaſons of this ſtupen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dions Diſpenſation. One ground thereof laid down is, that the <hi>Nations</hi> of the world, far and near, might be brought to abandon their <hi>Lying vanities,</hi> and to acknowledge the <hi>Only true GOD,</hi> with <hi>Jeſus Chriſt whom He hath ſent.</hi> At the mention of this there immediately falls in the gracious <hi>invitation</hi> to thoſe <hi>Nations</hi> which we have now to inſiſt upon: wherein we may obſerve,</p>
                     <p>(1.) The <hi>Subjects</hi> which are call'd upon, Theſe are <hi>all the ends of the earth;</hi> even the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> in all quarters of the world, whoſe <hi>Vocation</hi> is here
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:109162:23"/>
foretold; The poor ſouls whoſe <hi>natural Diſtanse</hi> from the <hi>Church</hi> of God, and whoſe <hi>moral</hi> Diſtance from the <hi>Love</hi> of God was exceeding deplorable. (2.) The <hi>Object</hi> propounded for theſe to converſe withal. This by that Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion <hi>Me,</hi> is determined to be the Lord Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. But who? Truly, it is God the <hi>Saviour,</hi> it is the <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> a Devotion to whom ſhould come inſtead of the Homage which men had bin wont to yeild unto their other <hi>Images</hi> of God, and <hi>Deliverance</hi> by whom is the <hi>Antitype</hi> of what the Lords people had of old by <hi>other</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours. To confirm this Interpretation, I find the <hi>Chaldee Paraphraſe</hi> rendring this <hi>Me,</hi> by <hi>My Word;</hi> uſing the Term of [<hi>Meemar</hi>] which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to the <hi>2nd</hi> Perſon in the adorable <hi>Trinity.</hi> (3.) The <hi>Act</hi> to be applyed hereunto: This is to <hi>Look;</hi> namely with an <hi>Eye</hi> of <hi>faith</hi> &amp; of <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</hi> In this Clauſe, there ſeems to be an Alluſion to the <hi>Looks</hi> that the ancient <hi>Iſraelites</hi> had bin wont to give unto the <hi>Brazen Serpent;</hi> which, if that great Reformer <hi>Hezekiah</hi> had not made <hi>meer braſs</hi> of it, might, for ought I know be <hi>ſtill</hi> abus'd to vain &amp; vile <hi>Superſtitions</hi> among 'em. (4.) The <hi>End</hi> of the Whole. Tis ſaid, <hi>Be ye ſaved;</hi> and the intent of that is Double, it is both, <hi>be</hi> deſireous <hi>that ye</hi> may <hi>be ſaved,</hi> &amp; it is, <hi>be</hi> aſſured <hi>that ye</hi> ſhall be <hi>ſaved.</hi> The two fold End (both <hi>finis Operis,</hi> and <hi>finis Operantis</hi>) both the <hi>Deſign,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Event</hi> is to be Salvation. <hi>Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>
                        <pb n="42" facs="tcp:109162:24"/>
SALVATION—but what a Word is That It is a word that does contain more than any man can conceive.</p>
                     <p>From hence then, This <hi>Doctrin of GOD your Saviour</hi> does challeng your ſerious Attention.</p>
                     <p>Doct. <hi>The Lord Jeſus Chriſt in His Goſpel, gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly &amp; earneſtly</hi> inviteth all <hi>the Children of men to</hi> Look unto <hi>Him, by Faith</hi> upon <hi>Him for</hi> SAL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VATION.</p>
                     <p>When the no leſs unexpected than un <hi>deniable</hi> Requeſt of the <hi>dying man</hi> who now ſtands in in this Aſſembly, that I would allow him this Morning a Diſcourſe proper for his uncomfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Circumſtances, was yeſterday brought un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me; I cold not ſuddenly think on any thing more accommodated unto all the <hi>Perſons</hi> &amp; <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices</hi> which are before me, than that which I have now pitch'd upon. The Body of this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation can't hear of a more important thing than this, of <hi>Looking unto Jeſus Chriſt</hi> for <hi>Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> Men and Brethren, This is the <hi>One thing needful.</hi> The <hi>little flock</hi> of Communicants, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whom I am by &amp; by to adminiſter the <hi>Holy Supper,</hi> cannot be excited unto a fitter work than this, of <hi>Looking unto</hi> Jeſus Chriſt <hi>for Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> Chriſtians, this is our Errand hither. The poor condemned <hi>Malefactor,</hi> who is here liſtening to one of the <hi>three laſt</hi> Sermons that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he is like to fit under before his Encounter with the <hi>King of Terrors,</hi> cannot be put in mind
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:109162:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of any thing that will more tend to prepare him for his near approaching death, than this of <hi>Looking</hi> unto the Lord of Life, for <hi>Salvation</hi> &amp; Life. Poor man, do <hi>you</hi> hearken, I'll ſtudy to make this whole hour very particularly ſuitable &amp; ſerviceable to <hi>you;</hi> and methinks a man that knows himſelf about to take an eternal <hi>Farewel,</hi> of all Sermons, ſhould endeavour to hear with <hi>moſt earneſt heed.</hi> The God of Heaven grant, that <hi>Faith</hi> may <hi>come</hi> unto <hi>you</hi> by your <hi>Hearing.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>It is a very pretious Repaſt, which is thus brought unto you, O immortal Souls! It comes from the <hi>Land flowing with milk &amp; honey.</hi> The enſuing <hi>Propoſitions</hi> may carve it out unto you. The <hi>1ſt</hi> Propoſition that arreſts our thoughts is,</p>
                     <p>1. That, to <hi>Believe</hi> on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, is to <hi>Look unto Him for Salvation.</hi> Theſe bleſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed things are <hi>equivalent</hi> each to the other; and herein, we have both the <hi>Act</hi> of Faith, and the <hi>End</hi> of Faith. fairly ſuggeſted unto us.</p>
                     <p>¶ As for the <hi>Act</hi> of Faith, that is a <hi>Looking.</hi> The <hi>Faith</hi> of God's Elect hath in the Scripture ſeveral <hi>Bodily</hi> Actions, uſed as the Metaphors &amp; Shadows of it. There is the Action of the <hi>Hand,</hi> for the ſake of which in Joh. 1. 12. Faith is ſaid to be a <hi>Receiving</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt. There is the Action of the <hi>Mouth,</hi> in Reſemblance of which, in Joh. 6. 54. Faith is ſaid to <hi>Fat</hi> the Fleſh of Jeſus Chriſt. There is the Action of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:109162:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the <hi>Foot,</hi> in regard of which Joh. 6. 35. Faith is ſaid to be a <hi>Coming</hi> unto Jeſus Chriſt. Thus likewiſe the Action of the <hi>Eye</hi> is here improv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to denote the <hi>Chriſt-ward motions</hi> of <hi>ſoul</hi> which the Believer hath.</p>
                     <p>There is indeed a 3 fold <hi>Look,</hi> which the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving Soul in its Agonies does give towards the Lord Jeſus Chriſt. There is a Look of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire;</hi> a Look with a <hi>Wiſh,</hi> yea, with a <hi>Groan:</hi> a Look with a, <hi>Lord help me!</hi> Such a Look as the hoarſe <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>per</hi> gave in <hi>Marc.</hi> 1. 40. when he came to Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>beſeeching</hi> Him, &amp; <hi>kneeling down unto</hi> Him. There is alſo a Look of <hi>Dependance,</hi> a Truſting a Rolling a Relying Look; a Look accompanied with the Language of the Pſalmiſt in <hi>Pſal. 25. 2. O my God, I</hi> truſt <hi>in thee.</hi> And there is a Look of <hi>Acknowledment,</hi> producing both of theſe. Many things doth the Believer <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſcern &amp; confeſs</hi> to be in that Jeſus, whoſe Name is, <hi>Wonderful, Counſellor, The mighty God, the Everlaſting Eather, the Prince of Peace.</hi> But theſe 2 things eſpecially: One thing of which he is ſenſible is, that Jeſus Chriſt is a <hi>mighty Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour,</hi> owning that in <hi>Heb. 7. 25. He is</hi> able <hi>to ſave to the</hi> uttermoſt <hi>them that come unto God by Him.</hi> Another thing whereof he is not unſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble is, that Jeſus Chriſt is a <hi>Merciful</hi> Saviour, owning that in <hi>Joh. 6. 37. Him that cometh to me, I will in no wiſe caſt out.</hi> After this manner does the Believer <hi>look</hi> to the Saviour upon the <hi>ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:109162:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Hills,</hi> from whence <hi>comes all his help.</hi> But upon what <hi>Motive?</hi> for What?</p>
                     <p>¶ As for the <hi>End</hi> of Faith, that is SALVATI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ON. This the Apoſtle grants in 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 9. where he ſpeaks to Chriſtians about <hi>the</hi> end <hi>of their Faith, the</hi> Salvation <hi>of their ſouls.</hi> That which the Believer doth purpoſe to himſelf by his Addreſſes to <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> is, that he may be reſcued from all the Calamities which his Fall from God hath brought upon him, and that he may be made partaker of Benefits contrary thereunto, by the means of an <hi>All-ſufficient,</hi> &amp; a Compaſſionate Jeſus the <hi>Mediator.</hi> There are indeed eſpecially <hi>three</hi> things which the Believer does <hi>look</hi> unto the Lord Jeſus for. His <hi>firſt</hi> Look is with that glance in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 122. Lord, <hi>Be ſurely for thy ſervant for good.</hi> He would behold Jeſus Chriſt as <hi>the Lamb of God,</hi> appearing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>divine Juſtice</hi> in <hi>his</hi> room, adding unto this Caſt of his <hi>Eye,</hi> this Throb of his <hi>heart,</hi> Oh, <hi>let Jeſus Chriſt take away all my</hi> Sins, <hi>with all the</hi> wants &amp; woes, <hi>which thereby I become</hi> obnoxious <hi>unto.</hi> He would have Jeſus Chriſt to remove all the <hi>guilt</hi> that lies upon him, to enſtate him in the Favour and Fellowſhip of God, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure for him all Bleſſings whatſoever, eſpecially <hi>ſpiritual</hi> Bleſſings, the <hi>Bleſſings of the upper ſprings<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi> the <hi>ſure Mercies</hi> of the Covenant, by His own Obedience &amp; Interceſſion. His <hi>Next</hi> Look is with thatſigh in <hi>Plal.</hi> 25. 4. Shew <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e thy wayes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                           <pb n="46" facs="tcp:109162:26"/>
O Lord,</hi> Teach <hi>me thy paths.</hi> There is an <hi>Eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalve</hi> which he petitions unto this <hi>Lord</hi> our <hi>healer</hi> for. He flyes &amp; cryes unto Jeſus Chriſt, as that <hi>ſon of ſorrow</hi> did of old, <hi>Lord that I may receive my ſight.</hi> He would have Chriſt to <hi>remove</hi> all the <hi>blindneſs</hi> of his mind, to <hi>reveal</hi> unto him the <hi>hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs</hi> which is <hi>not ſeen,</hi> and which is <hi>eternal,</hi> and to diſcover unto him all that he muſt <hi>know &amp; do</hi> in order to his obtaining of it. His Look, is with that Aim in Pſal. 119. 5. <hi>Oh that my mayes were</hi> Directed <hi>to</hi> Keep <hi>thy ſtatutes O God!</hi> He ſubmits unto the <hi>ruling Will</hi> of God while he Emplores the <hi>Saving Grace</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> He reckons that the Moſt High by ſaying, <hi>I have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>t my</hi> Son <hi>to bleſs you, by turning you away from your Iniquities,</hi> hath told him of a Bleſſedneſs &amp; a Loving kindneſs, which he hath infinite cauſe to ſay <hi>Amen</hi> unto. He would have Jeſus Chriſt to remove all the <hi>Diſorder</hi> of his Will, to <hi>incline</hi> him ſo that he may <hi>refuſe</hi> the <hi>evil &amp; chooſe</hi> the <hi>good,</hi> and to ſhield him againſt all the ruining attempts of the <hi>World;</hi> the <hi>Fleſh</hi> and the <hi>Devil</hi> for evermore. This, <hi>all</hi> of this <hi>Faith</hi> is beck'n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for in this one word, <hi>Look unto Me.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>[And theſe are the Chriſtward <hi>Looks</hi> which muſt be given by <hi>you,</hi> whoſe eyes will be within a few dayes cloſ'd by the cold hands of grim <hi>Death,</hi> if you would not roar in <hi>outer</hi> (worſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>han-<hi>Egyptian) darkneſs</hi> for evermore.]</p>
                     <p>On the heel of the former, this <hi>ſecond</hi>
                        <pb n="47" facs="tcp:109162:26"/>
Propoſition taketh hold.</p>
                     <p>2. SALVATION will moſt undoubledly be the Fruit of a Believer's <hi>Looking</hi> unto the Lord Jeſus Chriſt. The great God, who once ſaid unto <hi>upright</hi> man, <hi>Obey</hi> and <hi>live,</hi> now ſaith unto <hi>lapſed</hi> man, <hi>Believe &amp; be ſaved;</hi> and truly an <hi>Exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing great multitude, whom no man can number,</hi> have bin happy witneſſes to the Fulfilment of it. It is that which our Lord has ordered to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed unto <hi>every creature,</hi> I mean (as the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews</hi> do by that Phraſe) unto every <hi>man</hi> in the world. <hi>Marc.</hi> 16. 16. <hi>He that</hi> believeth <hi>ſhall [be ſaved.</hi>] And when a convinced <hi>Jayler</hi> was ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citous about his everlaſting Weal, the Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of heaven gave him this Teſtimony (which ſurely the convinced <hi>Priſoner</hi> that I have before me, may very reaſonably look upon himſelf as concerned in) <hi>Act.</hi> 16. 31. Believe <hi>on the Lord. Jeſus Chriſt, and thou ſhalt [be ſaved.</hi>] Thus alſo it is repreſented as the Property &amp; the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge of true Believers, in <hi>Heb, 10. 39. We are of them that believe unto the</hi> ſaving <hi>of the ſoul.</hi> Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, a man does no ſooner <hi>look</hi> unto <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> in away of <hi>Beleeving,</hi> than a Sentence of <hi>Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> is paſſed upon him, and all the <hi>Promiſes,</hi> yea and all the <hi>Attributes</hi> of the Eternal Jehovah are engaged for the execution of it.</p>
                     <p>¶ Shall we deſcend unto ſome Particulars<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </p>
                     <p>Every part of that Salvation which <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> is the Author of, ever follows upon <hi>Looking &amp; Believing</hi> for it. As thoſe three comprehenſible
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:109162:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and inexhauſtible Treaſures of <hi>life,</hi> in 2. Cor. 13. 14. even the <hi>Grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and the <hi>Love of God,</hi> and the <hi>Communion of the Holy Spirit,</hi> are to be got by <hi>Booking.</hi> So parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly, the voice, the ſweet ſoul-mel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ng vo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ce of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt unto Sinners is, LOOK unto <hi>Me,</hi> and you ſhall be <hi>Juſtified.</hi> Hence, not to ſpeak of the large Diſcourſes on this point, in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans,</hi> concerning whom the ſpirit of Prophecy fore-ſaw that they would apoſtatize from their Orthodox Perſwaſion and Profeſſions herein: It is ſaid in Joh. 3. 18. <hi>He that believeth on the</hi> Lord Jeſus Chriſt <hi>is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned.</hi> No, he is <hi>in Chriſt,</hi> and there ſhall [<hi>not one] Condemnation</hi> fall upon him, (as the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle elſe-where has it) tho' he may have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved a Thouſand Million. He is ſaved from the horrendous Wrath &amp; Curſe of God. The <hi>Free Grace</hi> of God forgives all his tranſgreſſions, and accepts him as righteous, imputing the Righteouſneſs of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> unto him; the juſt &amp; holy God that was once <hi>angry with him every day,</hi> now ſayes unto him, <hi>Fury is not in me; Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is not in me.</hi> And he rejoices with ſuch a <hi>white ſtone</hi> put into his hand as that <hi>Paralitick</hi> had, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whom it was ſaid, <hi>Son, be of good theer, thy ſins <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>re forgiven thee.</hi> Yet again, The voice of the Lord Jeſus unto ſinners is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                        <hi>Look</hi> unto <hi>Me</hi> and you ſhall be <hi>Adopted.</hi> Hence is it averr'd in <hi>Gal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 10. Y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> are the</hi> children of God, <hi>by Faith in
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:109162:27"/>
Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> Thus theſe bleſſed believing <hi>Look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> ſhall be <hi>ſaved</hi> from the doleful Family of the Devil, they ſhall be taken into the <hi>number,</hi> they ſhall have a Title to the <hi>Felicity</hi> and <hi>Dignity</hi> of them that are <hi>the ſons of God;</hi> the Angels now call them <hi>Brethren:</hi> and the Almighty Magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent <hi>Governor of the world</hi> ſaies unto them, <hi>Ye are my ſons &amp; my daughters</hi> Beſides all this, the Voice of the <hi>Lord Jeſus</hi> unto <hi>ſinners</hi> moreover is, <hi>Look</hi> unto <hi>Me,</hi> and you ſhall be <hi>Sanctified,</hi> in regard of this it is that He has ſaid in Joh. 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 36. <hi>He that believeth hath everlafling life;</hi> the Seed &amp; the Spring of it is in Him. Truly ſuch a man ſhall be <hi>ſaved</hi> from his ſlavery to the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of his ſoul. He ſhall be <hi>renewed</hi> in his <hi>whole</hi> man after the Image of God, and be enabled more &amp; more unto a <hi>dying</hi> to <hi>ſin,</hi> and a <hi>living</hi> in <hi>Grace;</hi> his ſpirit, his ſoul, his body, his <hi>All</hi> is now under an enobling <hi>Dedication</hi> unto the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of <hi>ſhewing forth the praiſes of God:</hi> a curious Needle-work made by the fingers of the eternal<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Spirit covers him, adorns him, makes him <hi>more excellent than his neighbour.</hi> And Oh what <hi>peace</hi> even the peace of <hi>God that paſſeth all underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> O what <hi>Joh!</hi> even Joy <hi>unſpeakable &amp; full of glory;</hi> Oh what <hi>Aſſurance,</hi> Oh what <hi>Perſeverance</hi> in <hi>this</hi> life will flow from <hi>theſe</hi> unto the <hi>ſaved</hi> Believer! Finally the Voice of the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus unto ſinners likewiſe is, <hi>Look</hi> unto <hi>Me</hi> and you ſhall be <hi>Glorified.</hi> On this ſcore has the <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:109162:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Diſciple</hi> ſaid in 1. <hi>Joh. 5. 13. You that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve on the Name of the</hi> Son of God <hi>may</hi> know <hi>that ye have eternal life.</hi> Oh how firmly is Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life <hi>enſured</hi> unto Believers! Certainly, thoſe Chriſt-prizing Ones ſhall be <hi>ſaved</hi> from the <hi>ſecond Death;</hi> they ſhall <hi>awake</hi> in the <hi>upper</hi> world, in the <hi>future</hi> world; they ſhall <hi>behold</hi> the <hi>Face</hi> of God and Chriſt in <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> and be ſatisfied with His <hi>likeneſs.</hi> The <hi>Lamh</hi> ſhall <hi>feed</hi> them and <hi>lead</hi> them to <hi>Fountains of Living wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi> they ſhall <hi>enter into the</hi> Joy <hi>of their</hi> LORD; they ſhall <hi>drink</hi> of the <hi>Rivers</hi> of <hi>pleaſure, at the right hand</hi> of GOD for ever more: they ſhall ſo <hi>partly</hi> at their Diſſolution, they ſhall ſo <hi>fully</hi> at their <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> they ſhall ſo in the <hi>Heaven</hi> of Heavens, until the very Heavens be no more. Such is a little of the [<hi>Be ye ſaved</hi>] which all Believers hear from their heavenly <hi>Friend,</hi> from their Undertaker on high. <hi>So great</hi> Salvation will a <hi>Believing</hi> LOOK procure.</p>
                     <p>But that this Goſpel may have a fit and fult dwelling in your hearts, there is one Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on more to be laid into your Underſtandings.</p>
                     <p>3. The Lord Jeſus Chriſt in His Goſpel does <hi>graciouſly &amp; earneſtly</hi> INVITE all men thus to <hi>Look</hi> unto <hi>Him</hi> and be <hi>ſaved.</hi> That ever-glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious One whom God has <hi>exalted</hi> to be a <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>Saviour,</hi> to give <hi>Repentance</hi> unto His Elect with <hi>Remiſſion</hi> of ſins; <hi>He</hi> hath with a match<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:109162:28"/>
degree of <hi>Favour</hi> and <hi>Fervour</hi> too, ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>iſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> Man-kind about this matter; He hath reviv'd a dying world with ſuch <hi>ſweet words of his mouth</hi> as theſe, <hi>O ye periſhing</hi> Out-caſts, <hi>I am a</hi> Saviour <hi>infinitely</hi> able &amp; ready <hi>to relieve the</hi> Diſtreſſes <hi>which you are plung'd into: I</hi> require <hi>you and</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat <hi>you therefore, that you don't keep at a diſtance from me.</hi> And for <hi>this</hi> cauſe it is that in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65. 1. he makes (according to the <hi>Apoſtolical</hi> Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation in <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.) this proffer even to the very <hi>Heathen</hi> (O let the blackeſt blindeſt <hi>Negroe,</hi> at the further end of this Aſſembly count himſelf bound to anſwer ſuch a Call) <hi>Behold me, behold me!</hi> q. d. O that you would LOOK at me for my SALVATION. We have indeed a moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Bible in our hands [that <hi>Book</hi> of <hi>Life</hi> I ſee in thoſe hands too that muſt <hi>dye</hi> pinion'd before many dayes have roll'd away; man do you firſt look downward upon <hi>that,</hi> and ſo look <hi>upward</hi> unto Him from whom it comes] it is a Bible iudited by the Spirit of Jeſus Chriſt, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by His Providence; and the very ſcope of this, the <hi>principal</hi> buſineſs of it, is, to come from the Third Heaven, as a <hi>Letter</hi> with thy name, &amp; mine, &amp; every man's on the Endorſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it, beſpeaking the <hi>beleeving looks</hi> of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Reader unto a <hi>ſaving Jeſus.</hi> But there are likewiſe many ſpecial paſſages to this purpoſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſparkling and glittering like ſo many <hi>Jewels</hi> in the Cabinet of God. It is a Rule which our
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:109162:29"/>
Lord Jeſus has given about His <hi>Exhortations,</hi> in Marc. 13. 37. <hi>What I ſay to</hi> one <hi>I ſay to</hi> All: And will not the ſame ſquare to His <hi>Invitations</hi> alſo? Yes, the old loving Invitations which were more immediately given to other people do likewiſe call upon <hi>us</hi> upon whom the <hi>ends of the world are come,</hi> upon <hi>Thee,</hi> and <hi>thee,</hi> and <hi>thée:</hi> Well, we are informed in Joh. 7. 36. That when our Lord Jeſus was <hi>Incarnate</hi> among the mov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Duſt-heaps and Potſherds of the earth here below, once on the eight day of the <hi>Feaſt of Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacles,</hi> when there was a vaſt Confluence of People going to draw <hi>water</hi> from he Pool of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loam,</hi> ſinging the words of the Prophet, <hi>With joy ſhall ye draw water out of the wells of</hi> Salvation. Lo, then He took occaſion to <hi>ſtand,</hi> that He might be <hi>ſeen,</hi> to <hi>cry</hi> that he might be <hi>heard,</hi> &amp; to ſay, <hi>If any man thirſt, let him come to me &amp; drink.</hi> So then all the needy dying ſouls of men are ſtill are thus offered; the only Appointed &amp; Anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Redeemer of men does thus counſil them, <hi>Let me hear from you</hi> whenſoever &amp; whereinſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>you want Salvation.</hi> But how many other ſuch amazing lines has He alſo ſent down from the <hi>Excellent Glory</hi> into a deſolate world! It is the Lord Jeſus Chriſt who has compared the <hi>Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>l</hi> of Salvation unto a well-fraught Veſſel ſailing up a River, whereahout He makes that loud &amp; loving Out cry—O Never, never was there an <hi>O yee's</hi> vouchſaſed unto the world like
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:109162:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>
to <hi>This!</hi>—in Iſai. 55. 1. <hi>Ho, every one that thirſteth let him come</hi> and partake hereof. It is the Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> too, who concludes this miraculous Book with that remarkable <hi>Period</hi>—when He would put a <hi>full Stop</hi> to inſpired in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Writings, He does it by expoſing His <hi>Salvation</hi> unto general Acceptation, in <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. 17. <hi>Whoſoever will, let him take the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of life freely.</hi> In a word: For the ſuller In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culcation of ſuch a marvellous Thing, we have this immortal King, laying upon us in the name of Him that is Higher than the higheſt, in 1. Joh. 3. 23. <hi>A Commandment to believe.</hi> We have Him hence alſo annexing the <hi>Sanctions</hi> of a <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment</hi> hereunto, laying Bonds &amp; Graplings of Iron upon the Conſciences of men: We have Him both upon Mount <hi>Ebal</hi> &amp; upon Mount <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizzin</hi> giving accents to His <hi>Look unto Me.</hi> He diſcharges the <hi>dreandful rumbling Thunderclaps</hi> of ſuch <hi>denunciations</hi> as that in Joh 3. 36. <hi>He that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth not ſhal</hi> not <hi>ſee life.</hi> And many more ſuch <hi>Threats</hi> and <hi>Menaces</hi> does He <hi>roar out of Sion</hi> with, wherein the ſmoke of the Fire and Brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone reſerved in a hot Hell for the Portion of <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelievers</hi> is blown under the Noſtrils of men. Yea, and He preſents no leſs ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ming <hi>Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements</hi> to Beleeving than thoſe in the <hi>Preface</hi> to <hi>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Proverbs of Salomon:</hi> &amp; one Text more above all I have found which I muſt bring to you, as <hi>Sampſon</hi> did unto his Relations the <hi>Hen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>y</hi> which
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:109162:30"/>
he had light upon, it is in <hi>Mat.</hi> 11. 28. O feed upon it, every word in it is a drop of <hi>Canaans</hi> Hony; it is <hi>Honey from the Rock.</hi> He was a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Perſon that once ſaid, <hi>mallem carere</hi> Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo <hi>et</hi> Cœlo <hi>quam hoc Verbo,</hi> I had rather not have a bit of <hi>Bread</hi> to put in my mouth, I had rather the <hi>Sun</hi> in the Firmament ſhould ſhine no more upon me, than that I ſhould looſe ſo dear a <hi>Word</hi> as <hi>this.</hi> Thus our Lord ſpeakes COME, gr. [<hi>Deute</hi>] a moſt freindly &amp; familiar Call: <hi>q. d.</hi> I pray be ſo kind as to ſtep hither to a <hi>Friend.</hi> But unto whom ſhall we come? Lo, He ſaith, come unto <hi>Me,</hi> unto <hi>Me</hi> that have <hi>all things de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver'd</hi> unto Me by the Father, unto <hi>Me</hi> that am by Him <hi>empowered</hi> and <hi>employed</hi> to pluck never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dying ſouls from the devouring Jaws of every Death. But <hi>who</hi> ſhall come? mark the Anſwer, <hi>Let ALL come.</hi> But what if we have horrible <hi>Burdens</hi> of <hi>Filth</hi> and <hi>Fear</hi> lying upon us? Its <hi>no matter,</hi> ſayes our Ever-living and Ever-loving Lord, <hi>come</hi> all ye that <hi>Labour</hi> and are <hi>heavy La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den.</hi> But what if we <hi>do</hi> come, ſhall we not miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carry miſerably, and miſs of our Expectations, notwithſtanding all? No, no. The <hi>Faithful &amp; true witneſs</hi> ſaith unto us, <hi>I will GIVE you REST.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>[O let the poor fetter'd <hi>Priſoner</hi> recollect himſelf; <hi>James,</hi> thy name is not excepted in theſe INVITATIONS.]</p>
                     <p>It is a Feaſt of <hi>Fat things full of marrow,</hi> and
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:109162:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of <hi>wines on the lees well refined,</hi> which the Lord has made in this <hi>Doctrin</hi> for the ruin'd Race of ſinful <hi>men.</hi> It remains that we make ſome <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes</hi> of it.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SE.</hi> 1. And now <hi>Praiſes,</hi> Millions of <hi>Praiſes,</hi> an Eternity of <hi>High-praiſes</hi> be given unto our <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt</hi> who ſpeakes ſuch things <hi>to the rebellious.</hi> O the <hi>Admiration,</hi> O the <hi>Adoration</hi> which the never-enough praiſed <hi>Grace</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt ſhould beget in us! At the preaching of this <hi>Doctrin</hi> we have unnutterable cauſe to do as the <hi>Jews</hi> did at the building of the <hi>Temple</hi> in <hi>Zech.</hi> 4. 7. even to ſhout <hi>Grace, Grace,</hi> concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning it, until our Acclamations reach unto the very Heavens. It is recorded of the poor ſlaves among the Brick-kilns in <hi>Egypt,</hi> Exod. 4. 31. That <hi>when they heard the Lord had viſited the children of Iſrael, and had look'd on their</hi> Affliction, <hi>then they bowed their heads and worſhiped:</hi> behold, you have this morning <hi>heard,</hi> that the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt hath <hi>viſited</hi> the <hi>children</hi> of men, and bid them in their <hi>Afflictions</hi> to <hi>Look</hi> unto Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. O where are the <hi>good words,</hi> where are the <hi>kind thoughts</hi> that we ought to magnify this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer and His Grace withal? <hi>David</hi> once in an holy Ecſtafie of ſoul, 1. <hi>Chron.</hi> 29. 10,—14. <hi>Bleſſed the Lord,</hi> and ſaid, <hi>O who am I!</hi> Verily now, all of us have cauſe to abound with ſuch notes as thoſe, <hi>Lord who are we,</hi> that He who ſits on the lofty Throne of Eternity ſhould <hi>ſend</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way unto <hi>us</hi> that ly ſtarving like odious <hi>Beggars</hi>
                        <pb n="56" facs="tcp:109162:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>
among the <hi>Ditches</hi> and under the <hi>Hedges</hi> of Hell<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> inviting us to <hi>LOOK</hi> unto Him and be SAVED! The Phariſees of old aſpers'd Him with this as His Diſgrace, but let <hi>us</hi> cry it up in Him as his Honour, <hi>This man</hi> receiveth <hi>ſinners.</hi> The ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous <hi>Elizabeth</hi> in Luc. 1. 43. <hi>Wondred that the</hi> Mother <hi>of her Lord ſhould come unto her:</hi> but what a thing is this, that our Lord <hi>Himſelf</hi> ſhould <hi>Invite</hi> us to <hi>Look,</hi> yea, to <hi>come</hi> unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf! That he who ſits as King for ever upon the lofty Battlements of Heaven, &amp; charges the very <hi>Angels</hi> with Folly, ſhould ſo far ſmile upon <hi>us</hi> a company of <hi>born-fools</hi> wandering about the earth; upon <hi>us</hi> who dwell in houſes of <hi>Clay,</hi> whoſe Foundation is in the <hi>duſt,</hi> which are cruſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before the <hi>moth;</hi> did I ſay <hi>ſo?</hi> Nay this is not the worſt of our Character: we are not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly undeſerving creatures, but alſo <hi>Hell</hi>-deſerving <hi>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>inners.</hi> When our <hi>firſt Father</hi> began a <hi>deſperate</hi> War againſt the Omnipotent God, <hi>we</hi> were part of the mad Regiment involved in his perſidious Treaſon, and our <hi>Emnity</hi> againſt our Maker has from our very Cradles been ſo enormous, that we ſhould long ere now have bin <hi>Devils-in-fleſh,</hi> if the checks of <hi>Reſtraining Grace</hi> had bin taken away. And what <hi>unreaſonably</hi> vitious <hi>lives</hi> have we been leading ever ſince a <hi>Rational Soul</hi> appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently acted in us! How have we bin <hi>every moment</hi> ſinning againſt the <hi>Law</hi> of God, tranſgreſſing every precept of <hi>Love</hi> to God &amp; to man! Yea,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:109162:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>
how grievouſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ly have we bin ſinning againſt the <hi>Goſpel</hi> too! fearfully grieving, ſleighting, and ſhamefully affronting a Redeemer that for many a day beſought us to be reconciled unto God! This have we <hi>been &amp; done.</hi> And <hi>Ah Lord, doeſt thou open thine eyes upon</hi> ſuch <hi>ones?</hi> What if the Lord Jeſus Chriſt had now only ſpoken unto us ſuch fiery wrathful words as thoſe in <hi>Iſa. 1. 23. Aha, I will eaſe me of mine enemies, &amp; avenge me of mine Adverſaries!</hi> or thoſe in <hi>Luc. 19. 27. Thoſe mine enemies bring hither, and</hi> ſlay <hi>before me!</hi> Verily I ſay unto you, he would <hi>be clear in his ſpeaking and juſt in his judging ſo.</hi> What if he ſhould appear unto us in the black garments of all-deſolating indignation, with keen Darts &amp; conſuming Thunder-bolts in his hand? What if he ſhould appear in flaming fire, to take ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance on us that have not <hi>known God,</hi> nor <hi>obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> his <hi>Goſpel?</hi> Surely this would be no more than a <hi>proper</hi> and a <hi>proportionable</hi> Diſpenſation. But inſtead of this, the winning Language, which with bowels full of ſuch <hi>Philanthropy</hi> as (this King's wedding a Queen out of our poor Family) His taking our Nature to ſubſiſt in his Second Perſon, doth evince and encline Him to have unto us) he ſpeakes unto us, is, <hi>O Look in o Me and be</hi> SAVED. Yea, and in this thing he doth with a Riddle of <hi>Free</hi> Grace <hi>deſtinguiſh</hi> us <hi>from,</hi> by <hi>dignifying</hi> us <hi>above</hi> uncountable Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes of our Fellow-creatures, our Fellow-cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minals
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:109162:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>
If we do look through the earth and into <hi>Hell</hi> we ſhall ſoon ſee our ſelves <hi>lifted up to heaven</hi> by the <hi>Invitation</hi> which our Lord Jeſus has given to us to <hi>Look</hi> unto <hi>Him</hi> for <hi>Salvation.</hi> Let us (we eſpeceally in this Wilderneſs that that like <hi>Gideon</hi>'s Fleece, enjoyes theſe Dewes of Heaven when the reſt of the world is dry, may do it) take a view of all the <hi>Viſible World</hi> and ſee what incredible <hi>Millions</hi> in every Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, there are that either never <hi>had</hi> one beam from the <hi>Sun of Righteouſneſs</hi> falling on them, but drop down into the Land of Darkneſs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>hearing</hi> a word of Him, or, at leaſt, are by their <hi>blind Guides</hi> muffled up in ſuch <hi>Ignorance</hi> as proves to them the <hi>Mother of Deſtruction.</hi> Alas, Alas,—for the people that <hi>periſh for lack of viſion,</hi> that <hi>ſit in the region of the ſhadow of death.</hi> But here, in a little Spot of ground that t other day the <hi>Devil</hi> was worſhiped in, there now are the Colonies, whom the Invitations of Jeſus Chriſt <hi>have known above all the Families of earth.</hi> This is much! But take a view like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of the <hi>howling people</hi> in the <hi>Inviſible world.</hi> Who are there in the fiery <hi>diſmal</hi> Vault below? There are vaſt <hi>Legions</hi> of <hi>Devils</hi> in that place of torment; but unto which of thoſe <hi>apoſtate ſpirits</hi> has our Lord Jeſus ſaid, <hi>I would have thee to</hi> look <hi>unto me?</hi> There is an <hi>innumerable</hi> number of <hi>our</hi> Race too gone down into that <hi>formidable</hi> Pit; but unto none of thoſe does the Lord Chriſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:109162:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſay, <hi>Thou mayſt be ſaved by me if thou wilt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi> No, thoſe <hi>Invitations</hi> are <hi>our</hi> Prerogative. <hi>Wonderments,</hi> where are you? <hi>Halleluiahs,</hi> where are you? Syrs, let us place the utmoſt of them upon this miſterious <hi>Love.</hi> But we are ſottiſh; our unaffected rocky hearts are inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of our obligations to the Lord Jeſus Chriſt; Then <hi>wonder,</hi> O ye Angels, <hi>give Thanks,</hi> O all ye miniſtring Spirits, Let the <hi>Morning ſtars</hi> in the upper Regions, throughout eternal Ages <hi>think honourably</hi> of the Saviour whom we are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apt to acknowledge, for his <hi>remembring us in our low eſtate, becauſe his mercy endures for ever.</hi> O how, how ſhall we enough extol the <hi>mer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>iful High-Prieſt,</hi> whoſe <hi>Look unto me and be ſaved,</hi> has bin vouchſaved unto us! <hi>Is this the manner of</hi> men, <hi>O Lord?</hi> No, no. Then, <hi>Let the people praiſe the,</hi> O Lord, <hi>let</hi> all <hi>the people praiſe thee,</hi> ſince <hi>Thy way is known upon the earth,</hi> and <hi>Thy</hi> SAVING <hi>Health among all Nations.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But This is not all the <hi>Good-Speech</hi> of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, unto us; There's ſome-what more that remains to be ſaid unto us all, [and particularly unto that Condemned Malefactor here who is never to ſee the Light of another Sabbath in the world] It was a pathetic word of the Apoſtle to his <hi>Corinthians</hi> in 2. Cor. 6. 1. <hi>We beſeech you that receive not the grace of God in vain.</hi> Wherefore</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="60" facs="tcp:109162:33"/>
                        <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SE<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi> I<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I. O Let every one of us now <hi>Look unto Jeſus Chriſt by Faith for</hi> SALVATION. If he ſay unto us, <hi>Look unto me,</hi> let not us be ſuch prodigies of madneſs as to reply, <hi>No, we will</hi> not <hi>look unto thee.</hi> It is a ſweet intercourſe between God and man, which the prophet pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes in <hi>Jer.</hi> 3. 22. where the Call of God is <hi>Return ye backſliding children, and I will heal your backslidings:</hi> and the <hi>Echo</hi> of man is, <hi>Behold we come unto thee, for thou art the Lord our God.</hi> O that there might now be ſuch a Communion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Chriſt and us. His Call is, <hi>Look unto Mee and be ſaved:</hi> let our Return be, <hi>Behold we</hi> look <hi>unto thee, for thou art the Lord our Saviour.</hi> Do not, I entreat you, do not give unto the Lord Jeſus Chriſt ſuch a daring and damning Anſwer as that in Jer. 44. 16. <hi>As for the word ſpoken to us in the Name of the</hi> Lord, <hi>we will</hi> not <hi>hearken thereunto.</hi> It is a thing declared by the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt concerning theſe Goſpel-times <hi>Zech. 12. 10. Men ſhall</hi> look upon <hi>me and morn.</hi> Now ſhall a like thing be brought to paſs within theſe walls this day? How ſhall ſo great a thing as this be gained? A ſad part of this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, tis to be doubted, are too much like the <hi>Leviathan,</hi> Their hearts are <hi>as firm as a ſtone, as hard as a peice of the nether</hi> Milſtone. <hi>The ſword of him that layeth at them cannot hold.</hi> Alas; what ſhall be done for them? Unto <hi>Thee,</hi> O Lord, do I how my knee; <hi>O Father of ſpirits and of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:109162:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>
look down with thy tender mercies on the ſpirits of the unperſwadeable Children. And O Thou that haſt the keyes of</hi> David <hi>in thy hand, Open, open our hearts as thou didſt</hi> Lydia'<hi>s of old, and effect by thy mighty power that we may</hi> look <hi>unto thee &amp; believe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>God forbid that there ſhould be any <hi>Eſau</hi>-like deſpiſers of Jeſus Chriſt, and his Invitation, or his Salvation, in the Congregation. God forbid that there ſhould be <hi>one</hi> ſuch <hi>child of perdition</hi> as an impenitent unbeliever among us all. Some perſons there are indeed, who make a Scruple of it, <hi>May I venture to look unto Jeſus Chriſt, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all my</hi> vileneſs, <hi>my</hi> wretchedneſs, <hi>my unworthineſs?</hi> To theſe it may be ſafely rejoin'd If you find that God hath wrought your heart to a willingneſs to cloſe with a <hi>whole</hi> Chriſt, you ſhould not let your Unworthineſs be your Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement againſt doing of it. The Invitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation <hi>Look unto me,</hi> is enough to embolden you unto <hi>beleeving looks</hi> towards the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, notwithſtanding all the damps &amp; doubts which your miſgiving hearts may have about your ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance in it. Syrs, the Golden <hi>Sceptre</hi> is held out, you may draw near. When Jeſus Chriſt ſaid unto <hi>Peter,</hi> you may <hi>come,</hi> he preſently <hi>ran</hi> over the dangerous waves of the boiſterous Sea unto Him; Truly ſo, ſince Jeſus Chriſt ſayes to you, <hi>you may look,</hi> let no hard ſuſpicions and ſurmiſes keep you from doing your duty in it. The <hi>Canaaniteſs</hi> in Mat. 15. 27. did, as one of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:109162:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Ancients expreſſeth it, <hi>play the Philoſopher</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he diſputed the caſe after this rate; <hi>A Dog may have</hi> Crumbs, <hi>It ſeems I am a dog<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Therefore</hi> (an ingenious &amp; a gracious <hi>Therefore</hi>) I <hi>may have Crumbs too.</hi> Thus may you Argue proſtrate at the footſtool of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>All the Ends of the earth ſhould look unto thee,</hi> O Lord; I <hi>am one at the Ends of the earth;</hi> Therefore <hi>I may look unto thee.</hi> Surely He that hath his <hi>Chair</hi> in the <hi>heavens,</hi> will deny no part of the <hi>Syllogiſm</hi> which ſhall thus be framed by a wreſtling <hi>Faith,</hi> Though you have bin as bad as any among the <hi>Corinthians</hi> were of old, yet if you have arrived unto a due <hi>hunger &amp; thirſt</hi> after <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> you may endeavour to <hi>look</hi> unto him, ſaying as <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel</hi> to <hi>Eli,</hi> Lord <hi>here I am for thou calledſt me;</hi> and He will be far from ſaying to you as <hi>Eli</hi> to <hi>Samuel,</hi> No, <hi>I called not.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Queſtion which ſome will now be ready to ask, is, (and O that many with an earneſtneſs like that wherewith <hi>Peter</hi>'s hearers put forth their <hi>What ſhall we do,</hi> would ask ſuch a queſtion)</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>How ſhall I look unto Jeſus Chriſt?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>About this there are a few <hi>Directions</hi> to be given.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>O ſet your</hi> hearts <hi>unto the words that ſhall be te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified among you, for they are not vain things;</hi> your<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> very lives<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yea the lives of your ſouls are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in them.</p>
                     <p>I Know then, that beſides your <hi>occaſio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>al glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> towards the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, which every day ought to be very many, at leaſt as many as
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:109162:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the <hi>ſtings</hi> which the <hi>infernal</hi> vipers do vex your ſouls withal; there is a <hi>Set</hi>-work of this nature to be ſolemnly performed both by them whoſe <hi>dead eyes</hi> never yet look'd to Jeſus Chriſt, &amp; by them whoſe <hi>dim eyes</hi> have cauſe enough to <hi>continue looking</hi> unto <hi>him</hi> whom they have already ſeen.</p>
                     <p>Now there are Two things to be premiſed concerning this. Let this be the <hi>1ſt.</hi> premiſed.</p>
                     <p>It is highly expedient that you ſhould ſpeedily <hi>ſet apart</hi> a time to <hi>make attempts</hi> about the grand work of <hi>Looking unto Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> It is indeed true, that an unbeliever hath no other Aſſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of proſpering in his Eſſayes to break the iron Priſon doors of his unbelief, but ſuch an <hi>Who can tell?</hi> ſuch an <hi>Who knowes</hi> ſuch an <hi>It may be,</hi> as the Prophets of old were wont much to inſiſt upon. If you ſet your ſelvs to believe in your <hi>own</hi> ſtrength, the Faith of <hi>Simon Magus</hi> is all you are like to attain unto. Yet you may be quickned to do what you <hi>can,</hi> from the renown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Hiſtory of the man with the <hi>withred hand</hi> in <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. 13. unto whom <hi>Jeſus</hi> ſaying, <hi>ſtretch forth thy hand;</hi> he tryed to do it without any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murr at the ſeeming unſuitableneſs of the Injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and <hi>Behold he ſtretched it forth and it was</hi> reſtored.</p>
                     <p>Let this be <hi>next</hi> premiſed. It is extreamly requiſite that this rare work of <hi>Looking unto Jeſus Chriſt</hi> ſhould be often <hi>renewed.</hi> Sometimes per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps the ſpirit of <hi>Jealouſy</hi> will come upon you, you will be fearing, <hi>Alas, I did never yet</hi> aright
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:109162:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                        <hi>look unto Jeſus Chriſt!</hi> Now the beſt way <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>ſec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle</hi> theſe <hi>troubled waters,</hi> will be that which <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ah</hi> had, <hi>I will</hi> look <hi>yet</hi> AGAIN. And O remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that to do this work <hi>often,</hi> over &amp; over <hi>again,</hi> is a thing than which nothing can more tend to your Victory over all the Adverſaries of your endleſs Welfare. Yea, ſometimes if an Half or a Whole of a day, were purpoſely laid out i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> this work, the time will be found not to have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>in loſt when Eternity ſhall dawn upon the world. Hence in 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 4. they who have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready <hi>taſted the grace</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt are bid ſtill <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o <hi>come unto him.</hi> [Some of us before the ſands of another hour be run out, ſhall ſo meet with this <hi>King of glory</hi> in his <hi>Galleries</hi> that we may have a ſpecial opportunity to catch hold on the feet of the Lord who deigns to <hi>ſup</hi> with us, and like <hi>Mary</hi> cry <hi>my Lord, my Lord,</hi> until we have <hi>renewed</hi> the Looks that have hitherto <hi>kept our ſouls in life.</hi> O be you thankful for this, and <hi>do wish your might what your hands find to do.</hi>]</p>
                     <p>And now, <hi>Hear and your ſoul ſhall live.</hi> O that you would labour in a <hi>wiſe</hi> Retirement to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>if<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> up the wof<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>l eyes of your Hell-ſtung ſouls towards the <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt</hi> after <hi>ſuch</hi> a manner.</p>
                     <p>1. <hi>Meditate</hi> moſt affectionately on thoſe thing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> which may <hi>aw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ken</hi> the Chriſt-ward LOOKs of of your ſou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s. It is hinted in <hi>Luc.</hi> 1. 17. Tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>dina<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ily before perſons <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>an <hi>look</hi> unto Jeſus Chriſt, they muſt be a <hi>people</hi> prepared <hi>for the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:109162:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Lord.</hi> Now to promote and produce this peice or Soul-good, there is no Engine, li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e to <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration.</hi> O <hi>Conſideration,</hi> what Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>icine for <hi>ſou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi> maladies is comaparable to That! If we would but let the Angel of CONSIDERATION <hi>ſtir the</hi> Pool, how probably might we ſtep in, and have our <hi>unbelieving</hi> eyes <hi>enabled</hi> to look unto our dear Helper who longs to be doing good unto us! It's ſaid of a Convert in Ezek. 18. 28. <hi>He</hi> conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders <hi>&amp; he turns,</hi> perhaps it may likewiſe at <hi>laſt</hi> be ſaid of us, <hi>he conſiders &amp; he</hi> looks. There are then 2 or 3 ſavory Meditations, to which if you ſhould give a <hi>time</hi> and <hi>room,</hi> you may hereafter reap the comfort of it. I perceive in <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14. 2. and elſewhere, that the prophets would ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times put <hi>words</hi> into the <hi>mouths</hi> of <hi>them</hi> that they were travelling for the Salvation of: Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of that kind ſhal now be done by the <hi>bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of thoſe <hi>thoughts</hi> into your mind which may comport with the <hi>Invitations</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                     <p>Let your firſt Head of Meditation be an <hi>I Muſt</hi> Think with your ſelves, <hi>I muſt</hi> look unto Jeſus Chriſt. Say to your own ſouls about <hi>Looking</hi> to Jeſus Chriſt, as Paul did about <hi>preaching</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Neceſſity is laid upon me, and</hi> woe <hi>unto me if I do it not.</hi> Beſtow one look in the firſt place on your <hi>ſelvs,</hi> upon your own moſt rueful <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> &amp; <hi>Fears.</hi> O ponder on the hideous <hi>do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>ful pligh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> which by your Iniquities you have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>unk your ſelves into and with an Anguiſh of Soul ſpeak to
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:109162:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>
your ſelvs in ſuch Soli-loquies as theſe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <q>Ah, wo is me; In the <hi>Fruition of God</hi> is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrapped all my happineſs, without this, O Lord, what will become of me for evermore<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But never was there a more lamentably forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Soul than I. The Terrible God, at whoſe Rebuke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> the Everla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>ing Rocks are tumbled down, and the mountainous Pillars of heaven tremble, He is ſuch an <hi>Adverſary</hi> to me, that if I do not <hi>agree quickly</hi> with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>lim, never-ceaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Tormentors will take me into their unpit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tying hands. I have like a Fool in whom <hi>fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly was exalted</hi> horribly provoked him by my ſins that are as <hi>many</hi> as the Sands, &amp; as <hi>mighty</hi> as the Hills that over-top the Clouds. I am hereupon juſtly already ſmitten with <hi>ſpiritual</hi> plagues, &amp; juſtly given over into the clutches of the red roaring Dragons, &amp; devouring Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons whom I have moſt fondly hearkned unto Yea I ſee the dreadful Gulf below gaping for me, I ſee my ſelf ready to be prey'd upon by the <hi>worm</hi> that dyes not, &amp; by the <hi>fire</hi> which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſhall be quenched. Nor can I by any means pluck my <hi>ſelf</hi> out from this horrible Pit, this <hi>miery clay.</hi> Alas, What ſhall I do? <hi>O wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that I am, who ſhall deliver me?</hi>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p>Let your <hi>ſecond</hi> Head of Meditation hereupon be an, <hi>I May.</hi> Think with your ſelvs, <hi>I May</hi> look <hi>to Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> O hear him crying to you from the fragrant Tops of the Spicy Mountains
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:109162:36"/>
as in <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 13. 9. O Soul, <hi>thou haſt deſtroy'd thy ſelf but in Me is thy help.</hi> Don't let your Imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions be, that <hi>There is no hope.</hi> No, reſerve now <hi>anoth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> look for Jeſus Chriſt, as the <hi>Moſes</hi> ſent by <hi>God</hi> to <hi>draw</hi> you out from <hi>black floods</hi> of your <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                              <desc>••••</desc>
                           </gap>s.</hi> Now <hi>refreſh your ſelvs with</hi> this <hi>Reflection.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>That there is ſuch an one as the <hi>God-man</hi> Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt to goe unto; <hi>and ſo</hi> (ſay) <hi>tis poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that</hi> I may <hi>live.</hi> Say now with your ſelvs.</p>
                     <p>
                        <q>But is there <hi>no hope in</hi> Iſrael <hi>concerning</hi> me? yes, I ſee a <hi>door</hi> of hope. My God <hi>may</hi> become my <hi>Friend,</hi> and His <hi>Foe</hi> MAY become His <hi>child</hi> yet for all <hi>this.</hi> Yet may I <hi>glorify</hi> Him &amp; <hi>enjoy</hi> Him forever. The Son of <hi>God</hi> is become the Son of <hi>man,</hi> a <hi>Dayes-man</hi> between God &amp; man. <hi>It has pleas'd the Father that in</hi> him <hi>ſhould all ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs dwell,</hi> and it hath pleaſed <hi>Himſelf,</hi> to <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage</hi> in the bleſſed work of bringing God and man <hi>together.</hi> Neither will I undervalue Him ſo much, as to count that any of my ſtreights are too difficult for Him to meddle with, or that any of my <hi>Faults</hi> will cauſe him to reject the Supplications that his Spirit ſhall help me to come before him with. No, No, when I am about to ſay unto him, <hi>Lord, If thou</hi> wilt <hi>tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> canſt ſave me,</hi> His <hi>preventing</hi> Goodneſs ſayes to me, <hi>Soul, if</hi> thou <hi>wilt,</hi> I <hi>will.</hi> Then I will no longer <hi>pine away</hi> in mine <hi>Iniquities,</hi> but <hi>look,</hi> unto Him immediately.</q> Having got <hi>thus</hi> far,</p>
                     <p>Then 2. <hi>Cry</hi> to Heaven that you may be
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:109162:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                        <hi>Enabled</hi> to <hi>Look</hi> unto the Lord Jeſus Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The Caſe is ſo that you <hi>cannot</hi> look unto Jeſus Chriſt until you <hi>ſee</hi> that you cannot look. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver will you <hi>aright</hi> look, unto Jeſus Chriſt, if you do it not with Sentiments a kin to that in <hi>Joh. 6. 44. No man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> come</hi> (or look) <hi>unto Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt except the Father</hi> draw <hi>him.</hi> No, we have bin told by the heavenly Records, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this <hi>Look</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> that it is the <hi>gift</hi> of <hi>God.</hi> That it is the <hi>Operation</hi> of <hi>GOD,</hi> and that it is cauſed by the <hi>mighty power</hi> of <hi>God.</hi> It was ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of old in Joh. 6. 44. <hi>How can ye believe?</hi> Such an humbling Quære ſhould you put unto your ſelves, <hi>How can</hi> I look <hi>unto Jeſus Chriſt?</hi> Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly you can as eaſily make Iron <hi>ſwim,</hi> and ponderous Mountains to fly like Atoms about the Air, and bulky Rocks to place themſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the ſhining ſtars in the Firmament of <hi>God,</hi> as <hi>look</hi> unto Jeſus Chriſt by any Abilities of your <hi>own.</hi> If you would not have your Faith prove a Cobweb in the day when the fiery Bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom of Deſtruction ſhall ſweep the world, you muſt firſt ſay with him in <hi>1 ſal. 40. 12. I am</hi> not able <hi>to look up.</hi> Now with a bleeding ſoul, on the precipeice of an inevitable Hell, make your moans as the man did in <hi>Mar. 9. 24. Lord help my unbelief.</hi> Now ſay; <q>O Lord I <hi>muſt</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve or <hi>dy,</hi> I <hi>may</hi> believe and <hi>live;</hi> but I <hi>cannot,</hi> O I cannot. Do thou <hi>draw</hi> me, do thou <hi>turn</hi> me, or I ſhall yet miſcarry. Doe thou work
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:109162:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>
this work of thine own <hi>in</hi> me and <hi>for</hi> me<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo the <hi>whole</hi> of my Salvation will at length re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound to thy Honour. <hi>Not unto me, not unto me, but unto</hi> Thee, <hi>O Lord will be all the Glory.</hi>
                        </q> Hereupon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                        <hi>Labour to look as well as you can unto Jeſus Chriſt for</hi> All <hi>that</hi> Salvation <hi>which He has to confer upon you.</hi> There is a <hi>probable likelyhood</hi> that the <hi>iſſue</hi> of your <hi>ſtruggling</hi> after <hi>faith</hi> may be <hi>this,</hi> That the Lord Jeſus Chriſt will ſay unto you, as once unto deceaſed <hi>Lazarus,</hi> O thou <hi>dead</hi> Soul, <hi>ariſe.</hi> Watch now to follow him as <hi>Peter</hi> did the Angel in <hi>Act</hi> 12. 9. till you have got out of the Goal which you have on a Light fire over your heads. Tis <hi>poſſible</hi> and more than ſo, that Jeſus Chriſt may now do by you as he did to that man in Marc. 8. 25. when <hi>He put His hands upon his eyes, and made him</hi> look <hi>up.</hi> Now, now profeſs unto the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, as did <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> long ago, in 2. <hi>Chron. 20. 12. I know not what to do,</hi> O Lord, <hi>but my eyes are up unto thee.</hi> O ſay to him, Lord, I <hi>look</hi> unto Thee for for thy <hi>Salvation,</hi> yea, as the <hi>Hart panteth after the water brooks;</hi> ſo does my ſoul after Thee, O Saviour. I do heartily cloſe with Thee, as the <hi>Surety</hi> of the New everlaſting Covenant which is made between the <hi>Frſt Being</hi> &amp; my ſoul; and I wait upon Thee for the Communication of all the <hi>ſure mercies</hi> which belong unto it.</p>
                     <p>But in doing thus, have a ſpecial Regard to <hi>this,</hi> That you do not retain a <hi>Prejudice</hi> againſt any part
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:109162:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Part of the Salvation which you ought to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireous of. O don't look <hi>a ſquint</hi> when you look unto <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Don't <hi>divide</hi> his <hi>ſaving Offices</hi> His ſaving <hi>Kindneſſes;</hi> but with a <hi>ſingle eye,</hi> ſay, <hi>Lord, be</hi> all <hi>that to me which thou art to any of thy choſen ones.</hi> Hath the Lord ſaid of Him, in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110, 4. <hi>Thou art a</hi> Prieſt <hi>forever?</hi> Now do you anſwer, <hi>Lord,</hi> I conſent to have Jeſus Chriſt on my behalf a <hi>Prieſt</hi> whoſe Obedience, &amp; Inetrceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſhall take away all Controverſies between Thee &amp; me. Has the Lord ſaid of him in <hi>Act.</hi> 3. 22. <hi>A</hi> Prophet <hi>ſhall the Lord raiſe up unto you?</hi> Do you anſwer, Lord, let Jeſus Chriſt be my <hi>Prophet,</hi> leading me evermore in the way where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I ſhould go. Has the Lord ſaid of him in <hi>Pſal. 2. 6. I have ſet him as my</hi> King <hi>upon my holy hill?</hi> Do you anſwer, <hi>Lord,</hi> I would have Jeſus Chriſt be my <hi>King</hi> forever, <hi>Governing,</hi> Strengthening, defending of me whileſt I have any being. Do this;—And then <hi>labour</hi> to <hi>reſt</hi> with glorious Tranſports and Triumphs now ſaying, <hi>Why are thou caſt down, O my ſoul?</hi> Hope <hi>in the Lord, for thou ſhalt praiſe</hi> Him, <hi>who is thy</hi> Salvation.</p>
                     <p>This <hi>is the good way, walk therein and you ſhall find</hi> Reſt <hi>for your ſouls.</hi> But, O ye ſouls in peril, what is the Reſolution that you intend to go out of this Houſe withal? Is your anſwer like theirs in <hi>Jer. 6. 16.—we will</hi> not <hi>walk therein?</hi> Shall yonder Doors anon bear witneſs againſt you, <hi>Here paſſes by a perſon that will</hi> ſtill neglect
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:109162:38"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> look <hi>unto Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Alas has all this Rain fallen upon the <hi>Rocks?</hi> Will none of us now with full purpoſe of heart, ſay before the heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearching One, with him in <hi>Marc. 7. 7. I will</hi> look <hi>unto the Lord, I will wait for the God of my Salvation.</hi> how ſtrangely beſotted muſt that <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelite</hi> have been, who ſhould have declined to have given a <hi>Look</hi> unto the Remedy which the Almighty had provided for him, when the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal ſpreading Venome of a Scorpion had ſet his bloud in a torturing flame? Epecially, when all the world (as I perceive by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hat the <hi>Roman</hi> Poet <hi>Lucan</hi> wrote many Ages after) could not help to any other cure of the ſtinging Strokes which the Tayls of theſe <hi>Preſters</hi> gave? Ev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ery Unbeliever here is to be charged with a more bruitiſh &amp; ſtupid Madneſs. Indeed the Jewiſh <hi>Talmud</hi> affirms, that a <hi>Look mith the</hi> eye <hi>to the brazen Serpent did the people in the Deſart no good, unleſs there were at the ſame time a</hi> look <hi>with the</hi> heart <hi>unto the heavenly</hi> Father <hi>alſo.</hi> But moſt aſſuredly, without your <hi>Look</hi> unto <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> it is impoſſible that your <hi>Souls</hi> ſhould do any other than Welter and languiſh under dolours more ſcorching than Rivers of burning Brimſtone or of running <hi>Bell-metal</hi> world without end. 'Tis uncertain what your eſteem of Salvation is, but ſurely <hi>Salvation</hi> ſhould be worth a <hi>Look.</hi> My Friend, if the Saviour had bid thee <hi>do ſome great thing, wouldſt thou not have done it?</hi> yea, thou
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:109162:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſhouldſt have reckoned Salvation to be worth Rocks of Diamonds. <hi>Thouſands of Rams, and ten Thouſands of Rivers of oyl,</hi> are not too much to be parted with by him that would have SALVA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION. What an obdurate heart of Adamant muſt he then have that ſhall be <hi>diſobedient</hi> when our Lord only ſaith LOOK <hi>and be ſaved!</hi> You have <hi>now</hi> a ſeaſon to ſecure Salvation at ſo cheap a rate; but I may not break off till I have moſt vehemently and faithfully proteſted unto you, that you ſhall not <hi>alwayes</hi> have ſo. You are here mourning over a man in Irons whoſe life will be done before this week be out: and yet who among you can ſay that <hi>your</hi> Great <hi>Change</hi> is not nearer unto you? but I do with <hi>utmoſt</hi> ardour of ſpirit declare unto you, That if your ſouls are found <hi>Faithleſs &amp; Chriſtleſs</hi> when they are <hi>required of</hi> you, Wo, wo unto you ten thouſand times,—for inſinitely more than ten thouſand Ages. <hi>He that made you will not have mercy on you; He that</hi> formed <hi>you will ſhew you</hi> no <hi>Favour.</hi> You ſhall, be baniſhed from the <hi>light</hi> of <hi>his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance</hi> for evermore. Becauſe you would not look unto the Son of God while the day of His patience did continue, you, ſhall miſerably <hi>periſh</hi> when his <hi>wrath</hi> is <hi>kindled</hi> more than a <hi>little.</hi> Then inſtead of the delightful ſound which the <hi>High-Prieſts</hi> Bells do now make, of <hi>Look &amp; be ſaved,</hi> or the <hi>ſilver Trumpets</hi> wherewith the Lord Chriſt doth proclaim a <hi>Jubilee</hi> of <hi>Liberty to Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives,</hi>
                        <pb n="73" facs="tcp:109162:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and <hi>opening of the priſon to them that ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> bound,</hi> you ſhall hear nothing but the Thunder of his exaſperated Jealouſy. Now you have him offering of <hi>Salvation</hi> for a <hi>Look,</hi> but if you are ſuch <hi>deaf Adders</hi> as to diſregard the ſame, you ſhall hearafter <hi>look</hi> unto him, and ſee nothing but Frowns &amp; fierce Lightennings, and flagrant ſparkling Coals of Juniper about him: Alas, in the room thereof you ſhall have from him only thoſe bitter angry aſtoniſhing Words in <hi>Matt. 25. 41. Depart from me ye curſed into everlaſting ſire.</hi> Then, O then all your looks unto him will meet with ſuch confuſion as the Lord ſpeaks of in <hi>Zech. 7. 13. It is come to paſs, as</hi> he <hi>cryed</hi> &amp; they <hi>would not hear, ſo</hi> they <hi>cryed and</hi> I <hi>would not hear, ſaith the Lord.</hi> And will you make ſuch a choice as this, ye children of Folly? You that have a million times bin hearkning to the blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Devil when he has ſaid <hi>ſerve me and take</hi> Hell <hi>for thy pains:</hi> will you not hearken unto that <hi>altogether lovely Lord</hi> who ſaith unto you, <hi>Look unto me,</hi> and <hi>I with all my Salvation will be thine</hi> Verily, the moſt black mouth'd Oathes, and ſoul Uncleanneſſes and filthy Drunkenneſſes of the vileſt <hi>Debauchee,</hi> will not pull down ſorer Puniſhment than this UNBELIEF will bring upon the UNLOOKING Sinners, who will thus render themſelves as the <hi>Fat</hi> of <hi>Lambs</hi> before the <hi>J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STICE</hi> of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:109162:40"/>
for their contemning the <hi>Lamb</hi> of Gods <hi>I pray you Brethren, do not thus wickedly.</hi> O do not for want of a <hi>Look</hi> make it <hi>more tolerable for</hi> Sodom &amp; Gomorrha <hi>in the day of Judgment than for you.</hi> O that the eternal <hi>Spirit</hi> would <hi>rend the heavens &amp; come down</hi> to <hi>rend the hearts</hi> which are ſtill ſhut againſt all the motions that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> does make unto them. It is foretold concerning the Day of the Lord's working upon <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in Iſai. 12. <hi>In that day ſhall a man</hi> look <hi>to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker.</hi> O for the Dawns of ſuch a day upon <hi>us,</hi> wherein it may be ſaid, <hi>In this day, many a man</hi> looks <hi>to his Redeemer.</hi> O that every ſeat within theſe walls might be full of the believing ſouls, who at this moment ſay unto the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, as he in <hi>Pſal. 5. 3. My voice ſhalt Thou hear,</hi> O <hi>Lord, and I will</hi> look up: and who will evermore keep <hi>looking,</hi> and <hi>looking,</hi> and <hi>looking,</hi> unto the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, until He do ariſe &amp; ſave them. <hi> Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <p>BUt what is thus ſaid unto <hi>All</hi> is now mainly to be ſaid unto <hi>One.</hi> I ſee a Condemed Priſoner here, to whom this CALL <hi>of the</hi> GOSPEL is moſt <hi>particulurly</hi> to be directed.</p>
                     <p>The Meſſage which I have to bring unto <hi>You,</hi> is like that which the Prophet once carried unto a better man, O <hi>Set thy</hi> Soul <hi>in order, for thou ſhalt DY and not live.</hi> It is indeed a very ſorrowful thing unto us, to ſee, that a man in his early
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:109162:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>
dayes ſhould thus <hi>dy before his time</hi> for his being <hi>wicked overmuch!</hi> That when half the Age of a man has not paſſ'd over you, a doelful dreadful <hi>Storm</hi> of God does hurry you away from your afflicted <hi>family.</hi> Yea, that <hi>men</hi> do <hi>clap their hands at you,</hi> and <hi>hiſs</hi> you out of your <hi>place.</hi> I hope there are no ſuch flinty bowels here, as do not yern over you: yet the Land muſt not be <hi>pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted</hi> by the ſparing of you. You have <hi>ſlain a man to</hi> your <hi>wounding &amp; a</hi> miſerable <hi>man to</hi> your <hi>hurt.</hi> You that have been wont formerly to ſay of the Sabbath, <hi>What a wearineſs is it?</hi> muſt not now be permitted to draw your breath until the Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of another Sabbath. <hi>Behold</hi> Now <hi>is</hi> your <hi>accepted time,</hi> Now <hi>is</hi> your <hi>day of Salvation.</hi> By that time a few ſwift hours are flown away, your pretious and yet periſhing ſoul is to be hurried away into <hi>Eternity.</hi>—But O what a a ſoul gaſtring word is that, ETERNITY, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TERNITY! If within 4 or 5 days you have not ſecured the <hi>Salvation</hi> of your ſoul <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>looking</hi> unto Jeſus Chriſt, your ſoul, that never-dying Soul of yours, that <hi>Spark of Immortality</hi> which yet takes up its lodging in you, muſt be <hi>broken in the place of dragons,</hi> for as many millions of Years as there are ſtars in the Sky, or drops in the Sea, or ſands on the Shore, and yet be no nearer to the end of the <hi>Gnawes &amp; Scalds</hi> that ſhall over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelw it, than the <hi>firſt</hi> moment that they began<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Some Sips of the cup which is there alwaies in
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:109162:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the trembling hands of the Out-caſt Ones have before now made a man in this world to ſay, <hi>I deſire no greater mitigation of my miſery, than that I might ly in the room of the Back-log behind the fire on my hearth forever.</hi> Suerly you don't intend to try how you can grapple with ſuch a <hi>Damnation</hi> as you are now upon the brink and the Borders of. <hi>Can your heart be ſtrong, or can your hand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> endure in the day that I ſhall deal with you? ſaith the Lord.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I am glad for the ſeemingly penitent <hi>Confeſſion</hi> of your monſtrous Miſcarriages which yeſterday I obtained in writing from you, and which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed was no more than there was need of. But it now remains yet, That you give your <hi>dying Looks</hi> unto the Lord Jeſus Chriſt for <hi>Salvation</hi> from all your Guilt, and from all the Plagues in the <hi>flying Roll</hi> which that does expoſe you to. The Man-ſlayer of old had a <hi>City of Refuge</hi> to befriend him; Behold <hi>I</hi> do this day in the name of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> point you to ſuch an one. O poor ſoul, LOOK, <hi>look</hi> up, and run unto it. O don't ſit down on this ſide a full Reſignation of your ſelf unto Jeſus Chriſt, leſt the Everlaſting and the ever-burning Vengeance of the Almighty do overtake you in your doing ſo. For your Aſſiſtance herein, beſides what <hi>I</hi> have more pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately ſaid to you, ſince you firſt writt to me your deſires of ſpeaking with me, <hi>I</hi> have now only theſe Requeſts to make unto you. My <hi>firſt</hi> Requeſt unto you is,</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="77" facs="tcp:109162:41"/>That you would at <hi>this</hi> hour think of an <hi>inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt</hi> in Jeſus Chriſt, as you will <hi>quickly</hi> at the hour of your <hi>death</hi> &amp; of your <hi>judgment.</hi> Surely when the Executioner is laying the <hi>cloth</hi> of <hi>Death</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver your eyes, the <hi>Look</hi> with the <hi>Shriek</hi> of your ſoul will then ſay, <hi>O now a 1000 worlds for an intereſt in Jeſus Chriſt!</hi> Surely, a few minutes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that, when your naked ſoul ſhall appear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Judgment ſeat of the moſt High, you will again have it over, <hi>An Intereſt in Jeſus Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>s now worth whole mountains of maſſie gold.</hi> O let this be now the <hi>ſettled</hi> opinion of your awakned heart: reckon that if God help you to give <hi>one Look</hi> unto Jeſus Chriſt, it will be a greater mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ey to you than if not only a <hi>life</hi> in this world, but all the <hi>Riches &amp; honour &amp; pleaſures of it</hi> were beſtowed upon you. My <hi>next</hi> Requeſt to you <hi>is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>That you would look upon Jeſus Chriſt, as not only <hi>able</hi> but <hi>willing</hi> to be <hi>your Saviour.</hi> It is true, that you have <hi>murdered</hi> your own ſoul many Thouſands of times, by leading a life of moſt horrid <hi>Impietyes.</hi> It is true that after all you have <hi>murdered</hi> the <hi>Body</hi> (and no thanks to, <hi>you</hi> if not the <hi>ſoul</hi>) of your Neighbour too. Yea, It is true, (and O that the <hi>Rock</hi> in your boſom might <hi>flow</hi> with <hi>tears</hi> at the <hi>ſtroke</hi> of ſuch a thought) that you have by ſin wickedly <hi>murder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> the <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt Himſelf,</hi> Yet, yet is the Lord Jeſus Chriſt from yonder heaven this day pleading with you, <hi>O</hi> look <hi>upon Me as one ready
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:109162:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>
to be thine.</hi> He that ſaies, <hi>Look unto me<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> all ye end<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of the earth,</hi> alſo ſaith, <hi>Poor man, do</hi> thou <hi>look un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me from thy Dungeon, yea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> and when thou ſhalt be at the</hi> end <hi>of the</hi> Town <hi>upon thy</hi> Ladder <hi>alſo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi> Oh Jeſus Chriſt is that Saviour who ſaid once to a Malefactor in the after-noon wherein he was hang'd, <hi>This day ſhalt thou be with me in Paradiſe.</hi> Chriſt is that Saviour who made a <hi>pardoned Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipile</hi> of one from whom he was put to <hi>caſt out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> devils</hi> perhaps as many <hi>fiends</hi> as <hi>your</hi> ſoul has bin the Caſtle of. Multitudes of ſuch bloody crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures as the infamous <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> was have been taken under the merciful wings of Jeſus Chriſt. O thou <hi>Priſoner of hope,</hi> it is not an utterly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible thing, that Jeſus Chriſt ſhould take from the <hi>Gallows</hi> unto <hi>Glory.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>My <hi>Third</hi> Requeſt unto you is, That your <hi>looks</hi> unto <hi>Jeſus</hi> Chriſt may be very <hi>humble,</hi> exceeding <hi>ſincere,</hi> and exceeding <hi>earneſt.</hi> O while you are <hi>looking</hi> to Jeſus Chriſt be <hi>loathing</hi> of <hi>your ſelf.</hi> Abhor and condemn your ſelf as moſt worthy of all the <hi>cruſhes</hi> that you can have in the <hi>wine-preſs</hi> of Omnipotent Fury, of all the <hi>howling Torments</hi> between the Mill-ſtones in the Pit below. And let every <hi>way of wickedneſs</hi> become hateful, yea, <hi>more bitter than death</hi> unto you, as rendring you obnoxious hereunto. Nay, <hi>ſet open</hi> the Door of your ſoul unto the Saviour that is <hi>knocking</hi> at it, for this very thing, that he may make it <hi>an evil a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>d a better thing</hi> unto you, <hi>to for ſake the Lord:</hi>
                        <pb n="79" facs="tcp:109162:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>
for if you go out of the world with any <hi>ſweet morſel</hi> in your mouth or with any harboured be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved <hi>luſt</hi> of which you don't truly ſay, <hi>Lord, turn me from it.</hi> I do moſt ſolemnly teſtify unto you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                        <hi>It had bin good for you that you never had been born<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi> you ſhall becomeas a glowing <hi>Iron</hi> fully poſſeſſed by the hot wrath of God; &amp; you ſhall be made as a <hi>fiery Oven</hi> fill'd with his indignation, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Eaſe, without any End. Be alſo moſt importunate in your Sighs &amp; Cries unto Jeſus Chriſt for ſuch <hi>deſireable</hi> things, urge hard, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> for the life of a ſoul that ſhall <hi>never die.</hi> If the <hi>Court</hi> ſhould ſay to you, <hi>Beg hard &amp; you ſhall live,</hi> Oh how aflectionate would you be! Soul, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt ſaies that thing to you, <hi>If thou canſt heartily</hi> look &amp; beg <hi>thou ſhalt not be hang'd up among the monuments of my vengeance in chain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> of darkneſs forevermore.</hi> How can you now be ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent or ſenſleſs? or not <hi>ſtrive in prayer?</hi> or not <hi>ſtir up your ſelf to take hold</hi> of ſuch <hi>boundleſs mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy?</hi> It was indeed the <hi>inſolent</hi> ſpeech of <hi>Pilate</hi> unto Jeſus Chriſt when he had Him at his Barr, <hi>Speakeſt thou not unto me? knoweſt thou not that I have power to crucify thee, &amp; have power to releaſe thee?</hi> But it is more fitly ſpoken by <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> unto <hi>you, Knoweſt thou not that I have power to deſtroy</hi> thee <hi>ſoul &amp; body in hell forevermore? know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thou not that if thou paſſeſt a day or two more without a due regard unto me, thou canſt not be ſav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed therefrom, tho' the life of all the Angels in heaven
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:109162:43"/>
ſhould be proffered for thy ranſom; and ſpeakeſt tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> not unto Me?</hi> O thou deplorable ſoul, <hi>ſpeak</hi> and <hi>ſeek</hi> and <hi>look</hi> unto Him as for <hi>Life eternal.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>May <hi>laſt</hi> Requeſt unto you is, O give &amp; get all the <hi>Honour</hi> you can unto that Jeſus from whom you <hi>look</hi> for your <hi>Salvation.</hi> While you are ſeck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>look</hi> well unto Him, O ſee that you <hi>ſpeak</hi> well <hi>of</hi> Him, and <hi>do</hi> well <hi>for</hi> Him, until you ſhall <hi>ſpeak</hi> and <hi>do &amp; be</hi> among the living on the earth no more. Surely you have by <hi>preſumptious things</hi> enough <hi>reproached</hi> him already. The ſharp Ax of <hi>Civil Juſtice</hi> will ſpeedily cut you down; O for a little <hi>good fruit</hi> before the blow! Manifeſt your penitence for your <hi>Iniquities</hi> by a due care to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel in tempers quite contrary to thoſe ill <hi>Habits</hi> and <hi>cuſtoms</hi> whereby you have heretofore blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemed the <hi>worthy Name</hi> of Chriſt &amp; <hi>Chriſtianity.</hi> Eſpecially employ the <hi>laſt</hi> minutes of your Life in giving a zealous <hi>Warning</hi> unto others to take need of thoſe things which have bin deſtructive unto you. Tell them what <hi>wild Gourds</hi> of <hi>death</hi> they are by which you have got your Bane; point out before them thoſe <hi>pathes of the deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> which have led you down ſo near unto the <hi>Congregation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>f the dead.</hi> When the numerous croud of <hi>ſpectators</hi> are 3 or 4 days hence throng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed about the place where you ſhall then breathe <hi>your laſt</hi> before them all, then do you with the heart-piercing <hi>groans of a deadly wounded man</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> of your follow-ſinners that they would
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:109162:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                        <hi>turn new every one from the evil of his way.</hi> Beſeech of them to keep clear of <hi>ill Haunts</hi> &amp; <hi>ill Houſes,</hi> with as much dread of them as they could have of lying down in a neſt of poiſonful <hi>Snakes.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech of them to abhor all <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs</hi> as they would the <hi>deep ditch</hi> which <hi>the abhorred of the Lord do fall into.</hi> Beſeech of them to avoid all <hi>Exceſs</hi> in <hi>Drinking</hi> as they would not rott themſelves with more bitter Liquors than the <hi>Waters</hi> of <hi>Jealouſie.</hi> Beſeech of them to moderate and mortifie all inordinate <hi>Paſſions</hi> as they would not ſurrender themſelves into the hands of <hi>Devils</hi> that will hurry them down into <hi>deeper</hi> Deeps than they are aware. Beſeech of them to Shun idle <hi>Swearing</hi> as a <hi>Prophanity</hi> that the <hi>GOD</hi> to whom <hi>Vengeance belongeth</hi> will not permit to go unpuniſhed. Beſeech of them to avoid <hi>Curſes</hi> on themſelves or others, leſt while they like <hi>Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> ſo throw about <hi>fire-brands</hi> &amp; <hi>arrows</hi> &amp; <hi>death,</hi> they bring upon their own heads, as you have done, the things which they are apt raſhly to be wiſhing of. Beſeech of them to beware of <hi>Lying,</hi> as they would not be put to <hi>need</hi> &amp; <hi>crave</hi> &amp; be denied <hi>a drop</hi> of <hi>water</hi> to cool their <hi>tongues</hi> in the place of <hi>Torment.</hi> Beſeech of them to be as averſe to all <hi>Stealing</hi> as they would be to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>coals of fire</hi> into the Neſts that they ſo feather by their diſhoneſty. Beſeech of them to <hi>prize the means of Grace;</hi> to <hi>ſleep</hi> At or <hi>keep from</hi> Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons no more; to love the Habitation of <hi>God's
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:109162:44"/>
houſe,</hi> and the <hi>place</hi> where His Honour dwels leſt God do ſoon ſend their froward barren ſouls to <hi>dwell in ſilence,</hi> where there never ſhall be a <hi>Goſpel-Sermon</hi> heard; never, never as long as the Almighty ſits upon His <hi>Chryſtal Throne.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And when you have given theſe <hi>Warnings</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Ladder</hi> from whence you ſhall not come off without taking an <hi>irrecoverable</hi> ſtep into <hi>eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity;</hi> O remember <hi>ſtill</hi> you give unto <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> the honour of LOOKING to Him for His <hi>Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> Remember that if you would do a work highly for the honour of Him, <hi>This is</hi> The <hi>work of God, that you</hi> Believe on <hi>Him.</hi> Even after your eyes are ſo covered as to take their leave of all ſights below, ſtill continue LOOKING un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Him whom you have heard ſaying, <hi>Look unto Me.</hi> And now let the Everlaſting Saviour LOOK down in much mercy on you: O that He would give this <hi>Murderer</hi> and <hi>extraordinary Sinner,</hi> a place among the <hi>Wonders of free Grace!</hi> O that this wretched man might be made <hi>meet for the Inheritance</hi> with the <hi>Saints in Light;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing kept from ſuch an <hi>unrepenting</hi> and <hi>deluded</hi> heart as <hi>unquenchable fire</hi> will find Fuel in.</p>
                     <p>And be thou pleaſed, O Holy Lord God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty to ſanctifie this Example ſo, that the <hi>Sinners in</hi> this <hi>Zion</hi> may be <hi>afraid,</hi> &amp; that <hi>Fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs may ſurpriſe the Hypocrites thereof,</hi> and <hi>they may all hear, and fear, and do wickedly no more.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>Amen, Amen.</closer>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:109162:44"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:109162:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:109162:45"/>
                  <p>AN <hi>EXHORTATION</hi> To A CONDEMNED MALEFACTOR</p>
                  <p>Delivered <hi>March</hi> the <hi>7th</hi> 1686.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>JOSH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>A MOODY,</hi> Preacher of the Goſpel at <hi>Boſton</hi> in <hi>New-England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Ezek. 33. 9.</bibl>
If thou <hi>warn</hi> the wicked of his way to turn from it, if he do not turn from his way, <hi>he</hi> ſhall dy in his iniquity, but thou ſhalt deliver thy ſoul.</q>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Joſh. 7. 19.</bibl>
—Give glory—to the God of Iſrael and make <hi>Confeſſion</hi> to Him, and tell me what thou haſt <hi>done.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Iſai. 55. 7.</bibl>
Seek the Lord while he may be found, call ye upon him while he is near. Let the wicked forſake his Way, and the unrighteous man his Thoughts, and let him return unto the <hi>Lord,</hi> and He will have mercy upon him, and to our <hi>God,</hi> for He will abundantly pardon.</q>
                  <p>Printed at <hi>BOSTON,</hi> by <hi>R. P.</hi> Anno 1687.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:109162:46"/>
                  <head>To the Reader.</head>
                  <p>IT was the Motion of many, and the Importunity of ſome that drew from me my conſent to make this (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt extemporary) diſcourſe thus public. The Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſent to me on the <hi>After-noon</hi> before the Sabbath, a writing under his hand, wherein he own'd the Juſtice of God in bringing him to this untimely End, and the Righteouſneſs of the Sentence of <hi>Man</hi> upon him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with a Confeſſion of thoſe ſins that he had lived in all his dayes, of which there is ſomething ſpoken in the Sequel: adding 2 Requeſts, <hi>viz.</hi> that I would take ſome <hi>Notice</hi> of <hi>him</hi> in my Sermon, and that I would give <hi>warning</hi> to thoſe of his <hi>Follow</hi>-Siners that had been guilty of the like evils, leſt they alſo become like monuments of divine Juſtice. Such reaſonable requeſts eſpecially from a <hi>dying man</hi> I could not deny. My <hi>Subject</hi> that day was <hi>Iſa. 12. 1.</hi> and my Buſineſs at that time to diſcourſe of the neceſſity, means &amp; marks of the turning away of God's <hi>Anger,</hi> which I judged not unſutable for a perſon in his condition; according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly did, as there was occaſion, apply my ſelf particularly to <hi>him</hi> in my Sermon, which is not ſo proper to inſert here. What was directly ſpoken to himſelf, or to others at his deſire, ſo far at leaſt as my memory would ſerve me<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> is committed to the Preſs, and added as an Appendix to thoſe more ſtudied ſermons which the Lord put into the heart of other of His Servants to <hi>preach</hi> For his ſake that is <hi>gone,</hi> and <hi>publiſh</hi> for the good of <hi>others</hi> that <hi>ſurvive.</hi> The good Lord follow the whole with his bleſſing, and grant that <hi>all Iſrael</hi> may <hi>hear &amp; fear,</hi> ſo that there may no more ſuch great wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs be done in this our Land.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Joſhua Moody<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:109162:46"/>
                  <p>VVHat I have to ſay to the poor condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Priſoner ſhall be under theſe <hi>I we</hi> Heads: <hi>viz.</hi> Something, 1. By way of <hi>Convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> and <hi>Awakning.</hi> 2 By way <hi>Encouragement</hi> and <hi>Counſel.</hi> Firſt, To begin with Matter of <hi>Convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> &amp; Awakening<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and tho' I underſtand he is already ſomewhat conſiderably affected &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, yet more of that may be uſeful for him. And here I ſhall uſe all Plainneſs and Freedom, taking it for granted, that <hi>dying</hi> men are paſt all expectation of Flatteries or Complements, and that plain dealing, which will do <hi>moſt Good,</hi> will find <hi>beſt Acceptance.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>1. Thou ſtandeſt here before the Lord and his People at this Time, as a ſolemn Example of that ſacred Text, <hi>Numb.</hi> 32. 23. You <hi>have ſinned againſt the Lord, and be ſure your ſin will find you out.</hi> This day is this Scripture awfully fulfilled upon you. You have owned under your hand that you have lived all your dayes in thoſe abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable ſins of <hi>Curſing, Swearing, Lying, Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſs</hi> and <hi>Sabbath-breaking,</hi> ſuch ſins as that the <hi>leaſt</hi> of them (however you have made a light matter of them) without deep <hi>Humiliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> &amp; ſincere <hi>Application</hi> to the <hi>Bloud</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> enough to exclude you <hi>forever</hi> from any Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance in the Kingdom of Heaven. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 9<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 10. And thoſe that have been acquainted wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> you think you have not wrong'd your ſelf i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> that Confeſſion. Beſides all the other evils th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="86" facs="tcp:109162:47"/>
your <hi>own heart is privy to,</hi> and many more which the <hi>All-ſeeing God</hi> has obſerved in you. I ſpeak not this to <hi>upraid</hi> you but further to <hi>humble</hi> you, and withal to tell you, that <hi>you glorify</hi> God <hi>by this</hi> Confeſſion <hi>Thus</hi> you ſay you have <hi>liv'd,</hi> and <hi>theſe</hi> ſins you <hi>traded</hi> in, till now at laſt the Lord has left you to commit that <hi>great</hi> &amp; horrendous Sin of <hi>Murder,</hi> in the doing of which you have even <hi>fill'd up your meaſure,</hi> and all the reſt of your ſins do in this one ſin <hi>find you out</hi> and light up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you. You may look at <hi>this</hi> ſin as part of the puniſhment of your former and other ſins. And it is one of the Lord's moſt <hi>righteous,</hi> but withal moſt <hi>tremendous</hi> waies of puniſhing <hi>Sin;</hi> viz. <hi>with Sin,</hi> or <hi>by</hi> Sin: Leſſer ſins are puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by leaving men to <hi>greater</hi> ſins. Thus did the Lord puniſh the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> Rom. 1. 18, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the Apoſtle there calls it the <hi>Revelation of the wrath of God from heaven,</hi> when for their Unthankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs &amp; Vanity <hi>&amp;c.</hi> He <hi>gave them up to vile Aff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ections,</hi> and Actions, among which <hi>Murder</hi> is mentioned as one, <hi>v.</hi> 18.—32. Solomon tells us, <hi>Prov.</hi> 13. 21. that <hi>Evil purſueth ſinners,</hi> and it is true of the Evil of <hi>Sin</hi> and the Evil of <hi>Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment</hi> both, that they do purſue ſinners, tho<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <hi>there</hi> that of <hi>Puniſhment</hi> is properly intended, as appears by the Oppoſition unto the Good which ſhall be <hi>repaid</hi> to the <hi>righteous.</hi> You have bin <hi>purſuing</hi> the evil of <hi>Sin,</hi> and the evil of <hi>Pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhment</hi> hath been in the mean time purſuing <hi>you,</hi> and now you are overtaken &amp; ſeized thereby.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="87" facs="tcp:109162:47"/>2. The Great &amp; terrible God is dreadfully an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry with you for this ſin, &amp; for all the <hi>reſt</hi> that that have bin previous thereunto. The only Subject upon which that fearful thing the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> of <hi>God</hi> falls, is <hi>Sin,</hi> and <hi>Sinners</hi> for <hi>Sin.</hi> All His <hi>own</hi> works are good, his Creatures good, ſo owned &amp; pronounced in <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 31. and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord is pleaſed with them, <hi>SIN</hi> only that is the <hi>Devils</hi> work &amp; <hi>Man's</hi> work, God is angry with. You have heard ſomething e'en now of the nature of God's Anger, but who knowes the <hi>Power</hi> of it. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90. 11. And <hi>you</hi> are the perſon againſt whom this inconceiveable Anger is enkindled; O let this word ſink down into the bottom of thy Heart, and <hi>pierce</hi> thy very ſoul. Say to thy ſelf, <hi>I</hi> am the man with whom the eternal GOD, the Soveraign of the whole World is <hi>angry.</hi> Think on that Text, &amp; let thy heart meditate terror the while, <hi>Pſa. 7. 11. God is</hi> angry <hi>with the wicked</hi> every <hi>day.</hi> While thou wert Curſing, Swearing, Drinking, to exceſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> God was angry with thee, even every one of thoſe dayes was he angry, while thou wert wickedly tranſgreſſing, living in a courſe of open Tranſgreſſion, He was angry all the while; Thou wert conceiving <hi>Sin,</hi> and God was conceiving <hi>Anger,</hi> which is now <hi>brought forth,</hi> tho thou tookſt no notice of it, nor hadſt any dread of it before. Eſpecially He is ſevere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly angry with thee for this execrable Sin of
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:109162:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <hi>Murder,</hi> for which there is no <hi>expiation</hi> but by the <hi>death</hi> of the Murderer; whereof that Reaſon is given <hi>Gen.</hi> 9. 1. becauſe <hi>man</hi> was <hi>made</hi> in <hi>God's Image,</hi> ſo that the Killing of a <hi>man</hi> is the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying of the <hi>image</hi> of <hi>God.</hi> Murder is a Sin againſt the light of Nature; and ſo hainous that the <hi>Barbarians</hi> who had <hi>no</hi> knowledg of the true God, yet concluded that <hi>Vengeance</hi> followed the Murderer up and down<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo that tho' he may eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape for a while, however at length it would not ſuffer him to live. <hi>Act.</hi> 28. 4. Know then that this is the <hi>main</hi> thing thou haſt to think on, this is the moſt terrible thing before thee, not ſo much the <hi>pain</hi> or <hi>ſhame</hi> of the death thou art ſpeedily to undergoe, as the <hi>Anger</hi> of God that comes with it. This is the great Concernment of every man at all times, and of <hi>thee</hi> princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally at <hi>this</hi> time: How ſtand matters between God and <hi>thee?</hi> how is He affected, is He an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry or pleaſed? Why, I tell thee, That God whoſe favour is <hi>life,</hi> and whoſe Wrath is <hi>Death, He</hi> is angry with thee. That Anger of God at which the Heavens ſhake, the Earth moves, the Hills <hi>quake,</hi> the Rocks <hi>rend,</hi> Hell it ſelf <hi>trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles</hi> is now upon thee. The <hi>Devils believe</hi> that there is a God <hi>and tremble,</hi> Jam. 2. 16. do thou believe that, and further that God is <hi>angry</hi> with thee, and tremble at it.</p>
                  <p>3. You are by the Law of God and man, for this Sin declared to be a perſon whom the earth
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:109162:48"/>
cannot bear. The Creation groans under you as a common Enemy to mankind, and one who by the poſitive and indiſpenſable Command of God muſt <hi>fly to the pit and no man</hi> muſt <hi>ſtay you,</hi> Prov. 28. 17. This is the Decree of God, and<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the righteous Sentence of man concerning you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
                  <p>You are yet but a young man, and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ordinary courſe might have lived many years in this world, had not your over-much <hi>Wickedneſs</hi> brought you to <hi>dy before</hi> your <hi>time,</hi> as <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7. 17. Not before <hi>God</hi>'s time, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>your</hi> time, <hi>i. e.</hi> before that time which is uſual for man, whoſe dayes are reckoned <hi>three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore and ten,</hi> and ſometimes <hi>four ſcore</hi> years. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 9. 10. Alſo before your time which probably you had lotted on, and which men too often do promiſe themſelvs. Such as upon any awake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of Conſcience and Calls to Repentance, delay &amp; put it off while in their Youth, it is up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a promiſe of repenting when they are old, and how many in that ſenſe <hi>die before</hi> their <hi>time<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And here for your further awakning, obſerve the Lord in his Providence making good ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dreadful word upon you, viz. that <hi>bloudy</hi> and deceitful men ſhall not live out <hi>half</hi> their dayes, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55. 23. Thus you are a ſon of Death. God and man have ſaid to thee, Oh wicked man, <hi>thou ſhalt ſurely dye.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>4. Your time is numbred and almoſt <hi>finiſhed.</hi> Indeed God has numbred all our times &amp; Year<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:109162:49"/>
and <hi>the number of our months is with him,</hi> Job<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 5. But the number of <hi>your</hi> (I cannot ſay <hi>month<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> but) dayes is with your <hi>ſelf,</hi> you <hi>your ſelf</hi> may number your own dayes; The Lord teach you to apply your heart unto wiſdom while numb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ering them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90. 12. You are juſt now upon the very brink of the Pit, the Grave is ready for you, upon the very <hi>Edge</hi> of <hi>Eternity</hi> are you (I ſay eminently <hi>you</hi>) now walking, &amp; will be within the <hi>line</hi> of it very ſpeedily.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Job</hi> could ſay, when a few <hi>years</hi> are come, then <hi>I</hi> ſhall go the way whence I ſhall not return, <hi>Cap.</hi> 16. 22. But <hi>you</hi> may ſay, Before 4 <hi>dayes</hi> are come &amp; gone, I ſhall be gone to the place from whence I ſhall not return till the very heavens be no more. It made <hi>Belſhazzar's</hi> Countenance to be <hi>changed,</hi> the <hi>joints</hi> of his <hi>loins</hi> to be <hi>looſed,</hi> and his <hi>knees</hi> to <hi>knock one againſt another,</hi> to ſee the <hi>Hand-Writing</hi> upon the <hi>wall.</hi> Dan. 5. 6. and we may imagine (or at leaſt one would think <hi>you</hi> whoſe very caſe it is may imagine) how his thoughts within him were troubled, when the Interpretation laid that dreadful doom up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>himſelf,</hi> that his <hi>Kingdom was numbred &amp; fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed by God,</hi> and it was meant of his <hi>life</hi> &amp; All, which was loſt that night. <hi>v.</hi> 27. 30. It's true, we have <hi>none</hi> of us any <hi>leaſe</hi> of our <hi>lives,</hi> we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſay what may befal us <hi>this</hi> night, and yet (O amazing Madneſs &amp; Folly!) how apt are we (if not to <hi>boaſt</hi> of, yet) to <hi>lot</hi> upon <hi>to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morrow!</hi>
                     <pb n="91" facs="tcp:109162:49"/>
How ready to promiſe to our ſelvs <hi>many<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> years<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> as the Fool in the Goſpel did! <hi>Luc.</hi> 12. 20. who well deſerved the name of <hi>Fool,</hi> had it been for that one evidence of it only.</p>
                  <p>But for <hi>your</hi> part, <hi>you</hi> have your <hi>bounds ſet,</hi> &amp; told you, beyond which you cannot paſs; you know at the utmoſt the Date of your life, and Day of your <hi>Death,</hi> you may die <hi>ſonner,</hi> but you muſt not live <hi>longer,</hi> your end is in your view, you have but a few ſteps thither, and had not need take any <hi>vain,</hi> unprofitable or <hi>falſe</hi> ones.</p>
                  <p>You ſeem to bewail your ſin of <hi>Sabbath-break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> well, know that you ſhall never have an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Sabbath to break.—The Lord help you to keep <hi>this</hi> as you ought. I cannot paſs this particular without once more commending it to your ſerious Conſideration; O chew upon it, dwell upon it, that <hi>a few hours hence you ſhall cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly dye.</hi> It's a very awful thing to us to look upon you, a perſon in your Youth, Health, and Strength, <hi>Breaſts full of milk,</hi> and <hi>Bones moiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ned with marrow,</hi> and then to think that within ſo many daies this man, tho' in his full Strength muſt dy: and methinks it ſhould be much more awful to <hi>you.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>5. Your <hi>Death</hi> will not <hi>expi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>te</hi> your <hi>Offence</hi> in the ſight of God, nor cauſe the <hi>Turning away of His Anger from you:</hi> Its true the <hi>ſhedding of your bloud</hi> will take away, the Sin from the <hi>Land</hi> that it ſhall no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ly there, elſe innocent bloud
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:109162:50"/>
ſhould be imputed to the Land; but this doe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> nothing towards the Satisfaction of <hi>Gods Juſtic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> in order to the Removal of his wrath from the <hi>Murderer.</hi> Puniſhment makes no amends for Sin, unleſs it be that which was inflicted upon <hi>Chriſt</hi> as he ſtood in the capacity of a Surety in behalf of the Elect, and ſo bare both their ſin and their puniſhment, but otherwiſe <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ll</hi> torments don't ſatisfy God's Juſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ce nor quench the fire of his wrath, muchleſs can any bodily ſuffering do it, tho it be the <hi>higheſt,</hi> even <hi>death</hi> it ſelf. Do not then deceive your ſelf; Say not I have ſinned, its true, but am now to ſuffer the Law, and <hi>that</hi> being undergone I ſhall then be quitt. It is ſo indeed as to any thing that <hi>men</hi> can do to thee, but thy death does not at all deliver thee out of the hands of <hi>Divine</hi> Juſtice. Nay rather <hi>Sixthly,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If you get not this Sin and all the reſt of your ſins done away, and ſo the Anger of God remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, your approaching Death will be but the beginning of Sorrows to you. However ſenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally or like a Beaſt (or worſe) you have <hi>lived,</hi> you ſhall not <hi>dye</hi> as Beaſts dye, ſo as that there ſhall be an end of you and all your ſufferings together: No, no ſuch matter. Your precious immortal ſoul muſt live forever, and if you get not the fire of God's Anger put out, Know that there is a Fire kindled in his anger that ſhall burn to the loweſt Hell. Without Repentance
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:109162:50"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>to <hi>life</hi> (which is the gift of Chriſt, and for your Comfort I tell you in the midſt of all theſe bitter things I have been ſpeaking to you, he is freely willing to give it, even to <hi>you:</hi> Oh look up to Him heartily for the ſame, I ſay unleſs you get this <hi>Repentance unto life</hi>) your death is but an <hi>In-let</hi> to the <hi>Second death.</hi> No ſooner ſhall your guilty ſoul be forced out of your wretched body, but it ſhall appear before God <hi>that gave it,</hi> there to receive <hi>another</hi> manner of Sentence of Condemnation than what you have already heard from <hi>man,</hi> by which you were condemned to dye, but there was room for a <hi>Lord have</hi> Mercy <hi>on your ſoul,</hi> to be annexed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whereas in <hi>that</hi> Sentence there will be <hi>no</hi> mercy upon your ſoul, for your ſoul is the principal ſubject of the <hi>2nd.</hi> death. Separating your ſoul and body aſunder was the <hi>aim</hi> and will be the <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſſue</hi> of this Sentence, but the death &amp; everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, utter loſs of your <hi>ſoul</hi> (for which nothing can be given to God in <hi>Exchange</hi> Mat. 16. 26.) will be the meaning of this Sentence. The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſhall your <hi>ſoul</hi> be <hi>committed into</hi> &amp; <hi>left</hi> in the <hi>hands</hi> of the Devil your maſter, whom you have ſerved, that great Murderer &amp; Lyar (who was ſo <hi>from the beginning,</hi> and is the father &amp; lord of ſuch) to be dragged down by him into the place where your fellow-Murderers and fellow-Lyars and fellow-Drunkards are, <hi>viz. into the lake that burns with fire &amp; brimſtone, which is the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:109162:51"/>
ſecond death.</hi> Rev. 21. 8. there to be tormented with the Devil &amp; his angels, where the Worm never dyeth, and the fire never ſhall be quench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. <hi>Marc.</hi> 9. 43. 44. You have a ſcareing vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6. 8. of one whoſe name was <hi>Death</hi> ſitting on a pale horſe, that viſion is now before you and it cannot but be very terrible and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighting, but the main terror lies in what comes <hi>after,</hi> Hell followes it, Hell followes Death hard at the heels. Death is but the door between the two worlds, that lets the ſoul of a Chriſtleſs ſinner out of this world into Hell. The Second Death after the firſt, is the miſery of the firſt, and the firſt would be compartively but a ſmall matter were it not for the ſecond.</p>
                  <p>7. <hi>Finally,</hi> Conſider you have no time to get ſin pardoned &amp; wrath <hi>turned away</hi> (if it be not done already) but between this and Death, <hi>into</hi> the very <hi>Borders,</hi> and <hi>under</hi> the <hi>Sentence of which</hi> you now are. <hi>In the grave there is no repentance,</hi> no Remiſſion, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 9. 10. Before 4 dayes more paſs over your head (and Oh how ſwiftly do they <hi>fly</hi> away!) you will be entred into an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal &amp; unchangeable ſtate of <hi>weal</hi> or <hi>woe,</hi> and of Woe it will be if ſpeedy and thorough Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance prevent it not.</p>
                  <p>Thus far by way of Conviction &amp; Awakning. My <hi>2nd</hi> Word is principally by way of <hi>Counſel.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Unto which I ſhall promiſe a Word of <hi>Encour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agement,</hi> leſt what has bin ſaid may ſeem to harſh
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:109162:51"/>
and ſevere to a man in his Condition. But the Wound muſt be opened &amp; ſearched before the Plaiſter be laid on; and there is a Plaiſter as large as the ſore, the <hi>Lord</hi> in mercy make it <hi>ſtick.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Know then, That notwithſtanding all that has bin ſpoken, there is <hi>Hope in Iſrael concerning this thing.</hi> There is a way <hi>found out &amp; reveal'd</hi> by <hi>God</hi> for the <hi>Turning of His Anger</hi> even from ſuch ſinners. The bloud of Jeſus can waſh away the guilt of the <hi>ſin</hi> of <hi>ſheddng</hi> man's blood, for which no Ranſome may be taken by man, yet God ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> found out a Ranſome, and does now graciuoſly offer thee the benefit of it.—<hi>Paul</hi> was a <hi>Murderer</hi> and yet pardoned. <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> made the ſtreets of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to <hi>ſwim</hi> with innocent bloud, and yet was <hi>forgiven.</hi> Nay the greateſt Murderers that ever were in the world, even thoſe that imbrewed their wicked hands in the bloud of the <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>GOD</hi> were, many of them, converted &amp; reconciled to God; and are now in heaven beholding the Glory<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of that Chriſt whom they Crucifyed, <hi>Act.</hi> 2. And ſeveral o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers who were under the ſame Condemnation, were exhorted in the <hi>following</hi> Chapter to <hi>repent</hi> &amp; to be <hi>converted,</hi> and were thereupon promis'd that their ſins ſhould be blotted out. <hi>ver.</hi> 29.</p>
                  <p>It is true that <hi>no murderer hath eternal life. 1. Joh.</hi> 3. 15. and that <hi>Drunkards ſhall not inherit the Kingdom of God,</hi> 1. Cor. 6. 10. and yet the next words ſay (<hi>ver.</hi> 11.) <hi>ſuch</hi> were <hi>ſome of</hi> you, <hi>but
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:109162:52"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="95" facs="tcp:109162:52"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="96" facs="tcp:109162:53"/>
you</hi> are <hi>waſhed, ſanctifyed, juſtifyed.</hi> If all Sins and Blaſphemy againſt the <hi>Son of Man</hi> may be forgiven, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12. 31. 22. then this Sin againſt one of the <hi>ſons of men</hi> may be forgiven too. God can pardon great ſins, yea, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore or the rather pardon them becauſe <hi>great, Pſal</hi> 25. 11. And He does delight, where Sin has abounded to make Grace <hi>ſuper-abound,</hi> Rom. 5. 20. And ſo I come to my word of <hi>Counſel.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And Oh let my <hi>Counſel</hi> be <hi>acceptable</hi> to <hi>thee,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou be driven out from among <hi>men,</hi> &amp; put beyond all <hi>poſſibility</hi> of <hi>hearing</hi> or <hi>taking</hi> counſel.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>See</hi> &amp; be yet more <hi>affected</hi> with this deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable condition, and let thy <hi>ſoul</hi> be <hi>afflicted</hi> at the thoughts of it, and eſpecially at thy <hi>ſin</hi> that has brought thee into it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I urge this again becauſe thou canſt not be too <hi>much concerned</hi> thereabout.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Look upon all thy life paſt:</hi> let this ſolemn hand of God upon thee bring all thy ſins to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance. Conſider how thou haſt walked in a Courſe of ſin from <hi>ſtep</hi> to <hi>ſtep,</hi> and let all thy <hi>Actual</hi> ſins lead thee back to the Sin of thy <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> the evil <hi>Fountain</hi> from whence all theſe bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſtreams have iſſued; and let all put together make thee vile in thine own eyes, and make thee to abhor thy ſelf for the ſame.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Beg hard for a broken heart,</hi> that may <hi>unfeign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly</hi> mourn for ſin, that being burdened with it thou mayſt moſt <hi>bitterly weep,</hi> and ſigh &amp; groan under it. Such ſins as thou ſtandeſt Convicted
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:109162:53"/>
of call for the deepeſt Humiliation &amp; Contriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Its the bane of multitudes of Sinners in the world, that their Convictions of <hi>Sin</hi> were but <hi>ſleighty</hi> and their Humiliation <hi>ſuperficial,</hi> and ſo their Converſion not real. God <hi>will prick thee to the heart,</hi> yea and <hi>break</hi> thy Heart all to <hi>pieces</hi> for thy ſin if ever he pardon thee. Alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moan thy ſelf for all thy Prophanneſs, Looſneſs, Senſuality which has expoſed thee to this great ſin at laſt. Bewail all thoſe evils which the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly God has to charge thee with; thy <hi>Rending</hi> His Sacred name by <hi>Curſes</hi> &amp; <hi>Oaths,</hi> wronging His <hi>Truth</hi> by <hi>Lying,</hi> Abuſing his good <hi>Creatures</hi> to <hi>Exceſs,</hi> Making thy <hi>Belly</hi> thy <hi>god,</hi> and ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficeing the Lord's Bleſſings thereunto, which he lent thee for His <hi>own</hi> Uſe and Service; And e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially for thy <hi>rejecting</hi> of his Goſpel, of which great and horrible ſin, thou art convicted out of thy own mouth, while thou wert profaning his Sabbaths, &amp; neglecting to give thy Attendance on the publick Worſhip, and ſo turning away thine Ear from Hearing the <hi>joyful ſound</hi> by which thou mightſt have been forever <hi>bleſſed.</hi>—</p>
                  <p>Let all theſe be remembred, and be as Gall and Wormwood to thy ſoul.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Acknowledge an <hi>Holy &amp; Righteous hand of God in leaving thee to</hi> this <hi>great Tranſgreſſion.</hi> Confeſs what <hi>thou</hi> haſt done and <hi>give glory to God</hi> for what <hi>He has done:</hi> Say, <hi>He is</hi> juſt <hi>for I have ſinned.</hi> Yea, and glorify him for <hi>this,</hi> that He
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:109162:54"/>
can make even this <hi>Sin,</hi> at leaſt the puniſhment Attending it, a means to bring thee to Repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance for all the <hi>reſt</hi> of thy ſins which elſe thou mighteſt have gone on ſecurely in, unto endleſs Perdition. This prodigious ſin of Murder, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with thy being brought to Condign Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment for the ſame, may (through the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign Grace of God, who can bring good out of <hi>evil</hi>) be an occaſion by its loud cry of blood in thine ears to awaken thee out of that ſleep from which thou mightſt elſe have <hi>never</hi> awak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, till <hi>everlaſting burnings</hi> had awakned thee. The Lord bleſſed <hi>Manaſſeh's</hi> being brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chains to put him upon ſeeking the God of his Fathers; and the ſame God can bleſs <hi>this</hi> Chain with which <hi>thou</hi> art now bound, as a means to bring thee to everlaſting <hi>Liberty.</hi> It's one of the Lords wayes of Dealing with men to bring them to good, <hi>viz.</hi> when they are bound in Fetters, and holden in Cords of Affliction, to ſhew them their work and their Tranſgreſſion that they have exceeded in, and then to open their ears to <hi>Diſcipline</hi> and to command them to return <hi>Job.</hi> 36. 8. 9. 10. Yea, and he can cauſe them to return by <hi>Sealing</hi> Inſtruction at ſuch a Time and in ſuch a way. Thus can the Lord bring back thy <hi>ſoul</hi> from the pit tho' thy body muſt go thither. It is I confeſs a ſtrange way to leave men to undo themſelves, thereby to prevent their being everlaſtingly undone: But
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:109162:54"/>
doubtleſs there have been ſuch Examples in the world, of men that have been thus ſaved; and who can tell but <hi>thou</hi> mayſt make one more?</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Heartily bleſs God, and wonder at His Kindneſs therein, that He did not ſuddenly take thee away with His ſtroke, as He has done ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch a ſinner as thou haſt been. Many a Drunkard has ſtaggered and reeled into the <hi>Pit,</hi> has dropt into <hi>Hell</hi> in a moment, and gone <hi>full of Drink</hi> into the place where there is not a <hi>drop of water</hi> to <hi>cool his tongue.</hi> Bleſs Him that he did not choak thee with a <hi>Lye</hi> in thy mouth, or make thee <hi>fall down dead</hi> as ſoon as ever thou haſt vented it. So were <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Sapphira<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> ſerv'd, <hi>Act.</hi> 5. 5,—10. Bleſs him that He did not ſtop thy breath juſt when ſome execrable <hi>Curſe</hi> or <hi>Oath</hi> was out of the evil Treaſury of thy filtthy rotten heart crawling up that <hi>open Sepulchre</hi> of thy <hi>throat.</hi> Bleſs him that he did not ſtrike thee dead in the place when thou wert profaning of His Sabbaths and for not <hi>ſanctifying</hi> that <hi>holy Reſt</hi> unto God, that He did not in the twinkling of an eye ſend thee to the place where thou ſhould have <hi>no reſt,</hi> night nor day. O bleſs him for this time of <hi>Patience</hi> and <hi>Forbearance;</hi> for a <hi>ſpace to repent</hi> that Divine Long-ſuffering has afforded thee. Bleſs Him that He has given <hi>thee</hi> a <hi>longer</hi> time of <hi>Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> &amp; Preparation for a latter end, that that poor wretch had who was by thy cruel hand
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:109162:55"/>
hurried away into Eternity in a little time. When thou gaveſt him his death's wound, <hi>Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance</hi> might have given <hi>thee</hi> a fatal ſtroak, and ſent thee to thy <hi>own place</hi> before him. But he is gone, and thou art left, and forborn a little (tho' but for a very little) longer;—let the Goodneſs of God lead thee to Repentance.</p>
                  <p>6. See that of thy <hi>ſelf</hi> thou haſt no way left to ſatisfy Juſtice or pacify divine Anger. Say within thy ſelf, <hi>Wherewith ſhall I come before the Lord, before whoſe dreadful Tribunal I muſt appear within a few hours?</hi> And then ſay to thy ſelf, <hi>I have no thouſands of rams nor 10 thouſands of rivers of oyl:</hi> and if thou hadſt, hear the Lord ſaying to thee that they would avail nothing; no, nor would the <hi>firſt-born</hi> of thy Body be an expiation for the ſin of thy <hi>ſoul.</hi> All thy <hi>confeſſions, prayers, tears</hi> will not anſwer for the leaſt of a <hi>Thouſand</hi> of thoſe ſins, under the guilt of which thy ſoul is now lying. Shouldeſt thou ſpend every pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious <hi>moment</hi> of thy ſhort time in <hi>Confeſſing Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ying, fighing, groaning, weeping,</hi> all that would not doe. No, no: Here thou ſtandeſt, a guilty Creature, condemned of God &amp; man; and canſt not ſtrike one ſtroke toward thy own Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on nor deſerve that God ſhould do it for thee. God has judged thee, and <hi>men</hi> have judged thee worthy of Death, and do thou judge thy ſelf worthy of <hi>Damnation</hi> too. A ſelf-judging and ſelf-condemning frame is a ſuitable frame for thee to be in this day.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="101" facs="tcp:109162:55" rendition="simple:additions"/>7. Humbly &amp; heartily, like a poor, laborious <hi>heavy laden,</hi> periſhing, ſhiftleſs Creature, caſt thy ſelf down at the Footſtool of the <hi>Throne of Grace</hi> crying and looking for the Mercy of God through the Merits of Chriſt unto thy Pardon &amp; Acceptance. And Oh the <hi>height</hi> and <hi>depth</hi> and <hi>length</hi> and <hi>breadth</hi> of the <hi>Grace of God</hi> in <hi>Chriſt!</hi> There's room for a <hi>Curſer, Swearer, Lyar, Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kard,</hi> yea and a <hi>Murderer</hi> too, to ly at that Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtool with hope. Then <hi>fly for refuge to lay hold on that hope that is ſet before</hi> thee <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. 18. Flee away to the <hi>City of Refuge,</hi> and I do aſſure thee from God that the Door ſtands ready to receive thee: and Oh <hi>make haſte</hi> for the <hi>Aveng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of blood</hi> is at thy very heels. The <hi>City of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge</hi> under the <hi>Old Teſtament</hi> was only to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the <hi>Man-ſlayer,</hi> not the <hi>Murderer,</hi> him that killed a man <hi>unwittingly</hi> and <hi>unwillingly,</hi> while the <hi>wilful Murderer</hi> was by expreſs Command from God to be deliver'd up: But herein (as in all other things) does the Antitype out doe the Type. Jeſus Chriſt who was and is the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of that ſhaddow invites <hi>Murderer</hi> as well as <hi>Man-ſlayer;</hi> and has declared it to be the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's</hi> Will and his own Reſolution that <hi>whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever comes to Him He will in no wiſe caſt out.</hi> Joh. 6. 37. The ſame Advice which was given to the Murderers of Chriſt (as has been hinted to thee <hi>Act.</hi> 3. 20.) I do now in the name of the Lord give to thee, <hi>Repent and receive Chriſt,</hi>
                     <pb n="102" facs="tcp:109162:56"/>
and thou ſhalt be ſaved. Thou haſt ſorely an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gered God already by all that Courſe of ſin that thou haſt lived in, and principally by this laſt great ſin that thou art condemned for; now do not anger Him yet more by neglecting to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace his <hi>Son.</hi> Thou haſt done all theſe <hi>Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes,</hi> now don't <hi>add</hi> to all the reſt that which will be <hi>unſpeakably more</hi> than all the reſt, <hi>the reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of a Saviour;</hi> yea of a Saviour thus <hi>openly, free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, heartily, offering himſelf</hi> to thee, even to <hi>thee</hi> in <hi>particular</hi> in this ſolemn Ordinance, and that as <hi>verily</hi> &amp; as <hi>really</hi> as if He ſhould by an <hi>audible</hi> voice call to thee by name from Heaven and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite thee to come.</p>
                  <p>Set thy heart to theſe things that from the Lord I am Teſtifying to thee this day, <hi>for they are thy life.</hi> Hearken then, as for thy <hi>life,</hi> as for thy <hi>laſt,</hi> or at leaſt that which is <hi>next to thy laſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And that which I have to ſay to thee is this,</p>
                  <p>Behold Jeſus Chriſt is for thy ſake come into this <hi>place</hi> this <hi>day,</hi> this <hi>Sabbath,</hi> this <hi>thy laſt</hi> Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, which ſhould therefore be a <hi>great</hi> Day to thee, and here He ſtands, &amp; cries to thee, that if thy guilty ſoul be <hi>heated</hi> &amp; <hi>ſcorcht</hi> by God's <hi>Anger</hi> and made <hi>thirſty</hi> after <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> which may put out that <hi>flame,</hi> &amp; allay that <hi>heat,</hi> and in which thou mayſt be found in that day, Lo, here it is for thee; <hi>Open thy mouth wide, and He will abundantly ſatisfy thee.</hi> Hear Chriſt ſaying to thee, <hi>Thou condemned Malefactor, I pitty thy
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:109162:56"/>
caſe, my bowels do yern over thee, and tho' dye thou muſt by a violent death, as to the taking away thy</hi> bodily <hi>life, yet I profeſs I have no delight in thy deſtruction, I have no pleaſure in thy death, and tho, thou</hi> dye <hi>Temporally, I would have thee</hi> live <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally.</hi> Again, hear the ſame Lord Jeſus asking thee &amp; expoſtulating the caſe about thy ſoul, <hi>What doeſt thou mean to do with thy ſoul? whither ſhall it got when it leaves thy body? what care haſt thou taken about it? I'm afraid but little hitherto. Haſt thou provided a place of reſt for it?</hi> Why if thou be at a loTs (and it is a good ſtep to thy being <hi>found</hi> if thou doſt <hi>feel</hi> thy ſelf <hi>loſt</hi>) if thou art <hi>afraid</hi> leſt the <hi>devil</hi> ſhould get it at <hi>laſt,</hi> whoſe ſlave thou haſt <hi>too much</hi> bin all thy days and art willing to be effectually eaſed of that fear, why then, (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>Give it me, while it is yet thy</hi> own <hi>ſoul and thou art poſſeſſor of it, let me have it alienated unto</hi> Me; <hi>it is indeed a ſilly, ſorry, guilty, bloody ſoul, but be it as it is, give it me, I know how to take &amp; waſh &amp; cleanſe &amp; keep</hi> &amp; ſave it. <hi>Don't deny me, I have often</hi> asked <hi>thy heart &amp; ſoul of thee, and could never yet get a grant of thee I ask it</hi> once <hi>more, and it is one of the</hi> laſt <hi>times that I ſhall ask it, and I came</hi> this <hi>day into</hi> this <hi>Ordinance on purpoſe to be ſpake thy ſoul that I may</hi> have <hi>it for my</hi> ſelf, <hi>and</hi> ſave <hi>it for</hi> thee. Why <hi>thus</hi> is Chriſt urging, intreating, pleading with thee, &amp; even <hi>forceing</hi> himſelf upon thee by His Importunity. How canſt thou ſend Him away
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:109162:57" rendition="simple:additions"/>
grieved for want of His Errand! Eſpecially conſider that if thou do not <hi>voluntarily &amp; freely</hi> (Oh pray hard that in this <hi>day of power</hi> He will make thy ſoul a <hi>willing</hi> ſoul) give thy ſoul to Chriſt <hi>preſently,</hi> the Devil will have it quickly whether thou wilt or no.</p>
                  <p>Thou haſt then before thee this one <hi>great Duty</hi> of <hi>Beleeving,</hi> and He ſayes to thee this day, only <hi>believe;</hi> and <hi>that</hi>'s my <hi>great Counſel</hi> in His Name.</p>
                  <p>If thou ask, <hi>What is Believing on Chriſt?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>1 Anſwer,</hi> It is for a poor, ſinning, damned ſoul that is paſt ſtanding in himſelf, humbly to fall down before him, and proſtrate it ſelf at His feet, that He may ſave it. It is to commit thy ſoul into the hands of Chriſt, believing that He is <hi>able</hi> to keep what thou haſt committed to Him until <hi>that Day.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I am informed that thou didſt this morning hear a precious Diſcourſe in <hi>another</hi> Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, from that moſt <hi>ſuitable</hi> and <hi>ſeaſonable</hi> Text (Iſai. 45. 22.) <hi>Look unto me and be ye ſaved all ye ends of the earth.</hi> Why <hi>that is Beleeving;</hi> viz. <hi>Looking</hi> to Jeſus for <hi>Salvation.</hi> Looking <hi>to</hi> and <hi>taking</hi> Him <hi>as</hi> thy <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Saviour.</hi> One ſuch humble hearty <hi>Look will ſave thee,</hi> which if thou canſt but do before thou go'ſt out of this world, then thoſe that have bin affectionately and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely <hi>looking</hi> up to God for thee, ſhall find thee to their great Joy &amp; Comfort at the <hi>right</hi> hand of Chriſt in the <hi>day of His appearing</hi> among
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:109162:57"/>
thoſe <hi>ſheep that heard His voice and followed Him,</hi> tho' <hi>thou</hi> didſt never hear him till one of the <hi>laſt</hi> of his voices, nor <hi>follow him at all unleſs</hi> it were with ſome of thy <hi>lateſt</hi> Steps. And it will be <hi>magnifyed</hi> Mercy, <hi>amazing</hi> Mercy if it be ſo.</p>
                  <p>The Lord grant it may be ſo.</p>
                  <p>Only <hi>remember</hi> alſo, that is <hi>no eaſy</hi> matter to <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve,</hi> no <hi>eaſy matter</hi> to <hi>repent,</hi> and if thou know'ſt ought of the <hi>nature</hi> of each, thou haſt <hi>experienced</hi> it ſo to be. <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Repentance</hi> are the gift of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> ask them of <hi>Him,</hi> and be well aſſur'd that He is more ready to <hi>give,</hi> than thou art to <hi>ask.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And if the Lord help thee <hi>now</hi> to <hi>believe,</hi> i. e. to <hi>receive</hi> and <hi>take up</hi> with <hi>Chriſt</hi> as thy <hi>Lord &amp; Saviour,</hi> thou ſhalt <hi>give glory to God</hi> by <hi>believing,</hi> and the Lord will account Himſelf, by the <hi>righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which by Faith thou laidſt hold on, <hi>abundantly ſatisfyed</hi> for all the Disho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour thou haſt done to Him all thy dayes.</p>
                  <p>Now if any thing will break a hard heart, ſure it is the affectionate warming yea <hi>melting Offers</hi> of the Grace of <hi>Chriſt in the Goſpel</hi> unto a Perſon ſo vile that might be ready enough to fear he had ſinn'd himſelf into an eſtate <hi>beneath,</hi> &amp; out of the <hi>reach</hi> of <hi>Mercy.</hi> And Oh be <hi>ſpeedy</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout this work: almoſt all thy dayes are rolled away in <hi>Gods anger,</hi> thou mayſt count the few hours that are left thee, don't loſe an hour, a <hi>Minute;</hi> ſpend every one of them ſeriouſly in Reading, Meditation, Prayer, good Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, Asking Queſtions of and Hearing Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:109162:58"/>
                     <hi>from</hi> any that are concern'd for thy ſoul,</p>
                  <p>Let it appear to all that look on thee that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſo much <hi>miſpence &amp; loſs</hi> of <hi>precious time,</hi> the <hi>ſcarcity</hi> of it has raiſed the <hi>price</hi> with thee. Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>thee</hi> may it be moſt truly ſaid <hi>Now or Never.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And becauſe he deſires it, bear with me while I offer a Word of <hi>Warning &amp; Council</hi> to <hi>others.</hi> And it is commendable to ſee ſuch a perſon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireous to have his <hi>Companions</hi> in ſin <hi>warned</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Are there any that hear me (and I wiſh there were not <hi>many</hi>) who are guilty of <hi>Lying, Curſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Swearing, Drunkenneſs</hi> let me ſay to you,</p>
                  <p>You may not expect to have any <hi>come from the dead</hi> to warn you, but here is one that is juſt <hi>going to</hi> the dead who bequeathes you this <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,</hi> leſt <hi>you</hi> alſo be in like manner hung up as <hi>Monuments</hi> of God's <hi>wrath.</hi> God is picking him out, and <hi>ſeting him forth to be an Example</hi> unto you <hi>Jude.</hi> 7. He might as righteouſly have left ſome of <hi>you</hi> to have bin examples unto <hi>him</hi> and others; but unto the holy Soveraign Counſel of God it has ſeemed <hi>meet</hi> to <hi>take him</hi> and <hi>leave you,</hi> and in <hi>taking him</hi> has <hi>left you</hi> that ſolemn war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning which if you take it not, ſhall be a Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony againſt you in <hi>that Day.</hi> And becauſe he in his Writing deſir'd me that I would ſpeak ſomething to <hi>Young men,</hi> I would alſo deſire <hi>them</hi> eſpecially to mind what is ſaid, tho' as it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns all, let <hi>every one</hi> take his portion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="107" facs="tcp:109162:58" rendition="simple:additions"/>See wither leſſer ſins will lead you, even unto <hi>greater</hi> till at <hi>laſt</hi> you come to the <hi>Great Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion.</hi> Your frequent <hi>ſwallowing of Gnats</hi> will make you not to ſtick at <hi>Camels. Cuſtom</hi> of ſin will take away <hi>Conſcience</hi> of Sin; and when Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of ſin is <hi>gone,</hi> what ſin is there that you are not ready for?</p>
                  <p>I ſhall ſpeak a few words to each of thoſe Sins which he <hi>Wills</hi> them a Warning againſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Curſing &amp; Swearing</hi> begin to grow <hi>common</hi> in this Land. It was not ſo in our <hi>firſt</hi> dayes. I lived near 20 years in this Countrey before <hi>I</hi> heard an Oath or a Curſe. But <hi>now</hi> as you paſs along in the <hi>ſtreets,</hi> you may hear <hi>children curſe</hi> and <hi>Swear,</hi> and take the great &amp; dreadful Name of God in vain. They have learnt it from el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der perſons. Wo to thoſe that taught them if they repent not. The <hi>Lord will not hold you guiltleſs:</hi> You ſhall anſwer not only for your <hi>own</hi> Oaths &amp; Curſes &amp; Blaſphemings of God's Name, but for the ſins of thoſe <hi>Children</hi> whom you have taught, yea <hi>made</hi> to ſin. It has al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes bin the great deſign of Satan to debauch the Profeſſors of Religion; hence he ſuggeſted to <hi>Balaam</hi> the Counſel which he gave to <hi>Balak</hi> to <hi>draw Iſrael</hi> unto ſin, to <hi>debauch</hi> the <hi>Youth,</hi> and then he need not hire any to curſe them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their holy God would be <hi>wroth</hi> with them: and its dreadful to think what ſucceſs the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of the Devil have had of late years
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:109162:59"/>
in this Land. Thoſe that vainly <hi>ſwear,</hi> let 'em read what <hi>Jeſus Chriſt the Judg of all</hi> ſaith, (and He is a Judge that <hi>ſtands at the door</hi> and heares and is ready to <hi>judge both the quick</hi> and <hi>the dead,</hi> (Jam. 5. 9. with <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. 5.) I ſay hear Him ſpeaking thus (<hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 34.) <hi>I ſay unto you,</hi> (and there is a great deal of weight to be laid upon that Introduction, <hi>I ſay unto you ſwear not at all.</hi> The ſame is alſo repeated by the Apoſtle <hi>James<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> Cap. 5. 12. where note the form of <hi>vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency &amp; earneſtneſs</hi> (as one calls it) in which He propounds it, Above all things, <hi>Swear</hi> not, it being a great Sin much in uſe, and when ſo, it is hardeſt left:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>v.</hi> Manton in Locum.</note> therefore above all things do not ſwear, and its enforced from the danger of <hi>falling into Condemnation.</hi> I remember what pious <hi>Herbert</hi> ſaith in his <hi>Advice</hi> to <hi>young men,</hi> that the <hi>Swearer</hi> has neither any <hi>fair</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence for <hi>doing it,</hi> nor <hi>excuſe</hi> when <hi>done,</hi> either from pleaſure or profit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and adds, <hi>that if an</hi> Epicure <hi>he could forbear Swearing.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As to <hi>Curſing</hi> I ſhall commend that ſolemn <hi>Text</hi> to all that are guilty of it <hi>Pſa.</hi> 109. 17, 18, 19.) <hi>As he loved Curſing, ſo let it come unto him, &amp;c. let it come into his bowels like water and oyl into his bones.</hi> The cauſeleſs Curſe, ſhall not come (<hi>Pro.</hi> 26. 2.) unleſs it be upon the head of him that vented it. The Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> inveighs againſt it among the evils of an <hi>unruly Tongue,</hi> intimat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how abſurd it is, that <hi>out of the ſame mouth</hi>
                     <pb n="109" facs="tcp:109162:59"/>
ſhould <hi>proceed bleſſing &amp; curſing,</hi> that we ſhould <hi>bleſs</hi> God, and <hi>curſe</hi> men that are made in the ſame <hi>Image,</hi> with the ſame <hi>Tongue Cap.</hi> 3. 9, 10. If ever you deſire to be <hi>bleſt,</hi> hate &amp; ſhun <hi>Curſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> God will curſe them that curſe.</p>
                  <p>The next is <hi>Lying,</hi> a Sin that we learn from the Womb, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 58. 3. and can hardly leave it when <hi>old.</hi> Hence <hi>David</hi> ſaw need to pray to be kept from the way of Lying <hi>Pſ.</hi> 119. 27. A ſin emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently contrary and ſo diſpleaſing unto God, as He calls Himſelf a <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Truth,</hi> and yet I may truly ſay, a Sin much predominant among us.</p>
                  <p>We have had <hi>Truths</hi> Monthly <hi>Market</hi> kept of late in this place: and Truth has ſolemnly bin expoſed to Sale, in that faithful &amp; true witneſs that has been born to the <hi>worth</hi> of Truth, from that Text <hi>Prov.</hi> 23. 23. and it has bin offer'd a very good peniworth; what <hi>Buyers</hi> there have have bin God knowes, and the Day will Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver: but when the Truth is <hi>fallen</hi> in the Streets, and men don't according to the rule <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 25. every man <hi>ſpeak truth</hi> to his Neighbour, I fear they have miſſed their Market. If Truth be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived into the heart <hi>in the love of it,</hi> the <hi>tongue</hi> that <hi>ſpeakes out of the abundance of the he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Mat. 12. 34. would be taught to utter Truth. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that great Command, <hi>love the</hi> Truth <hi>&amp; peace.</hi> Zech. 8. 19. and if you mean to have the <hi>latter</hi> you muſt love and uſe the <hi>former.</hi> Truth &amp; Peace <hi>come &amp; go together.</hi> Want of Truth in
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:109162:60"/>
ordinary Converſe, utterly ſpoils all Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion here; and he that loves and <hi>frames</hi> a <hi>Lye,</hi> makes a way to himſelf down to the lake which is framed and prepared for the En-Entertainment of ſuch Lyars, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1. 8. and is the place allotted to them all. <hi>Herbert</hi> well ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſeth men to <hi>dare to ſpeak truth,</hi> and adds, that <hi>nothing needs a Lye</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ide his Church Porch</note> but a <hi>Fault,</hi> and <hi>that</hi> needs it <hi>leaſt</hi> becauſe it is <hi>doubled thereby.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And O you <hi>Drunkards!</hi> Let Trembling take hold of you, eſpecially you Drunkards of <hi>Ephra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>im</hi> Iſa. 28. 1. I mean <hi>Church-Member</hi> Drunkards, I wiſh there were none ſuch that hear me this day, who either <hi>are</hi> Church-Members now, or <hi>were</hi> till diſmembred for that ſin: ſee (I ſay) unto what end one of your Companions in that ſin is brought. God ſometimes hangs up <hi>Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards</hi> in <hi>chains,</hi> as Spectacles to the world, and that by ſnatching them away by ſome untimely End: Sometimes they they fall in the Water, and are drowned, ſometimes into the fire &amp; are burned, and ſometimes by other obſervable Providences He ſets a mark on thoſe ſinners, &amp; bears His Teſtimony againſt the <hi>Sin.</hi> And it was that ſin chiefly that expoſed this poor crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to the ſin of Murder for which he is now to ſuffer. Receive Inſtruction leſt Vengeance overtake you when you are leaſt aware of it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sabbath-breaking</hi> is likewiſe a growing evil<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     <pb n="111" facs="tcp:109162:60"/>
and therefore to be teſtifyed againſt. It was that Sin which brought <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old unto Deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation. Hear <hi>this</hi> perſon telling you that he feels this ſin now lying as an inſupportable load up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him. And believe it, all that are guilty of that ſin, ſhall find it <hi>ſooner</hi> or <hi>later,</hi> alike burden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to <hi>them.</hi> As men ſpend their <hi>Sabbaths,</hi> ſo they <hi>are.</hi> The right Sanctifyer of the Sabbath is a bleſſed man, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58. 13, 14. It has bin ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved of old, that Religion lives &amp; dyes with the Sabbath. Hear this dying man bewailing <hi>his Sabbath-breaking,</hi> and if <hi>you</hi> would not bewail alſo when <hi>dying</hi> and <hi>ſuffer</hi> for it for ever, after you are <hi>dead,</hi> repent of and reform that ſin. Its worth obſerving, that this <hi>Duty</hi> of <hi>Sanctifying the Sabbath</hi> in the 4th Commandment, is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to the care and charge of <hi>Superiors</hi> and <hi>Heads</hi> of Families eſpecially. See that you ſet a good example, and require all that are under your ſhaddow to immitate you,</p>
                  <p>Whether there be any other preſent that are guilty of the the ſin of <hi>Murder</hi> God knowes. Some Acts of Murder have been done among us ſundry years ſince, the Actors whereof lye yet concealed, but let them know; if there be any ſuch, that the Lord will have a time to <hi>bring to</hi> light <hi>all the hidden works of darkneſs.</hi> The ſame hand that has delivered up <hi>this</hi> Murderer to Juſtice, will alſo find out <hi>you</hi> at ſome time or other. You may wonder that a juſt and holy
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:109162:61"/>
GOD hath ſuffered you to live all this while Happy you if this Example may awaken you, and Gods Forbearance may lead you to Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. Otherwiſe be aſſur'd that you are but <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved</hi> to be puniſhed, if not in <hi>this</hi> world, as u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually ſuch ſinners are, yet in the world <hi>to come.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To Conclude in a few words more to <hi>this</hi> Bloody Sinner.</p>
                  <p>Conſider, that all who live under the Goſpel, are brought to Jeſus the Mediator of the New-Covenant, and to the blood of <hi>ſprinkling,</hi> that ſpeaks <hi>better</hi> things than that of <hi>Abel,</hi> Heb. 12. 24. And thereupon its preſently added <hi>ver. 25<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſee that ye refuſe not him that ſpeakes from</hi> Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. <hi>Abels</hi> blood cryed for <hi>Vengeance</hi> upon the Murderer, but <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s blood cries for <hi>Pardon:</hi> and Chriſt <hi>Himſelf</hi> calls on thee to receive &amp; not refuſe Him; unto which Call if thou yeild the Obedience of Faith, His blood will ſpeak on thy behalf. Thy <hi>Sins</hi> ſpeak bitter things againſt thee, old ſins, ſins of youth, a Courſe of ſin, and this <hi>bloody</hi> ſin cries aloud &amp; <hi>ſpeaks</hi> moſt <hi>bitterly,</hi> but that blood of <hi>Chriſt</hi> can out ſpeak, <hi>out</hi>-cry all theſe. It was from Hence that <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> when under the Anguiſh of ſoul for his Blood-Guiltineſs, expected pardon and <hi>had</hi> it, and ſo mayſt thou. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.</p>
                  <p>Let thy heart leap to hear ſuch Language of this blood. Goe thy way and ſpend that little time that is left thee in ſtudying the Vileneſs of thy ſins committed, &amp; the Miſery unto which
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:109162:61"/>
thou art thereby expoſed, together with the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellence and Preciouſneſs of Jeſus Chriſt, and Him crucified, who is ready to ſave thee from Sin preſent and wrath to come. And tho' thou art not able to come, yet the glorious lifting up of Chriſt in the Goſpel, together with the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Invitation unto all that need Him, are the means appointed &amp; bleſt by God to draw Men to come.</p>
                  <p>Chriſt would fain have the Honour of ſaving ſuch a wretched Sinner as thou art, and be thou well aſſured that unleſs thou add unto that Sin of ſhedding of Man's Blood, the guilt of Refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and Slighting of Chriſt's Blood, thou ſhalt not periſh.</p>
                  <p>All the ſins that ever thou haſt committed ſhall not damn thee, unleſs thou add Unbelief to all the reſt, <hi>viz.</hi> the wilful rejecting of a tendered Saviour. There is Wrath on thee, but it ſhall not be Everlaſtingly upon thee, if thou Believe; it is Unbelief only that makes-Wrath abide, (<hi>Joh. 3. ult.</hi>) other Sins do diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe, but <hi>this</hi> only can deſtroy.</p>
                  <p>Look up to Him for the gift of Faith.</p>
                  <p>The good Lord open thine Ear, that thou may'ſt be no longer rebellious, but help thee <hi>ſo</hi> to hear as that thy Soul may live.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="addendum">
                  <pb facs="tcp:109162:62"/>
                  <div type="printer_to_the_reader">
                     <head>The Printer to the Reader.</head>
                     <p>THe general <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſefulneſs &amp; Acceptableneſs</hi> of this Book, together with the <hi>ſpeedy ſale of the 1ſt Impreſſion,</hi> as alſo ſome honeſt <hi>gain</hi> to my <hi>ſelf &amp; good</hi> to <hi>others,</hi> has enclin'd me to renew the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of it. But to render it the more <hi>compleat,</hi> I have (yet not without hazarding the diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of a <hi>worthy Friend,</hi> the Reverend <hi>Perſon</hi> who labour'd for the <hi>beſt</hi> good of the Priſoner in his <hi>laſt</hi> hours) procured (utterly againſt his <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg,</hi> I entreat him that it may be <hi>with</hi> his <hi>pardon</hi>) by an <hi>innocent Wile,</hi> the <hi>true Copy</hi> of the <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> which paſs'd between himſelf &amp; the Malefactor from the <hi>Goal</hi> to the place of <hi>Execution;</hi> judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it would contain things for the <hi>profit</hi> of the <hi>living:</hi> The <hi>laſt words</hi> of <hi>dying men</hi> being wont to leave no ſmall Impreſſions on the hearts of the <hi>ſurviving Spectators;</hi> many having bin captivated &amp; convinced, &amp; at laſt <hi>converted</hi> (with the <hi>bleſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of Heaven thereupon) by a Speech from an <hi>illiterate Malefactor</hi> at the <hi>Gallows,</hi> who have <hi>bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken</hi> the ſharp ſhining <hi>Swords</hi> of an Eloquent <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine,</hi> and <hi>laughed at the Shaking</hi> of his threatning <hi>Spear:</hi> and it being upon experience found that the Publication of the <hi>Priſon-diſcourſes</hi> between ſome <hi>other</hi> Malefactors &amp; their friends has prov'd <hi>edifying</hi> to the <hi>ſurviving.</hi> By a harmleſs Strata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem I have, as is ſaid, got into my hands a <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript</hi> of the <hi>Summ &amp; Subſtance</hi> of what was <hi>ſpoken: (drawn up, for ought I know, for the Author's own uſe, or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſatisfaction of ſome of his private friends, who I know have ask'd him to do it)</hi> it is as <hi>follows.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>R. P.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="dialogue">
                     <pb facs="tcp:109162:62"/>
                     <head>The <hi>DISCO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RSE</hi> of the MINISTER with <hi>James Morgan</hi> on the <hi>WAY</hi> to his <hi>Execution.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>I'm come hither to anſwer your deſires which juſt now you expreſt to me in the</hi> Church, <hi>that I would give you my company at your Execution.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Morg.</speaker>
                        <p>Dear Sir, how much am I beholden to you! you have already done a great deal for me. Oh <hi>who am</hi> I that have bin ſuch a <hi>vile wretch</hi> that any Servants of God ſhould take notice of me!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>I beſeech you to make</hi> this <hi>uſe of it, I believe there is not one</hi> Chriſtian <hi>this day beholding you, who would not willingly be at the greateſt pains they could deviſe to ſave your precious ſoul: How merciful then is that</hi> Man <hi>who is</hi> God <hi>as well as man! how unſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kably ready is the Ld. Chriſt to ſave the ſouls of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners that affectionately</hi> look <hi>unto him! The goodneſs &amp; pittifulneſs of the moſt tender-hearted man in the world is but a ſhadow of what is in</hi> Him. <hi>The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſions of any man compared with the Bowels of a merciful</hi> JESUS <hi>are but as the</hi> painted <hi>Sun, or the</hi> painted Fire <hi>in Compariſon of the</hi> real.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mor.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh that I could now look unto Him as I ought to do! Lord help me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Well, you are now a</hi> dying <hi>man, the</hi> laſt <hi>hour or 2 of your life is now running. You know your ſelf now to ſtand juſt on the brink of Eternity, you ſhall preſently be in a ſtate of wonderful happineſs or of horrible miſery which muſt endure forever: which of thoſe eſtates do you new count your ſelf ſtepping into?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="116" facs="tcp:109162:63"/>
                        <speaker>Mor.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh Sir, I am afraid, but I am not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hope that God may have mercy on me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                        <p>Whats your ground for that hope? O ſee that your confidences been'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> ſuch as God willby'nd by reject.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mor.</speaker>
                        <p>I don't know well what to ſay, but <hi>this</hi> I hope is a good ſign, I have lived in many grieve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſins, in <hi>Lying, Drinking, Sabbath-breaking</hi> &amp; evil <hi>Company-keeping;</hi> God has made <hi>now</hi> theſe ſo <hi>bitter</hi> to my ſoul, that I would not commit them <hi>again,</hi> might I have <hi>my life this afternoon by doing it.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>That's a great word, God grant it may not be a word only, the good word of a good</hi> pang, <hi>without a through chang of</hi> heart, <hi>as you</hi> muſt <hi>have if you would not periſh</hi> everlaſtingly <hi>You are not like to have any longer time in this world to</hi> try the Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity of your Profeſſion.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mor.</speaker>
                        <p>I know it, and I beſeech you Sir to help me what you can: I hope the means uſed with me ſince my Condemnation ha'n't been loſt.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>I would not have the ſenſe of the pain &amp; ſhame which your</hi> Body <hi>is about to undergoe, any waies hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your</hi> Mind <hi>from being taken up about the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matters which I ſhall endeavour to ſet before you.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mor.</speaker>
                        <p>Sir, as for the <hi>pain</hi> that my <hi>body</hi> muſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently feel I matter it not: I know what pain is; but <hi>what ſhall I do</hi> for my poor <hi>ſoul?</hi> I'm <hi>terrify'd</hi> with the Wrath of <hi>GOD;</hi> This, <hi>this</hi> terrifyes me, <hi>HELL</hi> terrifyes me: I ſhould not <hi>mind</hi> my <hi>Death,</hi> if it were not for that.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Now the</hi> Lord <hi>help me to deal faithfully with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ou, &amp; the</hi> Lord <hi>help</hi> you <hi>to</hi> receive <hi>what He ſhall
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:109162:63"/>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>able</hi> me <hi>to offer unto you. Mark what I ſay: You were born among y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> enemies of God, you were born with a ſoul as full of</hi> emnity <hi>againſt God as a Toad is full of poiſon. You have liv'd now—how many years?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Morg.</speaker>
                        <p>I think about Thirty.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>And</hi> all <hi>theſe 30 years have you been ſinning againſt the holy God. Ever ſince you knew how to do</hi> any <hi>thing, you have every day bin guilty of innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſins: you deſerve the dreadful wrath &amp; curſe of the infinite God. But God has brought you here, to a place where you have enjoy's the means of grace<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And here you have added unto your</hi> old <hi>Sins, moſt fearful Iniquityes: you have bin ſuch a matchleſs, prodigious Tranſgreſſor, that you are now to</hi> dye <hi>by the ſtroke of civil Juſtice; to</hi> dy before your time, <hi>for</hi> being wicked over much. <hi>There is hardly any ſort of Wickedneſs which you have not wallowed in-That ſin particularly which you are now to die for, is a moſt</hi> monſtrous <hi>Crime. I can't poſſibly</hi> deſcribe <hi>or declare the ſins whereby you have made your ſelf an aſtoniſhing Example of Impiety &amp; puniſhment.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mor.</speaker>
                        <p>O Sir, I have bin a moſt helliſh ſinner<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I am ſorry for what I have bin.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Sorry you ſay: well, tell me which of all your ſins you are now</hi> moſt <hi>ſorry for: which lyes moſt heavy?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mor.</speaker>
                        <p>I hope I am ſorry for <hi>all</hi> my ſins, but I muſt eſpecially bewail my <hi>neglect</hi> of the <hi>means</hi> of <hi>grace.</hi> On Sabbath dayes I us'd to lye at home, or be ill imploy'd elſewhere when I ſhould have bin at Church. <hi>This</hi> has undone me!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="118" facs="tcp:109162:64"/>
                        <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>And let me ſeriously tell you, Your</hi> Deſpiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſt is a moſt dreadful ſin indeed. <hi>You have, for whole</hi> years <hi>together had the Call of</hi> Jeſus Chriſt <hi>to ſeek an</hi> Intereſt <hi>in him, &amp; you would</hi> now <hi>give all the</hi> world <hi>for that</hi> intereſt, <hi>but you</hi> would take no notice <hi>of him. The</hi> Jews <hi>of Old put him to a</hi> worſe <hi>death than</hi> yours <hi>will be this</hi> afternoon, <hi>and by</hi> your <hi>contempt of Chriſt you have ſaid,</hi> the Jews did <hi>well</hi> to do ſo. <hi>How</hi> juſtly <hi>might he now</hi> Laugh at your Calamity? <hi>And for theſe ſins of</hi> yours, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the</hi> direful woes &amp; plagues <hi>that have</hi> already <hi>come upon you,</hi> you <hi>are</hi> now <hi>expoſ'd unto the</hi> Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance of eternal fire. <hi>You are in danger of being now quickly caſt into thoſe exquiſite amazing</hi> Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>in compariſon of which, the anguiſhes which your</hi> body <hi>ever</hi> did <hi>feel, or</hi> ſhall <hi>feel before night, or</hi> can ever <hi>feel, are juſt nothing at all; and theſe</hi> do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorous torments <hi>are</hi> ſuch <hi>as</hi> never <hi>have an</hi> End; <hi>as many</hi> ſands <hi>as could lie between this</hi> earth &amp; <hi>the</hi> Stars <hi>in Heaven would not be</hi> near <hi>ſo many as the</hi> Ages, <hi>the</hi> end-leſs Ages <hi>of theſe</hi> Torments.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mor.</speaker>
                        <p>But is there not Mercy for me in Chriſt?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Yes, and its a</hi> wonderful <hi>thing that I have now further to tell you: Mind, I entreat you. The</hi> SON of GOD <hi>is become the</hi> Son <hi>of</hi> Man; <hi>the</hi> Lord Jeſus Chriſt <hi>is both</hi> God &amp; <hi>man in</hi> one Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, <hi>&amp; he is both ſufficiently able &amp; willing alſo, to be</hi> your Saviour. <hi>He lived a moſt</hi> righteous <hi>life, and this was that ſuch as</hi> you &amp; I <hi>might be able to ſay before God,</hi> Lord, accept of me as if <hi>I</hi> had
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:109162:64"/>
liv'd righteouſly. <hi>He died at length a moſt</hi> curſed death, <hi>and this was that we might be able to ſay un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God,</hi> Lord, let not <hi>me die</hi> for ſin, ſince thy <hi>Son</hi> has died in my room. <hi>This glorious Redeemer is now in the higheſt heaven, pleading with God for the Salvation of His choſen ones.—And He</hi> pours out his Spirit continually upon <hi>them</hi> that do <hi>believe</hi> on him: <hi>might</hi> you <hi>then be enabled by his</hi> grace <hi>to carry your poor, guilty, condemned, enſlaved, ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant</hi> ſoul <hi>unto</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>and humbly put your truſt in him for deliverance from the</hi> whole <hi>bad ſtate which you are</hi> brought into. <hi>Oh then his voice is to</hi> you <hi>the ſame that was to the penitent Thief,</hi> This day ſhalt thou be with me in <hi>Paradiſe.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mor.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh that <hi>I</hi> might be ſo! Sir I would hear more of <hi>theſe things:</hi> I think, I can't <hi>better fit</hi> my ſelf for my <hi>death</hi> than by <hi>hearkning</hi> to <hi>theſe things.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Attend then: The</hi> never-dying <hi>ſpirit that</hi> lodges <hi>within you, muſt</hi> now <hi>within a few</hi> minutes <hi>appear before the</hi> Tribunal <hi>of the Great</hi> GOD; <hi>in</hi> what, <hi>or in</hi> whoſe Righteouſneſs <hi>will you then ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear? will you have this to be your Plea,</hi> Lord, I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced many good Motions &amp; Deſires in my ſoul, &amp; many Sorrows for my <hi>ſin</hi> before I dy'd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                           <hi>or will you expect to have</hi> no other <hi>Plea but</hi> This, Lord, <hi>I</hi> am <hi>vile,</hi> but thy Son is a <hi>Surety</hi> for the <hi>worſt</hi> of <hi>ſinners</hi> that <hi>believe</hi> in him; for <hi>his</hi> ſake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, have MERCY on me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Morg.</speaker>
                        <p>I thank God for what He has wrought in my Soul<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>—</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="120" facs="tcp:109162:65"/>
                        <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>But be very careful about this matter: if you build</hi> on your own good Affections inſtead of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt the only Rock, <hi>if you think</hi> they <hi>ſhall recommend you to God,</hi> He that <hi>made</hi> you will not have mercy on you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mor.</speaker>
                        <p>I would be clothed with the Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of JESUS CHRIST.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Min</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>But you can't ſincerely deſire that Chriſt ſhould</hi> juſtify you, <hi>if you don't</hi> alſo <hi>deſire that He ſhould</hi> ſanctify you: <hi>thoſe 2 alwaies</hi> go together. <hi>Is ev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> luſt <hi>that has hitherto had</hi> poſſeſſion <hi>of your heart become ſo</hi> loathſom <hi>to you, that it would fill your ſoul with</hi> joy <hi>to hear Jeſus Chriſt ſay,</hi> I will ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due thoſe Iniquities of thine; I will make a ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, heavenly, a ſpiritually minded perſon of <hi>thee.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mor.</speaker>
                        <p>I would ſin againſt God no more.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>But I muſt deal</hi> plainly <hi>with you: You have made it</hi> ſadly ſuſpicious <hi>that your repentance is not yet as it</hi> ought to be: <hi>when men truly &amp; throughly repent of ſin they uſe to be in a ſpecial manner watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful againſt</hi> that Sin <hi>which has bin their</hi> chief Sin: <hi>one of your</hi> principal <hi>ſins which has indeed brought</hi> you <hi>to the Death of a</hi> Murderer, <hi>is</hi> Paſſion, <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortifi'd &amp; outragious</hi> Paſſionateneſs: <hi>Now I have been this day informed, that no longer ſince than the laſt night,</hi> upon ſome Diſſatisfaction about the <hi>place</hi> which the Authority hath ordered you by and by to be <hi>buried</hi> in, <hi>you did expreſs your ſelf with a moſt unruly</hi> Paſſionateneſs.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mor.</speaker>
                        <p>Sir, I confeſs it, and I was <hi>quickly</hi> ſorry
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:109162:65"/>
for it, tho' for the preſent I was too much di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed: 'Twas my folly to be ſo careful about the place where my <hi>body</hi> ſhould be laid when my precious SOUL was in ſuch a Condition.—</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Truly you have cauſe to</hi> mourn <hi>for it. Secure the welfarre of your</hi> ſoul, <hi>and this (now)</hi> pinion'd, <hi>hang'd</hi> vile body of yours <hi>will ſhortly</hi> be raiſed <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to glory,</hi> glory forevermore. <hi>And let me put you in mind of</hi> one thing <hi>more, I doubt you han't</hi> yet <hi>laid aſide your</hi> unjuſt Grudges <hi>againſt the Perſons concerned in</hi> your Conviction &amp; Condemnation: <hi>You have</hi> no <hi>cauſe to complain of them: and you are not fit to pray, much leſs are you fit to</hi> dye <hi>till you heartily wiſh them as well as</hi> your own ſoul: <hi>if you die</hi> malicious, <hi>you die</hi> miſerable.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mor.</speaker>
                        <p>I heartily wiſh them all <hi>well,</hi> I bear <hi>Ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will</hi> to none—What a lamentable thing is <hi>this,</hi> Ah <hi>this</hi> is that which has brought me hither!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                        <p>What do you mean?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mor.</speaker>
                        <p>I over-heard a man mocking &amp; ſcoffing at me when I <hi>ſtumbled</hi> juſt now, he does very ill. <hi>I</hi> have done ſo my <hi>ſelf: I</hi> have mock'd &amp; ſcoff'd like that man, and ſee what it hath brought <hi>me</hi> to: <hi>he</hi> may come to the like.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>The</hi> Lord forgive <hi>that fooliſh hard-hearted creature. But be not</hi> too much <hi>diſturbed.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mor.</speaker>
                        <p>Yonder! I am now come in ſight of the <hi>place</hi> where I muſt <hi>immediately end</hi> my dayes. Oh what a huge Multitude of people is come toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on this occaſion! O Lord, O Lord I pray
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:109162:66"/>
thee to make my Death profitable to all this Multitude of People, that they may not <hi>ſin</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee as I have done!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Amen, Amen</hi> ten thouſand <hi>times; the Lord GOD Allmighty ſay Amen to this</hi> Prayer <hi>of yours! It would indeed be an excellent thing if you could now come to receive your death with ſome Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of</hi> ſoul <hi>in this thought, That</hi> Much Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is like to come to God by it: <hi>I am verily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded God intends to</hi> do good <hi>to</hi> many ſouls <hi>by means of</hi> your Execution: <hi>This is a</hi> greater ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour <hi>than you are worthy of.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>[After the Diſcourſe had been intermitted about a <hi>minute or two by reaſon of the</hi> miery <hi>way</hi>]</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mor.</speaker>
                        <p>I beſeech you Sir ſpeak to me. Do me all the good you can: my time grows very ſhort: your diſcourſe <hi>fits</hi> me for my Death more than any thing.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>I'm ſorry ſo ſmall a thing as a</hi> plaſhy Street <hi>ſhould make me looſe one minute of this</hi> more-than-ordinary <hi>precious time: a few paces</hi> more <hi>bring you to the place which you have now in your</hi> eye, <hi>from whence you ſhall not</hi> come back alive. <hi>Do you find your ſelf</hi> afraid to dy <hi>there?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mor.</speaker>
                        <p>Sir, If it were not for the Condition that my SOUL muſt by &amp; by be in, I ſhould not fear my death at <hi>all;</hi> but I have a little comfort from ſome of Gods promiſes about <hi>that.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>And what ſhall I now ſay? Theſe are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:109162:66"/>
the</hi> laſt words <hi>that I can have</hi> liberty <hi>to leave with you. Poor man, thou art now going to</hi> knock at the door <hi>of Heaven, and to beg &amp;</hi> cry, Lord, Lord open to me! <hi>The only way for thee to ſpeed, is,</hi> to open the door of thy own ſoul now unto <hi>the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Do this, <hi>and thou ſhalt</hi> undoubtedly <hi>be admitted into</hi> the gloryes of His heavenly Kingdom: <hi>You ſhall fare as well as</hi> Manaſſeh <hi>did before you: leave this undone, and there's nothing remains for you but</hi> the Worm which dyeth not, <hi>and</hi> the fire which ſhall not be quenched.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mor.</speaker>
                        <p>Sir, ſhow me then <hi>again</hi> what I have to do.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>The voice, the ſweet voice of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, (who was once</hi> hanged on a tree, <hi>to take away the</hi> Sting <hi>and</hi> Curfe <hi>of even ſuch a Death as</hi> yours) <hi>unto all that</hi> cloſe <hi>with him, His heavenly voice now is,</hi> Oh that <hi>I</hi> &amp; my Saving work might be entertained, kindly entreated, in that poor, periſhing ſoul of thine! <hi>Are you willing?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Morg.</speaker>
                        <p>I hope I am.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>His Voice further is,</hi> If <hi>I</hi> am lodged in thy ſoul <hi>I</hi>'ll ſprinkle my blood upon it, and on <hi>my</hi> account thou ſhalt find Favour with GOD. <hi>Do you conſent to this?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mor.</speaker>
                        <p>This I want.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>But this is not</hi> all <hi>that he ſaith, His Voice further is,</hi> If <hi>I</hi> come into thy ſoul I will <hi>chang</hi> it, I will make all <hi>ſin bitter</hi> to it, I will make it an holy heavenly ſoul. <hi>Do you value this above
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:109162:67"/>
the proffers of all the World?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mor.</speaker>
                        <p>I think I doe,—and now, Sir, I muſt go no further, Look <hi>here</hi>—what a <hi>ſolemn ſight</hi> is <hi>this!</hi> Here lyes the <hi>Coffin</hi> which this Body of mine muſt preſently be laid in. I <hi>thank</hi> you dear Sir, for what you have already done for me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>When you are gone up this Ladder, my laſt ſervice for you before you are gone off will be to</hi> pray <hi>with you: But I would here take my leave of you. Oh that I might meet you at the right Hand of the LORD JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S in the laſt Day! Farewel</hi> poor heart, <hi>Fare thee well.</hi> The everlaſting Armes receive thee! The Lord JESUS, the merciful SAVIOUR of Souls take poſſeſſion of thy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit for himſelf. The Great GOD who is a <hi>great Forgiver,</hi> grant thee <hi>Repentance unto Life;</hi> and glorify himſelf in the Salvation of ſuch a <hi>wounded</hi> ſoul as thine forever. <hi>With HIM, and with His free, rich, marvellous, infinite Grace, I leave you;</hi> Farewell.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:109162:67"/>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
